<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thememeticist.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thememeticist.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-14T18:04:20+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Memeticist</title><subtitle>Memes worth spreading </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Case for Education</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/08/14/the-case-for-education.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Case for Education" /><published>2020-08-14T10:37:47+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-14T10:37:47+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/08/14/the-case-for-education</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/08/14/the-case-for-education.html">&lt;p&gt;I discovered the rationalist community two years ago. I had just dropped out of college, was looking for a software engineering job in London, and was in the process of getting what would become &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2018/11/23/the-case-for-dropping-out-of-college/?v=322b26af01d5&quot;&gt;The Case for Dropping Out of College&lt;/a&gt; published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my research for the piece, I had stumbled on &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/06/06/against-tulip-subsidies/&quot;&gt;Against Tulip Subsidies&lt;/a&gt; on Slate Star Codex. I found the post brilliant, and the couple of other posts I then read seemed equally insightful. The site also listed meetups, and so I decided to go to one which was organized by the 'London Rationalish' group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The people I found there were welcoming, but I was suffering of mild impostor syndrome. At that time, I had only read a handful of SSC posts, and if I recall correctly, I wasn't even aware of the existence of LessWrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the fact that many there had advanced degrees didn't help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I greatly enjoyed the discussions. I had been interested in EA for at least two years before that and consumed some rationalist-adjacent content such as Sam Harris' podcast, —where I first encountered Yudkowsky. I've also had a long-running interest in psychology, physics, and economics. So, I did end up feeling quite at home culturally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the first meetup I attended, I told people my story. I explained why I had dropped out of college, and the conclusions I had come to about the education system in general. I was a little surprised when I was met with near-universal agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it quite validating and reassuring. I felt alienated at the time. I felt betrayed by society for keeping up with such a system. I felt doubt, because what are the odds that I had understood the problem, while all the people in charge were all oblivious? I was quite confident in my object-level model, but the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/dhj9dhiwhq3DX6W8z/hero-licensing&quot;&gt;argument from modesty&lt;/a&gt; still made me wonder whether there was something out there that would prove me wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So meeting a group of young highly educated adults who all more or less agreed with me was comforting. But it was also a bit disconcerting. There was something bizarre about finding a group of people who all disavowed the institutions of higher education, while also having spent so much time within them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not that there would be anything irrational about it. From an individual perspective, it makes sense to go to college. College may be largely about a zero-sum competition for credentials, but little is achieved by single individuals forgoing getting a college degree. Education is in a bad Nash equilibrium, and only governmental action or mass coordination can get us out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I broadly agree with this position (unlike what the slightly misleading title of my &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2018/11/23/the-case-for-dropping-out-of-college/&quot;&gt;Quillette piece&lt;/a&gt; might suggest). But there still is something about this that doesn't sit right with me. An attitude that I have now encountered a few times after having explained that I dropped out of college because it was expensive and I wasn't learning much is something like, &quot;but haven't you heard of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Case-against-Education-System-Waste/dp/0691196451/&quot;&gt;Caplan's work&lt;/a&gt;? You have to go to college, or you won't get the signaling.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some truth to this, but there is something seriously going wrong when the very people who believe that education is in a bad Nash equilibrium become de facto enforcers of the status quo. Shouldn't EA and rationality be about overcoming this kind of situation? Why have there not been more attempts to bust smart nerds out of the hands of &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/07/30/meditations-on-moloch/&quot;&gt;Moloch&lt;/a&gt;? To help them escape the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/s/kNANcHLNtJt5qeuSS/p/bQ7BKK5efogcR9YqN&quot;&gt;immoral maze&lt;/a&gt; that is the current higher education system?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes this more depressing is that many of the most prominent EAs are working in higher education, and young EAs are generally advised to gain career capital in the form of university credentials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, organizations like 80k and GiveWell generally advise against trying to improve education. In their &lt;a href=&quot;https://80000hours.org/problem-profiles/&quot;&gt;problem profiles page&lt;/a&gt;, 80k presents about 40 problem areas. Not one of them is about education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how can it be that EAs see so much wrong with the education system, while also spending so much time in university—and then not see improving education as a cause with a great potential to do good? Shouldn't education be an area with a significant amount of leverage?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many people have to recognize that higher education is seriously dysfunctional before they should try to coordinate an exit? At what point does a fatalistic attitude vis-a-vis improvements of the education system become a self-fulfilling prophecy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many people need to recognize this prisoner's dilemma before they stop defecting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Case For Education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&quot;Education is the process through which the body of knowledge and culture that we have been accumulating for thousands of years passes from our generation to the next one.&quot;&lt;/em&gt; -&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/fchollet/status/1278857519784292352&quot;&gt;Francois Chollet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's easy to become cynical about higher education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I hear praise for the promises and virtues of education I often roll my eyes. Not because I disagree that education has the potential to change the world for the better, but because the institutions that people are defending by making vague idealistic statements about education are doing a terrible job at providing an education that actually has a positive impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let me now make the case &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education is key to civilizational sanity, sensemaking, and survival. Education is key to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Secret-Our-Success-Evolution-Domesticating/dp/0691178437/&quot;&gt;The Secret of our Success&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education is the &lt;em&gt;scaffolding&lt;/em&gt; on which our society, culture and civilization are built and maintained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first two or three decades of people's lives, they are taken on a guided tour of what humanity has learned and achieved. They are taught the laws that govern our universe, how these laws gave rise to life on earth, and ultimately led to the ascent of our species. They are instructed in the history of the ideas that shaped the trajectory of human civilization, the mistakes made along the way, and the principles of rational thought that have allowed the best ideas to win out. They are introduced to the institutions that form the bedrock of society and have allowed the current generation to live in relative prosperity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And as they learn about the world, and their place in it, they are also shown the construction sites and &lt;a href=&quot;https://equilibriabook.com/&quot;&gt;inadequacies&lt;/a&gt; of our budding collective project so they will be able to contribute to maintaining and improving on what previous generations have built. And so, just as 20,000 years ago, the information needed for the survival and thriving of a hunter-gatherer tribe was transmitted from generation to generation, today the ideas, information and skills necessary for civilizational sanity and the survival of our species continue to be transmitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me be more specific. There are two areas for which education is needed in the modern world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first is economic growth. Education increases human capital and allows people to be more productive. The success of an economy depends on the ability of its participants to create value for others, and it is the acquisition of knowledge and skills, as well as the discovery of new ideas, that allow this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus many economists believe that in order to come out of the slump in productivity growth that has afflicted advanced economies in the past few decades, education is key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where these same economists are often &lt;a href=&quot;https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2018/04/21/the-case-against-education-foundations/&quot;&gt;led astray&lt;/a&gt; is in thinking that the solution lies in sending more people to college. The problem being that college has largely turned into a zero-sum competition for credentials, rather than being a place where people learn valuable skills and information that would allow them to succeed in the modern economy. Only a minority of college graduates get to use much of what they learned in college in their professional life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Critics of this view often appeal to the second area where education is useful—&lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/11/education-public-good.html&quot;&gt;the public good of an educated citizenry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an important point often overlooked by detractors of the education system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory, a zero-sum competition for credentials can be worth it even if it doesn't lead to the acquisition of skills useful on the labor market if it leads to the positive externality of creating citizens who will productively contribute to resolving problem areas that are left unsolved (or even caused) by free markets. Whether it is by voting, the choice of a career, public service, charitable giving… people have great power to contribute to human flourishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, an education that is not only job training is crucial for a well-functioning society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But once again, looking through this lens, the current institutions of higher education perform quite poorly. College grads know little about public affairs, are taught even less about how they might have a positive impact on the world, and even the most prestigious universities—priding themselves on educating the next generation of leaders—seem more set on &lt;a href=&quot;https://palladiummag.com/2020/07/27/harvard-creates-managers-instead-of-elites/&quot;&gt;creating mid-level managers than an elite that can take on the responsibility of contributing to human progress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No wonder &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/12/trillion-dollar-bills.html&quot;&gt;trillion-dollar bills are regularly left on the sidewalk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if education is so important, why do EA orgs like 80k and GiveWell recommend against working to improve it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isn't what I have discussed above exactly what EA is all about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the simple answer is that EA and the rationalist community are in fact working to fix education. It's just that there is an implicit understanding in EA and rationalist orgs that the institutions that are conventionally thought to be responsible for providing an education are too broken to be fixed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, you don't get involved in EA or LW by eschewing learning. Quite the contrary. There are few communities that value their education more. One of the most up-voted posts on LessWrong is titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/xg3hXCYQPJkwHyik2/the-best-textbooks-on-every-subject&quot;&gt;The Best Textbooks on Every Subject&lt;/a&gt;. One of the most up-voted posts on the EA Forum is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/bsE5t6qhGC65fEpzN/growth-and-the-case-against-randomista-development&quot;&gt;long post&lt;/a&gt; describing the academic literature on the importance of economic growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EA orgs don't think that improving education is an important cause because they are the ones providing the education necessary for people to understand how they can positively contribute to the thriving of our species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, many EA and rationalist organizations are effectively trying to compensate for some failure of the higher education system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LW was created to teach people how to think more rationally, and to draw attention to an issue—AI alignment—that has been neglected in academic circles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MIRI is doing research in AI alignment that isn't being done in universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RAISE and AI safety camp were also created to support people trying to contribute to technical AI safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CFAR pursues LW's mission to help people think more rationally and helps them to think strategically about how to achieve what they aim to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;80k is effectively &quot;career services&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://ceealar.org/&quot;&gt;EA Hotel&lt;/a&gt; allows people to self-study, do independent research, and it gives people the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/yLLkWMDbC9ZNKbjDG/slack&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt; they need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charity entrepreneurship helps EAs create high-impact charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of other organizations also do research that is important but isn't being done within academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why not go all the way? For how much longer will young EAs and rationalists have to navigate the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/6NrnyjzRby5MBewSp/survival-in-the-immoral-maze-of-college&quot;&gt;immoral maze that is the education system&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current strategy that EA orgs seem to be pursuing is to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.effectivealtruism.org/articles/ea-neoliberal/&quot;&gt;imitate the success of neoliberalism&lt;/a&gt;. That is, gaining the respect of academic institutions, and thus increasing its influence among elite circles. But why should EA try to gain the respect of institutions that themselves don't deserve any?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, what I suggest is that EA starts aiming to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/s/kNANcHLNtJt5qeuSS/p/NerqNs3nfAkcJauWE&quot;&gt;Create a Full Alternative Stack&lt;/a&gt;. That is, replacing the current higher education institutions entirely. That would mean creating the space for learning and research that isn't subject to the traditional academic incentives. A space in which young people don't have to ask themselves what they have to do to get their degree, but one where their learning would be guided by the question of how they can become successful while contributing to human flourishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons 80k &lt;a href=&quot;https://80000hours.org/2017/01/5-reasons-not-to-go-into-education/&quot;&gt;lists&lt;/a&gt; in arguing against focusing on education is that the field is neither neglected nor tractable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I go into how this issue might be tractable, and what concrete steps I recommend, I will explain why I think this issue is neglected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is true that hundreds of billions are spent every year on education in the US alone. However, the organizations spending this money show very little understanding of why the education system is broken, work from misguided assumptions (like the blank slate ideology), and demonstrate even less creativity in how they go about trying to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fixing education will require a radical rethinking of how education is approached and what is taught. And the key to answering these questions lies in the Why of education. What is it for? This question is what EA is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason this question is so important is that much of education is all about the motivation of the students. One of the main roles of professors is to provide students with incentives to learn. Homework, exams, grades, and the authoritative presence of a professor—to the extent that they enable learning—do so by helping the student overcome akrasia. The struggle that even if one actually wants to learn a subject, putting in the work necessary through sheer will power can be incredibly difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that by providing a student with the ultimate purpose of their education, some incredible gains in efficiencies are possible. To &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/end-of-education.html&quot;&gt;quote Neil Postman&lt;/a&gt;, there is a &quot;fundamental simplicity [in] teaching and learning when both teacher and student share a reason for the enterprise.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No wonder EAs and rationalists tend to be lifelong learners. When your education might contribute to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/F2DZXsMdhGyX4FPAd/on-saving-the-world&quot;&gt;saving the world&lt;/a&gt;, a teacher is often not even necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, concretely, what do I suggest should be done?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons I'm frustrated with how little effort has been put into fixing the education system by those who understand why it is broken is that I believe the solution lies to a large extent in the for-profit sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside this post, I am publishing two others. In the first I describe my very positive experience self-studying ML at the EA Hotel. In the second, I describe my plan to start a for-profit project inspired by the EA Hotel, for people to study and do independent ML research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because I believe that replacing the current institutions will require a two-pronged approach. First it will require &lt;em&gt;the creation of learning communities where people can go and find peer support and accountability.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second prong is &lt;em&gt;the creation of comprehensive standardized exams&lt;/em&gt; to replace the signaling provided by a college degree (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/05/what-i-learned-dropping-out-of-high-school.html&quot;&gt;What I Learned Dropping Out of High School&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have encountered some skepticism about the potential of such exams to compete with college degrees, despite the fact that such exams have the potential to be up to two orders of magnitude cheaper than a college degree. But I find it easy to imagine how a &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/10/pinker-on-education.html&quot;&gt;Pinker degree of Psychology&lt;/a&gt;, a Marginal Revolution degree of economics, or a MIRI degree in AI Safety would successfully challenge the dominance of college degrees while also making a profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the very least, creating such exams and degrees would demonstrate the dysfunctional nature of the higher education system in a more convincing way than Thiel fellowships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LW community has gotten a few things very right in the past decade. Seeing the potential of crypto was one, taking the threat of COVID-19 seriously earlier than most was another, and I believe that education will turn out to be a third. I just hope that, if I'm right, this community will take better advantage of this opportunity &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/MajyZJrsf8fAywWgY/a-lesswrong-crypto-autopsy&quot;&gt;than it did with crypto&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, existing EA orgs and initiatives such as AI safety camp, CFAR, and the EA Hotel can be given more funding and expanded. I think that, for example, a permanent AI safety camp would give young talented aspiring AI safety researchers the slack to self-study, do independent research, and prepare for a career in AI safety research. A MIRI AI safety degree (or whatever organization might create such a thing) would also provide those who fail to get a job in this field with something to show for their effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I'm a bit nervous about publishing this. After all, I am making two bold claims here: first that EA should change its macro strategy (i.e. stop following the neoliberal playbook), and second that there is a lot of wealth to be created by disrupting an education system that has proven immune to large changes for more than a century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I understand if people reading this might have reservations. However, even though creating a full alternative to college might sound radical, I think none of the projects and initiatives I propose above seem to be that drastic or have a big downside risk. At the same time, the potential upsides are enormous. Not only do I think that there is a chance to create a great deal of wealth with for-profit initiatives, but there might also be the potential to influence new educational institutions, and expose a new generation of talented youth to EA and rationalist ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last thought. I don't want young people facing the decision of pursuing a college education to think that they should boycott the education system at their own expense. I'm still not sure if my own decision of dropping out of college was the right one. However, I did notice that in most EA and rationalist circles, at least, my decision and my write-up explaining my decision seem to be a &lt;em&gt;stronger&lt;/em&gt; signal of competence than a B.S. degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, if you think there is a good chance that the current educational system will be exposed for what it really has become within the next decade, then it might be in your long-term self-interest to quit now. The first ones leaving a sinking ship might be frowned upon at first, but once the gaping holes in the hull become apparent to everyone, they will be praised for their foresight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hope is that this will turn out to be a self-fulfilling prophecy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably the most important lesson I have learned from the EA and LW community is that individual actions matter. That we shouldn't take the world as it is for granted. That changing things for the better is possible. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/ham9i5wf4JCexXnkN/moloch-hasn-t-won&quot;&gt;Moloch Hasn't Won&lt;/a&gt;. So let's not act as if the war has already been lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you to everyone at &lt;a href=&quot;https://ceealar.org/&quot;&gt;CEELAR&lt;/a&gt; (EA Hotel) for their useful input. I’m especially grateful for the feedback from Kris Gulati, David Kristofferson, Rhys Southan and Michele Campolo.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">I discovered the rationalist community two years ago. I had just dropped out of college, was looking for a software engineering job in London, and was in the process of getting what would become The Case for Dropping Out of College published.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Room and Board for People Self-Learning ML or Doing Independent ML Research</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/08/14/room-and-board.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Room and Board for People Self-Learning ML or Doing Independent ML Research" /><published>2020-08-14T10:37:46+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-14T10:37:46+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/08/14/room-and-board</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/08/14/room-and-board.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/08/14/room-and-board.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Important context.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently planning to rent a large house in northern England, somewhere rents are affordable, for people to study or to research machine learning. ML seems to be an obvious initial choice. I believe that the model of getting a group of smart, somewhat self-motivated people under one roof to work on or study a particular topic, to give them some structure, peer support and accountability, and then to validate progress being made by means of comprehensive standardized exams, is one that could work for any subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But since, today already, it is possible to get into ML without traditional qualifications, creating a comprehensive exam isn't really necessary. &lt;a href=&quot;https://triplebyte.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Triplebyte&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, an American company, has even created something similar already: a background-blind test and interview that places successful candidates directly to the last interview of ML or other programming roles at partnering companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All people need is a place to study, work on projects, compete in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kaggle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; competitions, prepare for interviews or do &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@andreas_madsen/becoming-an-independent-researcher-and-getting-published-in-iclr-with-spotlight-c93ef0b39b8b&quot;&gt;independent research&lt;/a&gt;. The network effect alone of such a place would probably be incredible. And that would be possible at a significantly lower price than university or bootcamps alike. And for anyone feeling about university and bootcamps as I do, such an environment would also provide a significantly better learning experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key is to attract people who treat their own education as volunteers rather than grudging conscripts, to create the right supportive social environment and productivity norms, and to have an accountability system that would allow everyone to live up to their own ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concrete steps that can be taken to create such an environment are subject to iterative experimentation and improvement. A few ideas: having people write down their goals before arriving, regular one-on-one meetings to discuss progress, productivity and difficulties, encouraging work in public spaces, a weekly event to discuss research papers, communal dinners…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the real innovation here is cultural. The revolutionary potential I see in such a place is not based on some great education technology or new teaching method, but on the expectations of the residents. Expectations of themselves and of others. Expensive and mediocre educational institutions have created the belief among many that learning requires some rigid ritual of lectures, assignments and tests. Those who see past this illusion have the potential to transform our understanding of what an education entails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in coming to such a place, believe that others would benefit from this project getting off the ground, would consider investing, or just believe that such a place should exist, I invite you to add your information &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSfcb_8PijSmP69-rw1pdr2ZnHEsFK_weApyWzRa9maiF6PCeQ/viewform?usp=sf_link&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and to share this widely. This becoming a reality will depend on it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">Important context.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Best Educational Institution in the World</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/08/14/the-best-educational-institution.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Best Educational Institution in the World" /><published>2020-08-14T10:37:45+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-14T10:37:45+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/08/14/the-best-educational-institution</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/08/14/the-best-educational-institution.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: I originally intended to publish this at the end of February. I decided to hold off until now because of COVID-19.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would happen to college dorms if all colleges disappeared? Imagine some crazy parallel Universe in which the US government decided to disband all institutions of higher learning: All professors and administrators get fired, all classes are canceled, nowhere to turn anymore to get a university degree, yet all student housing remains open. What happens next? What will this crowd of young adults do? Just a day earlier they were college students with assignments, schedules, exams… Just a day earlier, they were living under the watchful eye of campus security and residential assistants. Now, they are all slammed from their state of extended childhood straight into adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe they would start by throwing a giant party. Not necessarily because they would be happy that this track, that society had laid out for them to mindlessly follow, suddenly had disappeared, but because that is what college students do when they have nothing else to do. And with no one to stop them if the music became too loud, or if people started to become visibly intoxicated, the temptation would probably be too great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, as the hangovers would pass, these former college students would have to decide what would come next. What would they want to do with their lives? Many would probably move back in with their parents and hope to figure things out there. Others would look for a job, and maybeget the same job they would have gotten had they finished their degree. After all, most jobs don't require any of the knowledge and skills taught in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And since no one would be getting a degree anymore, companies would have to abandon the practice of discriminatingbased on degree completion and invest some more in applicant screening. This would allow those who don't have a degree, who are disproportionately low income individuals or from a minority background, to have a shot at those jobs that, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.burning-glass.com/research-project/credentials-gap/&quot;&gt;for no good reason, require a Bachelor's degree&lt;/a&gt;. And when a skill typically learned in college would be required for a specific job, companies could increase the resources spent on employee training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But some students might stay in the college dormitories. Some students weren't there just to get a degree and improve their job prospects. Some students were actually there to learn. They didn't enroll into university because they believed they might be left behind if they didn't, but because they wanted to study physics, and understand the mysteries of the universe. They were fascinated by the intrinsic beauty of mathematics. They wanted to understand the intricacies of the world's economic system, and learn how to improve people's lives. They wanted to discover how computers work, and how to build software. They pursued a philosophy degree, not because they hoped to become a lawyer, but because they wanted to think about the mysteries of consciousness and about what constitutes a good life. They wanted to learn about human psychology, the history of civilization, what unites and divides different societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These students didn't need any extrinsic motivation to learn. And so you might identify them by finding those who were already spending some of their free time reading books, reading blogs and tutorials, watching videos and listening to podcasts about the subjects they were fascinated by. And when the university disappears, some of them might just decide to continue to study on their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They would use free online material including the video lectures and other material put online by many top universities. They would find out what textbooks were used in the classes not yet taken, and ask more advanced students for help. They would create reading and study groups to help each other out, and hold each other accountable for their progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They might invite their former favorite professors to come over to ask them questions, ask for advice or just talk. These former educators would thus face the most attentive and interested audience they ever encountered in their whole career. None of the students would be there because they were hoping to get a good grade, or because they were meeting some random requirement to get their degree. They would all be there because they actually cared about what the scholar had to tell them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, some of the public money that used to go into universities, as well as some investment from the private sector would be used to open new research labs or think tanks. And because a university degree cannot be used anymore as a screening tool, some clever company might start to develop comprehensive and challenging standardized tests that research organizations and think tanks might be able to use as a screening tool to find those who have the knowledge and skills necessary to contribute to the organization's mission. These would then allow those young adults who continued to learn after the closure of all colleges to demonstrate their progress, and allow them to make a career in their chosen field of study, despite the complete absence of any higher education institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might think that this scenario is unrealistic. The part about governments closing all universities certainly is. But maybe you also don't believe that there is at least a substantial minority of students who might be capable of learning without the structure of an expensive 4-year college, or you are skeptical that significantly cheaper alternative structures are possible. I will get back to this in a few paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, the only point I am hoping to illustrate with this thought experiment is that the higher education system today is full of bullshit. It becomes quite obvious when you know what to look for. Students will take classes they have no interest in. They usually do as little work as they can get away with. They choose the easiest professors, cram for exams and don't care if they forget everything right after the end of a semester. They feel frustrated when they learned something that ended up not being on the test, and happy when they get away with not doing a required reading. Professors are waging a battle against ignorance with unwilling conscripts that fear a bad grade infinitely more than leaving the semester having learned nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But who can blame them? They can smell the bullshit. For most students, their college major ends up never being relevant to their career. Meanwhile, colleges have little respect for those who learn things on their own rather than concentrating on whatever busywork is required of them. The student's behavior is quite rational given their environment. Of course, if college actually were about learning, students would indeed do themselves a disservice, but unbeknownst to most students and professors, the core product of universities isn't actually an education, but just the degree one gets at the end of it. Ask yourself, would you rather have a Yale degree without the education, or a Yale education without the degree?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People often complain that their work often feels meaningless. Employees don't see how their effort is contributing to the company they work for, or the society they inhabit. But there is nothing more meaningless than the arbitrary deadlines and irrelevant coursework that are the subject of college students' attention, and the cause of their stress for four years. It's &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/vb.html&quot;&gt;bullshit&lt;/a&gt;. And it is this bullshit that is at the root of the student debt crisis, the rapidly increasing cost of higher education, and it is also one important factor in the recent decrease in social mobility, and itcontributes to the hiring discrimination faced by vulnerable minorities. Why would anyone want to put more public money in such a system?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But is there really a better way? Is the vision I present at the beginning, of students taking responsibility for their own education, a realistic one? Or is it just a pipe dream? Today I can say with some conviction that the education experience I sketched earlier is indeed possible, as I have experienced something quite similar for the past eight months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got my first hint that an educational experience significantly different than what is currently on offer is possible when I dropped out of high school two years before graduating, and passed the French Baccalaureat with honors by just studying on my own. I wrote about this experience in detail in &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/05/what-i-learned-dropping-out-of-high-school.html&quot;&gt;a previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was this attainment, getting into college despite having dropped out of high school, that then gave me the confidence to also drop out of college in the summer of 2018. When it became clear to me what a sham higher education had become, I set myself the task to find an alternative. I had become convinced that, in theory at least, anything traditionally learned within the gates of academia could also be learned outside of it. This was informed by both my experience dropping out of high school and my observations in college, where more often than not, students ended up learning the class material on their own anyways. The professor's main function being just to set the content and pace and to enforce deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial plan had been to look for a junior software engineering job in London. I did a handful of interviews, but I ended up giving up on that plan. I was feeling increasingly ambivalent about the idea of getting an entry level programming job rather than self-studying Machine Learning (ML), where I ultimately wanted my career to go. I also became increasingly depressed. Living alone in a tiny airbnb room with no desk in a city in which I knew no one turned out to be more difficult than I had anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2018, I ended up moving back in with my mother. This set-back was quite sobering, but there were some silver linings. During my time in London, I increasingly became aware of the importance of social support, and outside accountability. Sure, a smart disciplined individual can get far on his own, but a solitary education is still quite sub-optimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, I started to experiment with my ideas of outside accountability. I started to learn probability and linear algebra. During the day I left my door open and left my screen facing the door, so that I at least had to look busy at all times. And I started meeting with my mother every evening to tell her what progress I had made, and what were my plans for the next day. It worked quite well for a while though due to various circumstances this routine ultimately petered out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did start to consider various bootcamps or online coding schools at the time. But I had started to develop a fairly concrete idea of what the ideal educational institution would look like and Lambda School or any other bootcamp weren't it. For one thing, they produce their own educational material, which given the abundance of free online material, is a clear sign to me that they are doing something wrong. Education startups should be complementary to, rather than competing with, the wealth of content already available online. Here's an excerpt from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/learnprogramming/comments/8qopsz/if_youre_thinking_about_doing_lambda_school_dont&quot;&gt;one well received review&lt;/a&gt; of Lambda School, in my opinion one of the best online coding schools out there, on the r/learnprogramming subreddit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;TL,DR: If you're smart enough to teach yourself topics you will succeed without Lambda, if you go to Lambda and learn the stuff at an equally fast rate you will also succeed except you will have to give up 17% of your earnings for 2 years. (If you earn over 50,000)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not entirely fair, but insofar as Lambda School is busy hiring teachers and creating lectures for their course, it is true that it isn't adding much value. They are probably just duplicating educational content that already exists for free online. The real value of Lambda school comes from the accountability it provides for students. Students in bootcamps make a big commitment at the beginning, and roll calls, live lectures and deadlines for assignments keep everyone on track. Sure, it's possible to learn everything on your own, but it takes a lot of discipline, and that's what these online coding schools are selling: Discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other problem with these coding schools is that they are all still one size fits all. Everyone has to go at the same rhythm, and the content learned is the same for everyone. So, there is no incentive to go faster than the official pace; people who cannot keep up flunk out. If you already know parts of the curriculum, you will waste money, and if you want to learn something outside of the curriculum, then again, you're faced with the problem of having to learn everything on your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did however see one organization that did have many of the ingredients I saw as lacking in all other educational organizations. While in London, I had gone to a few rationalist meet-ups. I had become aware of these during my research for &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2018/11/23/the-case-for-dropping-out-of-college/&quot;&gt;the piece&lt;/a&gt; I wrote to explain my decision to drop out of college. I had stumbled on a few &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/06/06/against-tulip-subsidies/&quot;&gt;excellent posts&lt;/a&gt; on the problems with the current education system on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/&quot;&gt;Slate Star Codex blog&lt;/a&gt;, and saw some meetups advertised there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of these meetups, I heard about the &quot;EA Hotel.&quot; The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Effective_altruism&quot;&gt;effective altruist&lt;/a&gt; hotel. All they did was offer room and board for people working on effective altruist projects, or for effective altruists wanting to further their education. That sounded almost exactly like the ideal study setting I was imagining. It came with the social support, the freedom and also some accountability that I was looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, in June of 2019 I moved to the EA hotel in Blackpool, UK. My experience at the hotel has been quite close to what I describe in my thought experiment. It was as if I had gotten into some weird and awesome graduate school. I was suddenly surrounded by a group of smart and highly educated young adults with whom I had regular high-level conversations about economics, philosophy, politics, psychology, AI…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I got there, I filled gaps in my understanding of the probability and linear algebra courses I had worked on, I went through the textbook &quot;Introduction to Statistical Learning&quot;, I built a lightweight deep learning library, I learned about computer vision, natural language and reinforcement learning and implemented various papers in those fields. Some of those papers were published less than a year ago. It took me about six months to go from knowing only some basic MLto getting to a point at which I understood much of the cutting-edge deep learning research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also developed a meditation habit, something I had tried to develop, but had failed at, many times before coming to the hotel. For the past eight months, I have meditated for 20 minutes six days a week. And I recently started to practice public speaking at the weekly &quot;lightning talks&quot; event. I also have read more books in the past eight months than in my two years in college, though, admittedly, that's a fairly low bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Hotel is not the perfect educational institution. Since I was the only person working on ML, I have had no one to discuss what I have been learning, or to turn to, to ask for help. Over the summer of 2019, an incoming senior at Cornell University stayed at the Hotel for a month and spent some of his time working on implementing DQN, a reinforcement learning algorithm developed by DeepMind. So, I dropped what I was working on then and put myself to the same task. I have some fond memories of our discussions trying to figure it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I suspect most people would need more supervision. For the most part, I've managed to stay productive by getting into good habits from the start, always working in the common area and waking up early every day. The lessons I learned during my previous experiences with self-teaching came in quite handy, though people who are used to always being told what to do might find it more difficult. The ideal educational environment should externalize people's own learning aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But despite the fact that I have some ideas on how the Hotel as an educational institution could be improved, I still believe that it provides the best learning experience currently available. The best opportunity for intellectual development isn't offered by some expensive prestigious private university, but by a small charity in Blackpool, UK, the operating cost of which is less than 500£/month/resident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the question of whether the vision of a better education system I present at the beginning is in fact a realistic one, I can now answer that yes indeed, it is. Something very close already exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/08/14/room-and-board.html&quot;&gt;And now I want to make this learning experience available to everyone.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">Note: I originally intended to publish this at the end of February. I decided to hold off until now because of COVID-19.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blogs I’ve Been Reading</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/other/2020/08/13/blogs-ive-been-reading.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blogs I've Been Reading" /><published>2020-08-13T10:37:45+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-13T10:37:45+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/other/2020/08/13/blogs-ive-been-reading</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/other/2020/08/13/blogs-ive-been-reading.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some blogs I’ve been reading. I picked two posts for each blog that I think are particularly great or underrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.conradbastable.com&quot;&gt;Conrad Bastable&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.conradbastable.com/essays/the-uncharity-of-college-the-big-business-nobody-understands&quot;&gt;The Uncharity of College: The Big Business Nobody Understands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.conradbastable.com/essays/unequal-growth-the-zero-sum-games-you-dont-see&quot;&gt;Unequal Growth: The Zero-Sum Games You Don’t See&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/&quot;&gt;Slate Star Codex&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2016/04/04/the-ideology-is-not-the-movement/&quot;&gt;The Ideology Is Not The Movement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2017/07/24/targeting-meritocracy/&quot;&gt;Targeting Meritocracy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/&quot;&gt;Gwern&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/Conscientiousness-and-online-education&quot;&gt;Conscientiousness &amp;amp; Online Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/Tool-AI&quot;&gt;Why Tool AIs Want to Be Agent AIs: The Power of Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://marginalrevolution.com/&quot;&gt;Marginal Revolution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2020/01/what-libertarianism-has-become-and-will-become-state-capacity-libertarianism.html&quot;&gt;What libertarianism has become and will become — State Capacity Libertarianism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2020/06/the-gaslighting-of-parasite.html&quot;&gt;The Gaslighting of Parasite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pseudoerasmus.com/&quot;&gt;Pseudoerasmus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pseudoerasmus.com/2015/10/04/ce/&quot;&gt;Where do pro-social institutions come from?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pseudoerasmus.com/2015/06/15/education-econ-growth/&quot;&gt;Educational Romanticism &amp;amp; Economic Development&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://meltingasphalt.com/&quot;&gt;Melting Asphalt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://meltingasphalt.com/startups-are-frontier-communities/&quot;&gt;Startups are Frontier Communities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://meltingasphalt.com/playing-god-for-fun-and-profit/&quot;&gt;Playing God for Fun and Profit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.overcomingbias.com/&quot;&gt;Overcoming Bias&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.overcomingbias.com/2009/09/this-is-the-dream-time.html&quot;&gt;This is the Dream Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.overcomingbias.com/2009/02/write-your-hypothetical-apostasy.html&quot;&gt;Write Your Hypothetical Apostasy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.benkuhn.net/&quot;&gt;Ben Kuhn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.benkuhn.net/grad/&quot;&gt;Grad school is worse for public health than STDs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.benkuhn.net/wnf/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why Nations Fail&lt;/em&gt; and the long-termist view of global poverty&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nintil.com/&quot;&gt;Nintil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nintil.com/on-building&quot;&gt;On building&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nintil.com/the-crumbling-public-private-distinction&quot;&gt;The crumbling public/private distinction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://guzey.com/&quot;&gt;Alexey Guzey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://guzey.com/books/why-we-sleep&quot;&gt;Matthew Walker’s “Why We Sleep” Is Riddled with Scientific and Factual Errors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://guzey.com/personal/how-to-use-your-wife/&quot;&gt;How to use your wife/husband/gf/bf correctly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alexdanco.com/&quot;&gt;Alex Danco&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alexdanco.com/2020/02/15/can-twitter-save-science/&quot;&gt;Can Twitter Save Science?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://alexdanco.com/2020/01/23/social-capital-in-silicon-valley/&quot;&gt;Social Capital in Silicon Valley&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/&quot;&gt;Paul Graham&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/vb.html&quot;&gt;Life is Short&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/say.html&quot;&gt;What You Can’t Say&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.econlib.org/econlog-by-author-and-letter/?selected_letter=C#bcaplan&quot;&gt;Bryan Caplan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.econlib.org/if-the-only-way-you-can-get-your-great-idea-implemented/&quot;&gt;If the Only Way You Can Get Your Great Idea Implemented…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.econlib.org/archives/2011/11/the_magic_of_ed.html&quot;&gt;The Magic of Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://devonzuegel.com/&quot;&gt;Devon Zuegel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://devonzuegel.com/post/singapore-sovereign-city&quot;&gt;Singapore: Sovereign City&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://devonzuegel.com/post/we-should-be-building-cities-for-people-not-cars&quot;&gt;We Should Be Building Cities for People, Not Cars&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://putanumonit.com/&quot;&gt;Put A Number On It!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://putanumonit.com/2020/07/04/kelly-bet-on-everything/&quot;&gt;Kelly Bet on Everything&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://putanumonit.com/2018/03/03/jordan-peterson/&quot;&gt;The Jordan Peterson Mask&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thezvi.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;Don’t Worry About the Vase&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2019/12/28/moloch-hasnt-won/&quot;&gt;Moloch Hasn’t Won&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2018/04/21/the-case-against-education-foundations/&quot;&gt;The Case Against Education: Foundations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">Here are some blogs I’ve been reading. I picked two posts for each blog that I think are particularly great or underrated.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Books I’ve Been Reading</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/other/2020/08/13/books-ive-been-reading.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Books I've Been Reading" /><published>2020-08-13T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-13T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/other/2020/08/13/books-ive-been-reading</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/other/2020/08/13/books-ive-been-reading.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are some books I’ve read since finishing the books on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/update-and-reading-list.html&quot;&gt;Quarantine Reading List&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/First-Break-All-Rules-Differently/dp/1595621113/&quot;&gt;First, Break All the Rules&lt;/a&gt; by Marcus Buckingham&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I got interested in this book after reading about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Two-factor_theory&quot;&gt;two-factor theory of motivation&lt;/a&gt; in Clay Christensen’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/How-Will-Measure-Your-Life/dp/0062102419/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Will You Measure Your Life?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and this book seemed to be the one to read to learn more about it. Also, since &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/06/05/students-are-employees.html&quot;&gt;Students are Employees&lt;/a&gt;, I think that some management lessons might be transferable to the education environment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One interesting point: treat every employee differently. They all have different strengths, interests, motivations… and so there is no one size fits all. This is definitely something applicable to schools.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Tribe-Homecoming-Belonging-Sebastian-Junger/dp/1455566381/&quot;&gt;Tribe: On Homecoming and Belonging&lt;/a&gt; by Sebastian Junger&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This book was brought to my attention by an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.econtalk.org/sebastian-junger-on-tribe/&quot;&gt;EconTalk Podcast episode&lt;/a&gt; with the author. It starts with the question, why did some Europeans decide to go live with American Indians, while the reverse almost never happened?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s a quite thought-provoking read, though I’m less convinced than Junger about the extent to which some of the lessons can be applied to the modern world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Drive-Surprising-Truth-About-Motivates/dp/1594484805/&quot;&gt;Drive: The Surprising Truth About What Motivates Us&lt;/a&gt; by Daniel H. Pink&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Great book on the science of human motivation. Daniel Pink argues that much of the economy runs on extrinsic motivation (motivation 2.0), while for many jobs a reliance on more autonomy and intrinsic motivation (motivation 3.0) would get better results and lead to happier employees. Maybe too optimistic at points, but it still seems highly applicable in the education context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Amusing-Ourselves-Death-Discourse-Business/dp/014303653X/&quot;&gt;Amusing Ourselves to Death&lt;/a&gt; by Neil Postman&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is the third book by Neil Postman I read this year. I greatly enjoyed The End of Education and Education as a Subversive Activity, and so when I saw Patrick Collison &lt;a href=&quot;https://patrickcollison.com/bookshelf&quot;&gt;recommending it&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to read this one as well, even though it doesn’t directly relate to what brought me to Postman in the first place.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The central thesis is  “The medium is the message.” He argues that the medium of television has shaped public discourse for the worse. A similar analysis can probably be made about the effects of the internet, though for all its faults, online discourse has also allowed a deepening of the discourse. You just need to know where to look.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/End-History-Last-Man/dp/0743284550/&quot;&gt;The End of History and the Last Man&lt;/a&gt; by Francis Fukuyama&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A classic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I really liked Francis Fukuyama’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Origins-Political-Order-Prehuman-Revolution/dp/0374533229/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Origins of Political Order&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Political-Order-Decay-Industrial-Globalization/dp/0374535620/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Political Order and Political Decay&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and this is the book that launched his career as a public intellectual. I greatly enjoyed this one as well. It’s quite misunderstood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Benedict-Option-Strategy-Christians-Post-Christian/dp/0735213305/&quot;&gt;The Benedict Option&lt;/a&gt; by Rod Dreher&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I got interested in Rod Dreher after I stumbled on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theamericanconservative.com/dreher/lgbt-pride-social-justice-our-new-civil-religion/&quot;&gt;post of his&lt;/a&gt; extensively quoting from and praising a &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/07/08/gay-rites-are-civil-rites/&quot;&gt;SSC post&lt;/a&gt;. Which I found quite fascinating since he is a conservative christian. The Benedict Option provides an interesting look at the thinking of conservative christians on the losing side of the culture war.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Enlightenment-Now-Science-Humanism-Progress/dp/0143111388/&quot;&gt;Enlightenment Now&lt;/a&gt; by Steven Pinker&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seemed fitting after &lt;em&gt;The Benedict Option&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The main lesson to take away from this book is that you better understand how and why the world works before trying to fix and change it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Great-Delusion-Liberal-International-Realities/dp/0300248563/&quot;&gt;The Great Delusion&lt;/a&gt; by John J. Mearsheimer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I saw &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lzqkXhdo0qc&quot;&gt;this debate&lt;/a&gt; with Fukuyama and Mearsheimer. I found Mearsheimer’s phrasing of how liberalism is predicated on people not being able to agree on first principles pretty interesting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was mainly interested in his take on the history of the current liberal order, which is what the first part of the book is about, but the introduction to the realist school of thought of international relations was quite interesting as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Identity-Demand-Dignity-Politics-Resentment/dp/0374129290/&quot;&gt;Identity&lt;/a&gt; by Francis Fukuyama&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fukuyama again, writing about the challenges to the current liberal order.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Myth-Rational-Voter-Democracies-Policies/dp/0691138737/&quot;&gt;The Myth of The Rational Voter&lt;/a&gt; by Bryan Caplan&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s by Bryan Caplan, so it had to be interesting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Political institutions are quite dysfunctional and the standard answer given is that we need more democracy. So, I was wondering what Caplan’s arguments against this would be. Thought-provoking, and a must read for anyone hoping to improve democratic institutions with more democracy.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Some similar arguments are also made by David Friedman &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Bpn645huKUg&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Innovators-Dilemma-Technologies-Management-Innovation/dp/1633691780/&quot;&gt;The Innovator’s Dilemma&lt;/a&gt; by Clayton M. Christensen&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I read in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/The-Everything-Store-Brad-Stone-audiobook/dp/B00FJFJOLC/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Everything Store&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that Jeff Bezos is a big fan of this book. It’s quite interesting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/How-Fail-Almost-Everything-Still/dp/1591847745/&quot;&gt;How to Fail at Almost Everything and Still Win Big&lt;/a&gt; by Scott Adams&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good self-help book.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Manufacturing-Consent-Political-Economy-Media/dp/0375714499/&quot;&gt;Manufacturing Consent&lt;/a&gt; by Edward S. Herman and Noam Chomsky&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ve been curious about Chomsky for a while. The thesis sounds conspiratorial, but the mechanisms through which consent is ‘manufactured’ are quite credible. I am planning to read more of his books.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See also &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/09/11/book-review-manufacturing-consent/&quot;&gt;this book review on SSC&lt;/a&gt;, and also &lt;a href=&quot;https://rhizzone.net/articles/article-review-book-review-manufacturing-consent/&quot;&gt;this critique of the book review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Triumph-City-Greatest-Invention-Healthier/dp/0143120549/&quot;&gt;Triumph of the City&lt;/a&gt; by Edward Glaeser&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My brother recommended it to me, I saw it &lt;a href=&quot;https://devonzuegel.com/post/cities-reading-list&quot;&gt;Devon Zuegel’s cities book recommendations&lt;/a&gt; and it seemed like a good book for some background information before I dived into private cities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Seasteading-Floating-Environment-Liberate-Politicians/dp/1451699271/&quot;&gt;Seasteading&lt;/a&gt; by Joe Quirk and Patri Friedman&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s a beautiful idea in principle (imagine your house could float away from your street, your street from your city, or your city from your country), but I’m skeptical in practice. It too often sounds like a solution in search of problems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’m still glad people are looking into this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">Here are some books I’ve read since finishing the books on my Quarantine Reading List.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">List of Peter Thiel’s Online Writings</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/other/2020/07/28/thiel-online-writing-list.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="List of Peter Thiel's Online Writings" /><published>2020-07-28T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-28T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/other/2020/07/28/thiel-online-writing-list</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/other/2020/07/28/thiel-online-writing-list.html">&lt;p&gt;This 100 page document has recently made the rounds: &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zao_AyBhNb8TPWrQqgXn5NzNAgfEqzTIaFYos7wdqGI/edit#&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thiel on Progress and Stagnation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Despite looking quite comprehensive, I was surprised to see that quite a few of Thiel’s online writings were absent from the references section. Maybe the creators of the document left those out on purpose, but I suspect they might just not have been aware of them. A lot of Thiel’s online writings appear in relatively obscure places, and I haven’t been able to find a good list that includes all of them. So here is a list of everything Peter Thiel has &lt;em&gt;written online&lt;/em&gt;, as far as I’m aware of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.firstthings.com/article/2007/11/spending-the-future&quot;&gt;Spending the Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.firstthings.com/article/2015/06/against-edenism&quot;&gt;Against Edenism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.firstthings.com/article/2020/03/back-to-the-future&quot;&gt;Back to the Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/2014/09/run-startup-like-cult-heres/&quot;&gt;You Should Run Your Startup Like a Cult. Here’s How&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hoover.org/research/optimistic-thought-experiment&quot;&gt;The Optimistic Thought Experiment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2015/11/28/opinion/the-new-atomic-age-we-need.html&quot;&gt;The New Atomic Age We Need&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/16/opinion/peter-thiel-the-online-privacy-debate-wont-end-with-gawker.html&quot;&gt;Peter Thiel: The Online Privacy Debate Won’t End With Gawker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/08/01/opinion/peter-thiel-google.html&quot;&gt;Good for Google, Bad for America&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cato-unbound.org/2009/04/13/peter-thiel/education-libertarian&quot;&gt;The Education of a Libertarian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evernote.com/shard/s542/client/snv?noteGuid=46c636b6-b404-45df-ab0a-1f84c6fdc8c2&amp;amp;noteKey=7c94233539b8258d72b395a063f3c589&amp;amp;sn=https://www.evernote.com/shard/s542/sh/46c636b6-b404-45df-ab0a-1f84c6fdc8c2/7c94233539b8258d72b395a063f3c589&amp;amp;title=That+Essay&quot;&gt;The Straussian Moment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalreview.com/2011/10/end-future-peter-thiel/&quot;&gt;The End of the Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/peter-thiel-thinking-too-highly-of-higher-ed/2014/11/21/f6758fba-70d4-11e4-893f-86bd390a3340_story.html&quot;&gt;Thinking too highly of higher ed&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tampabay.com/opinion/thinking-too-highly-of-higher-education/2207911/&quot;&gt;No paywall&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can comment or DM me if I’m missing anything.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">This 100 page document has recently made the rounds: Thiel on Progress and Stagnation. Despite looking quite comprehensive, I was surprised to see that quite a few of Thiel’s online writings were absent from the references section. Maybe the creators of the document left those out on purpose, but I suspect they might just not have been aware of them. A lot of Thiel’s online writings appear in relatively obscure places, and I haven’t been able to find a good list that includes all of them. So here is a list of everything Peter Thiel has written online, as far as I’m aware of:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Patrick Collison on Effective Altruism</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/ea/2020/06/23/patrick-collison-on-effective-altruism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patrick Collison on Effective Altruism" /><published>2020-06-23T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-23T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/ea/2020/06/23/patrick-collison-on-effective-altruism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/ea/2020/06/23/patrick-collison-on-effective-altruism.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/xBBXf7KXZCKHYBxeZ/patrick-collison-on-effective-altruism&quot;&gt;Crossposted&lt;/a&gt; on the EA Forum.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective Altruism came up in a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/8rxS6kj5Zt0?t=1785&quot;&gt;discussion between Patrick Collison and Jason Crawford&lt;/a&gt; on the topic of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/07/we-need-new-science-progress/594946/&quot;&gt;Progress Studies&lt;/a&gt;. This is a transcript of the relevant passage. Edited for clarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jason Crawford:&lt;/strong&gt; So compare and contrast the effective altruism movement with progress studies, and I would love to hear you comment on the notion of existential risk or global catastrophic risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patrick Collison:&lt;/strong&gt; On EA… Well… with anything that’s a kind of a totalizing framework and I don’t mean that pejoratively, I just mean that in principle everyone could have an EA mindset and I’m sure at least some EA members think that everyone should have an EA oriented mindset. And so you can then sort of ask the question of well, would it be good for everyone to have an EA mindset? But of course the other way of asking it is, is EA on the current margin a good new way for people to be thinking and would it be good, if instead of zero people before the EA movement to be thinking in an EA oriented fashion, would it be good for 5% of people or for 10% of people to be thinking that way? And in the latter sense, was it a good shift on the margin? I think EA has been great and I’m sort-of delighted that they have had the progress they they’ve had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if the question is, should everyone be an EA or even, I guess in the individual sense, am I or do I think I should be an EA? I think – and obviously there’s kind of heterogeneity within the field – but my general sense is that the EA movement is always very focused on kind of rigid, not rigid, that’s that’s unfair perhaps, but on sort of, estimation, analytical, quantification, and sort of utilitarian calculation, and I think that that as a practical matter that means that you end up too focused on that which you can measure, which again means – or as a practical matter means – you’re too focus on things that are sort of short-term like bed nets or deworming or whatever being obvious examples. And are those good causes? I would say almost definitely yes, obviously. Now we’ve seen some new data over the last couple of years that maybe they’re not as good as they initially seemed but they’re very likely to be really good things to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s hard for me to see how, you know, writing a treatise of human nature would score really highly in an EA oriented framework. As assessed ex-post that looked like a really valuable thing for Hume to do. And similarly, as we have a look at the things that in hindsight seem like very good things to have happen in the world, it’s often unclear to me how an EA oriented intuition might have caused somebody to do so. And so I guess I think of EA as sort of like a metal detector, and they’ve invented a new kind of metal detector that’s really good at detecting some metals that other detectors are not very good at detecting. But I actually think we need some diversity in the different metallic substances which our detectors are attuned to, and for me EA would not be the only one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jason Crawford:&lt;/strong&gt; Good metaphor. And what about the particular concerns about global catastrophic risk or existential risks especially from technology. This is where I get sort of the most, I won’t even say push back exactly, but concern from people about progress studies, is the question of, if we just run full throttle with progress what about the risk of, we’re just not careful enough and we get some catastrophe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patrick Collison:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I think it is probably true that the optimal rate of technological change is not monotonically better the more that there is. There probably are kind of shear forces with society at a certain point. I think the question is to, as a practical matter should our concern be having too much or having too little. And actually, I should say I don’t want to conflate ‘progress’ in progress studies with purely technological advancement, but it’s still a significant part of it. And generally I think, looking historically I think that too little has been a problem far more frequently than too much. I think that today in many super obvious ways we have… too many lives are not as good as they obviously could be, and so in a very tangible sense we have too little progress, and I think there are very valid ways in which one could imagine having too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I guess, I feel sort of, for every one unit of concern I give to ‘too much’ I give it four or five to ‘we have too little.’ Now there is an asymmetry there where the existential risks are, by definition, existential and I thought Toby Ord’s book was a great contribution. Broadly I think the existential risks folks, again, have introduced a good line of thinking that we really should be taking seriously. I suspect that it’s possible to mitigate most of those risks relatively effectively without redirecting vast swathes of society and I think the more difficult problem will actually be how do we generate enough.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">Crossposted on the EA Forum.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Students Are Employees</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/06/05/students-are-employees.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Students Are Employees" /><published>2020-06-05T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-05T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/06/05/students-are-employees</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/06/05/students-are-employees.html">&lt;p&gt;Education is a peculiar good. The usual model of private education is that the students are the consumers, the professors are the employees, and the lectures are the product. Students pay to receive the education they want. In reality, students pay more for the degree than the education. But let’s assume for now that education is all about increasing human capital, rather than being mostly about &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2018/11/23/the-case-for-dropping-out-of-college/&quot;&gt;signaling&lt;/a&gt;. For the sake of argument, let’s assume that I’m talking about an education start-up that doesn’t grant any kind of degree or certification, and is solely focused on the students’ learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, the model describing students as the consumer is still missing something important. The problem is that modeling students as simple homo economicus agents is not perfect. As the field of behavioral economics has extensively documented, humans aren’t perfectly rational, self-interested, utility-maximizing agents. And education seems to be one of the fields where the homo economicus model is most misleading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With education, a better model is the one of the elephant and the rider described by Jonathan Haidt in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Happiness-Hypothesis-Putting-Ancient-Science-ebook/dp/B00YY05O7G/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Happiness Hypothesis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He explains it thus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The rider can see farther into the future, and the rider can learn valuable information by talking to other riders or by reading maps, but the rider cannot order the elephant around against its will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The rider […] is conscious, controlled thought. The elephant, in contrast, is everything else. The elephant includes the gut feelings, visceral reactions, emotions, and intuitions that comprise much of the automatic system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When everything works well, it does look like the rider is in control. But sometimes things go wrong, and then it becomes apparent that really, the elephant is the one in control. Depression and addiction are the two main examples of when the rider is obviously not in charge anymore. Haidt describes the rider as more of an “advisor,” capable of nudging the elephant in the right direction, but incapable of just ordering the elephant around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rider also has the role of lawyer. If you eat a piece of cake even though the diet you’re trying to stick to forbids it, the rider might start trying to justify it. “I totally meant to do that.” - “It’s fine, I’ll eat less tomorrow.” - “This diet is dumb anyways.” Self-justification is the rider pretending that he’s still in control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that humans have a unified self is one thing that both the homo economicus model and most people’s model of themselves have in common. Self-justification is one way that people resolve the cognitive dissonance that arises when the model of the unified, in control, self is challenged by evidence that the self is more like a rider on an elephant with a mind of its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not to say that the model of the rider and the elephant is the “correct” way of understanding the mind. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_models_are_wrong&quot;&gt;All models are wrong, but some are useful.&lt;/a&gt; So take it with a grain of salt. You probably should use the unified model of the self in most settings, especially in the ones involving other people. No court of law is going to accept the excuse “the elephant did it.” Nor should it. The same goes for broken personal commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assumption that people are unified, responsible, agents is what makes society work. However, coming to terms with the fact that this model of individuals is flawed is just as important. Appeals to individual agency might work in most cases, but when trying to deal with depression or addiction, the assumption that people are always in control can be counterproductive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how does this relate to education? Well, for one thing, this model explains why online education hasn’t made in-person education obsolete yet. The fact that it’s much harder to get recognition for things self-learned online is part of the reason. But just as important is the fact that self-learning online is really hard. MOOCs’ completion rates are around 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, some people starting MOOCs don’t intend to finish them in the first place. But I’m certain that a significant share of those who don’t complete, did mean to finish when they first started. At the beginning, the rider managed to nudge the elephant onto the steep path that is learning anything challenging. The rider thought that the view on top would be incredible and managed to infect the elephant with the excitement that comes with the vision of achieving something ambitious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point along the track, however, the elephant gives up. All the elephant sees, is an arduous, unrewarding path ahead. The rider tries to convince the elephant to continue. He argues that the effort is worth it. He explains that he will be very disappointed if they don’t go ahead. To no avail. The elephant has started watching Netflix, and the rider gives up and joins the elephant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been there, and I suspect that anyone who has attempted anything difficult on their own will recognize themselves in this story. So, what is the solution? The self-help literature is full of advice on how to overcome this. Habits, to-do lists, separate work and leisure spaces… Self-help literature is all about advice to empower the rider to get the elephant to do what the rider wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One self-help service that takes this elephant and rider theory of the mind very seriously, is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.beeminder.com/&quot;&gt;Beeminder&lt;/a&gt;. It relies on the fact that the elephant really hates losing money. Beeminder allows you to make goals, track them, and if you fail to meet the set target, Beeminder takes a preset amount of money out of your bank account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds insane to anyone having a model of the self as unified and in control. With the elephant and rider model however, it makes sense. The rider is extorting the elephant. He threatens the elephant with sending money to Beeminder unless the rider’s demands are met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it works, to some extent. I have been using it for almost 2 years now to keep me writing a certain minimum amount of words in a personal diary. The document is now close to 400k words long. And I have paid $15 to Beeminder (3x$5). However, I also have entered fake data a few times. Beeminder works best when there’s independent verification. For example, a running app connected to beeminder to provide reliable data on the distance run. Absent that, the best one can do is to attempt to be strict and to never allow the elephant to enter any fake data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there a better way? Certainly. Something that much of the self-help literature misses is that taming the elephant is really a social activity. Humans have a deep-seated compulsion to conform to societal expectations, a strong desire for validation by peers and an instinctual impulse to obey authority figures. Thus, just as the rider can take advantage of the elephant’s aversion of short-term financial losses, he can also lead the elephant into situations in which the elephant will feel strongly motivated by social factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One technique that uses that insight is the accountability buddy system. It uses the fact that it is significantly harder to renege on a public commitment than one that remains hidden within one’s mind. The elephant hates the embarrassment that comes with publicly declaring one’s intention to do something, but then failing to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the extent that schools enable learning, it is also because of this. People learn from an early age that good grades are synonymous with approval and praise by both teachers and parents, while bad grades are usually met with opprobrium and disappointment. Thus, students will be able to expend a great deal of effort to prepare for an exam in some random subject they find uninteresting and won’t ever use. However, the same amount of effort can be extremely difficult to come up with when outside an educational institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Average-Over-Powering-America-Stagnation-ebook/dp/B00C1N5WOI&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Average Is Over&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Tyler Cowen echoes a similar idea:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will become increasingly apparent how much of current education is driven by human weakness, namely the inability of most students to simply sit down and try to learn something on their own. It’s a common claim that you can’t replace professors with Nobel-quality YouTube lectures because the professor, and perhaps also the classroom setting, is required to motivate most of the students. Fair enough, but let’s take this seriously. The professor is then a motivator first and foremost. Let’s hire good motivators. Let’s teach our professors how to motivate. Let’s judge them on that basis. Let’s treat professors more like athletic coaches, personal therapists, and preachers, because that is what they will evolve to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the primary role of the hypothetical education start-up I mentioned at the beginning would be to motivate the elephant. Just like Beeminder, it would be used by the rider to get the elephant to do what the rider wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities do partly fulfill this function. However, as I mentioned at the beginning, the fact that the average student is more motivated by the degree than the education, makes it a poor example of what an organization solely focused on education would look like. The average professor is a mediocre motivator, whose main tool is the threat of a lower GPA and the impediment to degree completion, and students have only limited freedom to choose what and how to learn. I will explore these points further in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this translate to the economic model? In light of this understanding of how and why educational institutions work, a more accurate model of education would put the rider as the consumer, the elephant as the employee, and the professor as the manager. Even in the best educational institutions, if the student doesn’t study, if the elephant isn’t motivated, the student isn’t going to learn anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An education isn’t something the professor makes and the student receives. It is something the student creates, and the professor’s role is to make sure that the student stays on track. In the end, the students are the ones creating the value. By studying, reading, doing their homework, students are the main contributors to the value created in educational institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;employees-are-students&quot;&gt;Employees Are Students&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viewing students as both the consumers and the employees also raises an interesting question: where lies the dividing line between being a student and being an employee? To illustrate this point more clearly, take the case of unpaid internships that some students take as part of their degree program. It is not uncommon for students to not only work for free but then also having to pay their university to get college credits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is often alleged that unpaid internships are exploitative, but then what is paying a university to get college credits for your work? It is a farce. It reveals the inherent contradiction in the standards we apply to higher education institutions and private companies. Why is it socially acceptable to get deep into debt to study at a university, while learning at an internship &lt;em&gt;for free&lt;/em&gt; is looked down upon? The reality is that the term ‘study’ masks the fact that there is no clear dividing line between studying and working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a journalism school that also runs a newspaper. It hires professional journalists and editors to both create content for the newspaper and to teach a batch of aspiring writers. The school thus earns money through both its newspaper and the students who pay for the education. Early on, students are encouraged to write pieces that might be published in the newspaper. What better practice can there be for an aspiring journalist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, almost none of the students manage to write anything worth publishing, or, when they do, the writing needs so much editing and feedback that the school ends up publishing their piece at a significant loss. But gradually, the writing becomes better and the cost of having to train the young aspiring reporters, and the additional editing required on their writing, starts being offset by their contribution to the newspaper. And so the school starts reducing the tuition of the students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, the students’ writing becomes so good that it completely offsets the cost. They can stay for free. And then they start getting paid. Gradually, their contributions become more and more valuable, and it starts exceeding the costs of mentoring, teaching, editing, advising… In the end, they become so skilled that they become indistinguishable from any of the other employees at the school/newspaper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At what point did they stop ‘studying’ and started ‘working’? The truth is that there is no point at which one stopped and the other started. Studying has always involved working, and working has always involved learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why is there such a vast gap between educational institutions and the rest of the productive economy? Why aren’t newspapers simultaneously also journalism schools? Wouldn’t that be the ideal way to find and train talent and to create an additional revenue stream? Why aren’t companies more involved in the education of the workforce?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to these questions is called regulatory capture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two reasons why someone might want to pay for work. First, because of the work’s educational value, and second for the signaling it provides. But because of a plethora of policies, such as minimum wage laws, subsidies for educational institutions, availability of student loans, regulations governing educational bodies, etc., companies cannot compete with universities for this kind of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributing to this state of affairs is also a misplaced societal bias against any work that is paid less than the minimum wage. Concerns about equity are valid, but then why the double standard with educational institutions? Why is work at an educational institution not significantly more exploitative than work in an unpaid internship?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I propose is that instead of giving money to universities and restricting businesses’ ability to provide educational opportunities, give the money directly to young people&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; and let them decide what constitutes the best opportunity for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; If you really don’t trust young people to spend the money responsibly, vouchers could work as well.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">Education is a peculiar good. The usual model of private education is that the students are the consumers, the professors are the employees, and the lectures are the product. Students pay to receive the education they want. In reality, students pay more for the degree than the education. But let’s assume for now that education is all about increasing human capital, rather than being mostly about signaling. For the sake of argument, let’s assume that I’m talking about an education start-up that doesn’t grant any kind of degree or certification, and is solely focused on the students’ learning. Then, the model describing students as the consumer is still missing something important. The problem is that modeling students as simple homo economicus agents is not perfect. As the field of behavioral economics has extensively documented, humans aren’t perfectly rational, self-interested, utility-maximizing agents. And education seems to be one of the fields where the homo economicus model is most misleading.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Harari on Religions and Ideologies</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/religion/2020/05/18/harari-on-religions-and-ideologies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Harari on Religions and Ideologies" /><published>2020-05-18T11:53:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-18T11:53:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/religion/2020/05/18/harari-on-religions-and-ideologies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/religion/2020/05/18/harari-on-religions-and-ideologies.html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Sapiens-Yuval-Noah-Harari-audiobook/dp/B0741F3M7C/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sapiens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Yuval Noah Harari writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The last 300 years are often depicted as an age of growing secularism, in which religions have increasingly lost their importance. If we are talking about theist religions, this is largely correct. But if we take into consideration natural-law religions, then modernity turns out to be an age of intense religious fervour, unparalleled missionary efforts, and the bloodiest wars of religion in history. The modern age has witnessed the rise of a number of new natural-law religions, such as liberalism, Communism, capitalism, nationalism and Nazism. These creeds do not like to be called religions, and refer to themselves as ideologies. But this is just a semantic exercise. If a religion is a system of human norms and values that is founded on belief in a superhuman order, then Soviet Communism was no less a religion than Islam. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Islam is of course different from Communism, because Islam sees the superhuman order governing the world as the edict of an omnipotent creator god, whereas Soviet Communism did not believe in gods. But Buddhism too gives short shrift to gods, and yet we commonly classify it as a religion. Like Buddhists, Communists believed in a superhuman order of natural and immutable laws that should guide human actions. Whereas Buddhists believe that the law of nature was discovered by Siddhartha Gautama, Communists believed that the law of nature was discovered by Karl Marx, Friedrich Engels and Vladimir Ilyich Lenin. The similarity does not end there. Like other religions, Communism too has its holy scripts and prophetic books, such as Marx’s Das Kapital, which foretold that history would soon end with the inevitable victory of the proletariat. Communism had its holidays and festivals, such as the First of May and the anniversary of the October Revolution. It had theologians adept at Marxist dialectics, and every unit in the Soviet army had a chaplain, called a commissar, who monitored the piety of soldiers and officers. Communism had martyrs, holy wars and heresies, such as Trotskyism. Soviet Communism was a fanatical and missionary religion. A devout Communist could not be a Christian or a Buddhist, and was expected to spread the gospel of Marx and Lenin even at the price of his or her life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It would be impossible to survey here the history of all the new modern creeds, especially because there are no clear boundaries between them. They are no less syncretic than monotheism and popular Buddhism. Just as a Buddhist could worship Hindu deities, and just as a monotheist could believe in the existence of Satan, so the typical American nowadays is simultaneously a nationalist (she believes in the existence of an American nation with a special role to play in history), a free-market capitalist (she believes that open competition and the pursuit of self-interest are the best ways to create a prosperous society), and a liberal humanist (she believes that humans have been endowed by their creator with certain inalienable rights).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Homo-Deus-Yuval-Noah-Harari-audiobook/dp/B01MYZ4OUW&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Homo Deus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, he makes a similar argument:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Equating religion with faith in supernatural powers implies that you can understand all known natural phenomena without religion, which is just an optional supplement. Having understood perfectly well the whole of nature, you can now choose whether to add some ‘super-natural’ religious dogma or not. However, most religions argue that you simply cannot understand the world without them. You will never comprehend the true reason for disease, drought or earthquakes if you do not take their dogma into account. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Defining religion as ‘belief in gods’ is also problematic. We tend to say that a devout Christian is religious because she believes in God, whereas a fervent communist isn’t religious, because communism has no gods. However, religion is created by humans rather than by gods, and it is defined by its social function rather than by the existence of deities. Religion is anything that confers superhuman legitimacy on human social structures. It legitimises human norms and values by arguing that they reflect superhuman laws. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Religion asserts that we humans are subject to a system of moral laws that we did not invent and that we cannot change. A devout Jew would say that this is the system of moral laws created by God and revealed in the Bible. A Hindu would say that Brahma, Vishnu and Shiva created the laws, which were revealed to us humans in the Vedas. Other religions, from Buddhism and Daoism to Nazism, communism and liberalism, argue that the superhuman laws are natural laws, and not the creation of this or that god. Of course, each believes in a different set of natural laws discovered and revealed by different seers and prophets, from Buddha and Laozi to Hitler and Lenin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Liberals, communists and followers of other modern creeds dislike describing their own system as a ‘religion’, because they identify religion with superstitions and supernatural powers. If you tell communists or liberals that they are religious, they think you accuse them of blindly believing in groundless pipe dreams. In fact, it means only that they believe in some system of moral laws that wasn’t invented by humans, but which humans must nevertheless obey. As far as we know, all human societies believe in this. Every society tells its members that they must obey some superhuman moral law, and that breaking this law will result in catastrophe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m planning to write a post digging deeper into this at some point. For now, if you’re interested in this topic, I recommend the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/03/25/is-everything-a-religion/&quot;&gt;Is Everything a Religion?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://meltingasphalt.com/playing-god-for-fun-and-profit/&quot;&gt;Playing God for Fun and Profit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/07/08/gay-rites-are-civil-rites/&quot;&gt;Gay Rites Are Civil Rites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2017/04/breaking-faith/517785/&quot;&gt;Breaking Faith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2018/12/andrew-sullivan-americas-new-religions.html&quot;&gt;America’s New Religions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nationalinterest.org/feature/war-over-liberal-democracy-44242&quot;&gt;The War over Liberal Democracy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evernote.com/shard/s542/client/snv?noteGuid=46c636b6-b404-45df-ab0a-1f84c6fdc8c2&amp;amp;noteKey=7c94233539b8258d72b395a063f3c589&amp;amp;sn=https://www.evernote.com/shard/s542/sh/46c636b6-b404-45df-ab0a-1f84c6fdc8c2/7c94233539b8258d72b395a063f3c589&amp;amp;title=That+Essay&quot;&gt;The Straussian Moment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">In Sapiens, Yuval Noah Harari writes:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Schools and Churches</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/13/schools-and-churches.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Schools and Churches" /><published>2020-05-13T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/13/schools-and-churches</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/13/schools-and-churches.html">&lt;p&gt;From Ivan Illich’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Deschooling-Society-Open-Forum-S-ebook/dp/B007EDLBBI/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deschooling Society&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;teacher-as-custodian&lt;/em&gt; acts as a master of ceremonies, who guides his pupils through a drawn-out labyrinthine ritual. He arbitrates the observance of rules and administers the intricate rubrics of initiation to life. At his best, he sets the stage for the acquisition of some skill as schoolmasters always have. Without illusions of producing any profound learning, he drills his pupils in some basic routines. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The &lt;em&gt;teacher-as-moralist&lt;/em&gt; substitutes for parents, God, or the state. He indoctrinates the pupil about what is right or wrong, not only in school buy also in society at large. He stands &lt;em&gt;in loco parentis&lt;/em&gt; for each one and thus ensures that all feel themselves children of the same state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Children are protected by neither the First nor the Fifth Amendment when they stand before that secular priest, the teacher. The child must confront a man who wears an invisible triple crown, like the papal tiara, the symbol of triple authority combined in one person. For the child, the teacher pontificates as pastor, prophet and priest–he is at once guide, teacher, and administrator of a sacred ritual. He combines the claims of medieval popes in a society constituted under the guarantee these claims shall never be exercised together by one established and obligatory institution–church or state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Classroom attendance removes children from the everyday world of Western culture and plunges them into an environment for more primitive, magical and deadly serious. School could not create such an enclave within which the rules of ordinary reality are suspended, unless it physically incarcerated the young on sacred territory. The attendance rule makes it possible for the schoolroom to serve as a magic womb, from which the child is delivered periodically at the schoolday’s and school year’s completion until he is finally expelled into adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The school system today performs the threefold function common to powerful churches throughout history. It is simultaneously the repository of society’s myth, the institutionalization of the myth’s contradictions, and the locus of the ritual which reproduces and veils the disparities between myth and reality. Today the school system, and especially the university, provides ample opportunity for criticism of the myth and for rebellion against institutional perversions. But the ritual which demands tolerance of the fundamental contradictions between myth and institution still goes unchallenged, for neither ideological criticism nor social action can bring about a new society. Only disenchantment with and detachment from the central societal ritual and reform of that ritual can bring about social change. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The American university has become the final stage of the most all-encompassing initiation rite the world has ever known. No society in history has been able to survive without ritual or myth, but ours is the first which has needed such a dull, protracted, destructive, and expensive initiation ritual in the name of education. We cannot begin a reform of education unless we first understand that neither individual learning nor social equality can be enhanced by the ritual of schooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;School seems eminently suited to be the World Church of our decaying culture. No institution could better veil from its participants the deep discrepancy between social principles and social reality in today’s world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure I fully endorse these paragraphs, but the school-church comparison is interesting. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Average-Over-Powering-America-Stagnation-ebook/dp/B00C1N5WOI&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Average Is Over&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Tyler Cowen also points out the parallels between educational and religious institutions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Of course, educational institutions aren’t ready to admit how much they share with churches. These temples of secularism don’t want to admit they are about simple tasks such as motivating the slugs or acculturating people into the work habits and sociological expectations of the so-called educated class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We like to pretend our instructors teach as well as chess computers, but too often they don’t come close to that ideal. They are something far less noble, something that we are afraid to call by its real name, something quite ordinary: They are a mix of exemplars and nags and missionaries, packaged with a marketing model that stressed their nobility and a financial model that pays them pretty well and surrounds them with administrators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil Postman also &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/end-of-education.html&quot;&gt;identified a connection&lt;/a&gt; beween religion and education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Peter Thiel is also fond of the analogy. He often compares the state of the education system today to the state of the Catholic Church 500 years ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SO_00POR-Po?start=2037&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">From Ivan Illich’s Deschooling Society:</summary></entry></feed>