<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thememeticist.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thememeticist.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-18T15:57:44+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Memeticist</title><subtitle>Memes worth spreading </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Harari on Religions and Ideologies</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/religion/2020/05/18/harari-on-religions-and-ideologies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Harari on Religions and Ideologies" /><published>2020-05-18T11:53:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-18T11:53:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/religion/2020/05/18/harari-on-religions-and-ideologies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/religion/2020/05/18/harari-on-religions-and-ideologies.html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Sapiens-Yuval-Noah-Harari-audiobook/dp/B0741F3M7C/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sapiens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Yuval Noah Harari writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The last 300 years are often depicted as an age of growing secularism, in which religions have increasingly lost their importance. If we are talking about theist religions, this is largely correct. But if we take into consideration natural-law religions, then modernity turns out to be an age of intense religious fervour, unparalleled missionary efforts, and the bloodiest wars of religion in history. The modern age has witnessed the rise of a number of new natural-law religions, such as liberalism, Communism, capitalism, nationalism and Nazism. These creeds do not like to be called religions, and refer to themselves as ideologies. But this is just a semantic exercise. If a religion is a system of human norms and values that is founded on belief in a superhuman order, then Soviet Communism was no less a religion than Islam. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Islam is of course different from Communism, because Islam sees the superhuman order governing the world as the edict of an omnipotent creator god, whereas Soviet Communism did not believe in gods. But Buddhism too gives short shrift to gods, and yet we commonly classify it as a religion. Like Buddhists, Communists believed in a superhuman order of natural and immutable laws that should guide human actions. Whereas Buddhists believe that the law of nature was discovered by Siddhartha Gautama, Communists believed that the law of nature was discovered by Karl Marx, Friedrich Engels and Vladimir Ilyich Lenin. The similarity does not end there. Like other religions, Communism too has its holy scripts and prophetic books, such as Marx’s Das Kapital, which foretold that history would soon end with the inevitable victory of the proletariat. Communism had its holidays and festivals, such as the First of May and the anniversary of the October Revolution. It had theologians adept at Marxist dialectics, and every unit in the Soviet army had a chaplain, called a commissar, who monitored the piety of soldiers and officers. Communism had martyrs, holy wars and heresies, such as Trotskyism. Soviet Communism was a fanatical and missionary religion. A devout Communist could not be a Christian or a Buddhist, and was expected to spread the gospel of Marx and Lenin even at the price of his or her life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It would be impossible to survey here the history of all the new modern creeds, especially because there are no clear boundaries between them. They are no less syncretic than monotheism and popular Buddhism. Just as a Buddhist could worship Hindu deities, and just as a monotheist could believe in the existence of Satan, so the typical American nowadays is simultaneously a nationalist (she believes in the existence of an American nation with a special role to play in history), a free-market capitalist (she believes that open competition and the pursuit of self-interest are the best ways to create a prosperous society), and a liberal humanist (she believes that humans have been endowed by their creator with certain inalienable rights).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Homo-Deus-Yuval-Noah-Harari-audiobook/dp/B01MYZ4OUW&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Homo Deus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, he makes a similar argument:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Equating religion with faith in supernatural powers implies that you can understand all known natural phenomena without religion, which is just an optional supplement. Having understood perfectly well the whole of nature, you can now choose whether to add some ‘super-natural’ religious dogma or not. However, most religions argue that you simply cannot understand the world without them. You will never comprehend the true reason for disease, drought or earthquakes if you do not take their dogma into account. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Defining religion as ‘belief in gods’ is also problematic. We tend to say that a devout Christian is religious because she believes in God, whereas a fervent communist isn’t religious, because communism has no gods. However, religion is created by humans rather than by gods, and it is defined by its social function rather than by the existence of deities. Religion is anything that confers superhuman legitimacy on human social structures. It legitimises human norms and values by arguing that they reflect superhuman laws. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Religion asserts that we humans are subject to a system of moral laws that we did not invent and that we cannot change. A devout Jew would say that this is the system of moral laws created by God and revealed in the Bible. A Hindu would say that Brahma, Vishnu and Shiva created the laws, which were revealed to us humans in the Vedas. Other religions, from Buddhism and Daoism to Nazism, communism and liberalism, argue that the superhuman laws are natural laws, and not the creation of this or that god. Of course, each believes in a different set of natural laws discovered and revealed by different seers and prophets, from Buddha and Laozi to Hitler and Lenin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Liberals, communists and followers of other modern creeds dislike describing their own system as a ‘religion’, because they identify religion with superstitions and supernatural powers. If you tell communists or liberals that they are religious, they think you accuse them of blindly believing in groundless pipe dreams. In fact, it means only that they believe in some system of moral laws that wasn’t invented by humans, but which humans must nevertheless obey. As far as we know, all human societies believe in this. Every society tells its members that they must obey some superhuman moral law, and that breaking this law will result in catastrophe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m planning to write a post digging deeper into this at some point. For now, if you’re interested in this topic, I recommend the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/03/25/is-everything-a-religion/&quot;&gt;Is Everything a Religion?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://meltingasphalt.com/playing-god-for-fun-and-profit/&quot;&gt;Playing God for Fun and Profit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/07/08/gay-rites-are-civil-rites/&quot;&gt;Gay Rites Are Civil Rites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2017/04/breaking-faith/517785/&quot;&gt;Breaking Faith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2018/12/andrew-sullivan-americas-new-religions.html&quot;&gt;America’s New Religions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nationalinterest.org/feature/war-over-liberal-democracy-44242&quot;&gt;The War over Liberal Democracy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evernote.com/shard/s542/client/snv?noteGuid=46c636b6-b404-45df-ab0a-1f84c6fdc8c2&amp;amp;noteKey=7c94233539b8258d72b395a063f3c589&amp;amp;sn=https://www.evernote.com/shard/s542/sh/46c636b6-b404-45df-ab0a-1f84c6fdc8c2/7c94233539b8258d72b395a063f3c589&amp;amp;title=That+Essay&quot;&gt;The Straussian Moment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">In Sapiens, Yuval Noah Harari writes:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Schools and Churches</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/13/schools-and-churches.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Schools and Churches" /><published>2020-05-13T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/13/schools-and-churches</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/13/schools-and-churches.html">&lt;p&gt;From Ivan Illich’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Deschooling-Society-Open-Forum-S-ebook/dp/B007EDLBBI/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deschooling Society&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;teacher-as-custodian&lt;/em&gt; acts as a master of ceremonies, who guides his pupils through a drawn-out labyrinthine ritual. He arbitrates the observance of rules and administers the intricate rubrics of initiation to life. At his best, he sets the stage for the acquisition of some skill as schoolmasters always have. Without illusions of producing any profound learning, he drills his pupils in some basic routines. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The &lt;em&gt;teacher-as-moralist&lt;/em&gt; substitutes for parents, God, or the state. He indoctrinates the pupil about what is right or wrong, not only in school buy also in society at large. He stands &lt;em&gt;in loco parentis&lt;/em&gt; for each one and thus ensures that all feel themselves children of the same state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Children are protected by neither the First nor the Fifth Amendment when they stand before that secular priest, the teacher. The child must confront a man who wears an invisible triple crown, like the papal tiara, the symbol of triple authority combined in one person. For the child, the teacher pontificates as pastor, prophet and priest–he is at once guide, teacher, and administrator of a sacred ritual. He combines the claims of medieval popes in a society constituted under the guarantee these claims shall never be exercised together by one established and obligatory institution–church or state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Classroom attendance removes children from the everyday world of Western culture and plunges them into an environment for more primitive, magical and deadly serious. School could not create such an enclave within which the rules of ordinary reality are suspended, unless it physically incarcerated the young on sacred territory. The attendance rule makes it possible for the schoolroom to serve as a magic womb, from which the child is delivered periodically at the schoolday’s and school year’s completion until he is finally expelled into adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The school system today performs the threefold function common to powerful churches throughout history. It is simultaneously the repository of society’s myth, the institutionalization of the myth’s contradictions, and the locus of the ritual which reproduces and veils the disparities between myth and reality. Today the school system, and especially the university, provides ample opportunity for criticism of the myth and for rebellion against institutional perversions. But the ritual which demands tolerance of the fundamental contradictions between myth and institution still goes unchallenged, for neither ideological criticism nor social action can bring about a new society. Only disenchantment with and detachment from the central societal ritual and reform of that ritual can bring about social change. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The American university has become the final stage of the most all-encompassing initiation rite the world has ever known. No society in history has been able to survive without ritual or myth, but ours is the first which has needed such a dull, protracted, destructive, and expensive initiation ritual in the name of education. We cannot begin a reform of education unless we first understand that neither individual learning nor social equality can be enhanced by the ritual of schooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;School seems eminently suited to be the World Church of our decaying culture. No institution could better veil from its participants the deep discrepancy between social principles and social reality in today’s world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure I fully endorse these paragraphs, but the school-church comparison is interesting. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Average-Over-Powering-America-Stagnation-ebook/dp/B00C1N5WOI&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Average Is Over&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Tyler Cowen also points out the parallels between educational and religious institutions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Of course, educational institutions aren’t ready to admit how much they share with churches. These temples of secularism don’t want to admit they are about simple tasks such as motivating the slugs or acculturating people into the work habits and sociological expectations of the so-called educated class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We like to pretend our instructors teach as well as chess computers, but too often they don’t come close to that ideal. They are something far less noble, something that we are afraid to call by its real name, something quite ordinary: They are a mix of exemplars and nags and missionaries, packaged with a marketing model that stressed their nobility and a financial model that pays them pretty well and surrounds them with administrators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil Postman also &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/end-of-education.html&quot;&gt;identified a connection&lt;/a&gt; beween religion and education.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">From Ivan Illich’s Deschooling Society:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trillion Dollar Bills on the Sidewalk</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/12/trillion-dollar-bills.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trillion Dollar Bills on the Sidewalk" /><published>2020-05-12T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-12T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/12/trillion-dollar-bills</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/12/trillion-dollar-bills.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading some more Mancur Olson. This is from a 1996 paper titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/2138479?seq=1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Big Bills Left on the Sidewalk: Why Some Nations are Rich, and Others Poor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If what has been said so far is correct, then the large differences in per capita income across countries cannot be explained by differences in access to the world’s stock of productive knowledge or to its capital markets, by differences in the ratio of population to land or natural resources, or by differences in the quality of marketable human capital or personal culture. Albeit at a high level of aggregation, this eliminates each of the factors of production as possible explanations of most of the international differences in per capita income. The only remaining plausible explanation is that the great differences in the wealth of nations are mainly due to differences in the quality of their institutions and economic policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The best thing a society can do to increase its prosperity is to wise up. This means, in turn, that it is very important indeed that economists, inside government and out, get things right. When we are wrong, we do a lot of harm. When we are right-and have the clarity needed to prevail against the special interests and the quacks-we make an extraordinary contribution to the amelioration of poverty and the progress of humanity. The sums lost because the poor countries obtain only a fraction of-and because even the richest countries do not reach-their economic potentials are measured in the trillions of dollars. &lt;br /&gt;
None of the familiar ideologies is sufficient to provide the needed wisdom. The familiar assumption that the quality of a nation’s economic institutions and policies is given by the smallness, or the largeness, of its public sector-or by the size of its transfers to low-income people-does not fit the facts very well (Levine and Renelt, 1992; Rubinson, 1977; Olson, 1986).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does remind me of something David Manheim recently said on Twitter about the government’s inept response to the COVID-19 crisis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Markets may be efficient, but government is not. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are nearly-literal trillion dollar bills people are trying to hand to governments, begging them to take them, and it has taken months for them to notice and respond. Most still haven&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; David Manheim (@davidmanheim) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidmanheim/status/1255020027343966208?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 28, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Off the top of my head, testing capacity, tracing programs, monitoring / fixing international food supply bottlenecks, stopping trade wars, better directed small business relief programs, ramped-up unemployment benefits that don&amp;#39;t discourage work.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; David Manheim (@davidmanheim) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidmanheim/status/1255044177995485184?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 28, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;They realize. The problem is that legislation is getting written quickly, by committee, without flexibility, and can&amp;#39;t be renegotiated easily.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;That doesn&amp;#39;t mean these aren&amp;#39;t free trillion dollar bills, it means the country is so arthritic it can&amp;#39;t bend down to pick them up.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; David Manheim (@davidmanheim) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidmanheim/status/1255045943445147649?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 28, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been reading some more Mancur Olson. This is from a 1996 paper titled Big Bills Left on the Sidewalk: Why Some Nations are Rich, and Others Poor.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Public Good of Education</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/11/education-public-good.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Public Good of Education" /><published>2020-05-11T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-11T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/11/education-public-good</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/11/education-public-good.html">&lt;p&gt;From Mancur Olson’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Rise-Decline-Nations-Stagflation-Rigidities-ebook/dp/B00267SS7W/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Rise and Decline of Nations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Individuals in a few special vocations can receive considerable rewards in private goods if they acquire exceptional knowledge of public goods. Politicians, lobbyists, journalists, and social scientists, for example, may earn more money, power, or prestige from knowledge of this or that public business. Occasionally, exceptional knowledge of public policy can generate exceptional profits in stock exchanges or other markets. Withal, the typical citizen will find that his or her income and life chances will not be improved by zealous study of public affairs, or even of any single collective good. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
The limited knowledge of public affairs is in turn necessary to explain the effectiveness of lobbying. If all citizens had obtained and digested all pertinent information, they could not then be swayed by advertising or other persuasion. With perfectly informed citizens, elected officials would not be subject to the blandishments of lobbyists, since the constituents would then know if their interests were betrayed and defeat the unfaithful representative at the next election. Just as lobbies provide collective goods to special-interest groups, so their effectiveness is explained by the imperfect knowledge of citizens, and this in turn is due mainly to the fact that information and calculation about collective goods is also a collective good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A citizenry with limited knowledge of public affairs can thus fail to recognize how various interest groups (dubbed &lt;em&gt;distributional coalitions&lt;/em&gt; by Olson) are advancing their own agenda at the expense of society at large. This is a great argument in favor of an education that is not purely designed to get people higher wages. A singular focus on economic return is a flaw in many critiques of education today. However, education can just as well exacerbate the problem of the accumulation of distributional coalitions. Still from Olson:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If a society mainly rewards production or the capacity to satisfy those with whom one engages in free exchange, it stimulates the development of productive traits. It does this particularly through cultural or Lamarckian evolution, whereby learned or acquired behavior can be passed on to descendants. If the accumulation of distributional coalitions increases the incentive for distributional struggle, augments regulatory complexity, encourages the dominance of politics, stimulates bargaining, and increases the complexity of understandings, this encourages the development of different attitudes and attributes. What we loosely call intelligence, or aptitude for education, will probably be favored as much as or more than before because the articulate and educated have a comparative advantage in regulation, politics, and complex understandings. This, in turn, probably limits the extent to which intellectuals oppose their elaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, a greater demand for education can also be a sign of an increasingly dysfunctional and sclerotic economy. Not only that, educational credentialing is in fact often a tool used by distributional coalitions. Olson gives the example of medicine and law:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If the number of physicians increases, for example, the earnings of physicians must decline if other things are equal, and in country after country one finds that the professional organizations representing physicians work to limit entry into the profession. As the high income-levels of physicians in many countries testify, these efforts often succeed. The educational credentials and qualifying examinations usually required of those who would enter the practice of medicine are, of course, explained as necessary to protect the patient against incompetence. But note that the examinations are almost always imposed only on entrants. If the limits were mainly motivated by the interest of patients, older physicians would also be required to pass periodic qualifying examinations to demonstrate that they have kept their medical knowledge up-to-date. Among lawyers and other professionals in many countries there are similar limitations on entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2018/11/23/the-case-for-dropping-out-of-college/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Case For Dropping Out of College&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I also made the argument that the whole higher education system has become in large part a zero-sum credentialing competition that entrenches racial and class inequalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ideal education system should serve as a counterweight to a society’s tendency to develop rent-seeking organizations. In the current system however, it seems that universities have more of an enabling function, and have devolved into rent-seeking institutions themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">From Mancur Olson’s The Rise and Decline of Nations:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Single Best Policy to Combat Climate Change</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/24/climate-change.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Single Best Policy to Combat Climate Change" /><published>2020-04-24T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-24T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/24/climate-change</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/24/climate-change.html">&lt;p&gt;The single best policy to combat climate change is an internationally enforced carbon tax. There is pretty much a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-01-17/from-greenspan-to-yellen-economic-brain-trust-backs-carbon-tax&quot;&gt;consensus&lt;/a&gt; on this among economists. But despite the fact that the experts agree, and that the issue of climate change is of great public interest, there seems to be almost no discussion of this policy in mainstream circles. William Nordhaus, winner of the 2018 economics Nobel prize, is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/united-states/2020-04-10/climate-club&quot;&gt;finally writing about his “climate club”&lt;/a&gt; proposal, for this year’s May/June issue of Foreign Affairs. All I could find before that, outside of academic publications, was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/2018/10/10/17959686/carbon-tax&quot;&gt;post by Matthew Yglesias&lt;/a&gt; on Vox:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt; to happen is that the US sits down with the European Union and Japan and decides on a carbon tax. The initial tax should be low, but it should be set to escalate. And the three big players in the global economy should also agree to impose a fairly stiff tariff on any country that doesn’t agree to join the carbon tax club.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Right away, a bunch of countries will want to join the club, and with each new country that joins, staying out of the club becomes costlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That pretty much sums it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked on YouTube, and there seems to be no good videos explaining a carbon tax. These two are the best I could find:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zD64kaTY5Vg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CilVymuAM8A&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
They are alright, but it could be explained much better. This from MRU is on cap and trade, not carbon tax, but it has a clearer explanation of the economics involved:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9tUb3MDrgEc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in none of these is there mention of how a carbon tax might be enforced at an international level. Why isn’t there anything better on this? This is an issue that has led millions, across the globe, to protest. It’s supposed to be one of the biggest issues of our time. Yet, the best policy solution seems to barely be discussed outside of academic economics papers. What are the billions going to higher education doing? What happened to educating the public?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in his post, Yglesias wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But activists, unlike me, need to find a politics that actually works politically. I think it’s pretty clear that this wonky pitch has failed, over and over again, in a range of times and places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he then goes on to praise the Green New Deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.econlib.org/if-the-only-way-you-can-get-your-great-idea-implemented/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; by Bryan Caplan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When you look at the real world, though, you see something strange: Almost &lt;em&gt;no one&lt;/em&gt; actually pushes for the textbooks’ clever-and-appealing policy proposals.  Instead, the people inspired by the textbooks routinely attach themselves to trendy-but-awful policy proposals.  If you point out the discrepancy, they’re often too annoyed to respond.  When they do, reformers shrug and say: “The clever-and-appealing policy never has – and probably never will – have much political support.  So we have to do this instead.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The moral: If the only way you can get your great idea implemented is to mutilate it and/or package it with a pile of expensive junk, you really should wonder, “Is it still worth it?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beyond that, what pitch is Yglesias talking about? The public was never pitched. No one has ever heard of the “climate club” proposal. There never has been a serious attempt to educate the public on this. I mean, how hard can it be to create a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/Kurzgesagt&quot;&gt;Kurzgesagt&lt;/a&gt; type video explaining the “climate club” proposal? That would really be the minimum. Academic institutions aren’t even trying. And people who know better have already given up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WWM9gIVvm78&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; about a carbon tax with the most views at the moment is barely longer than a minute and has under half a million views. Meanwhile, the latest Michael Moore &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Zk11vI-7czE&quot;&gt;documentary&lt;/a&gt;, promoting population control as a solution to climate change, has already 1.5M views. It lasts 1h40 and was released 3 days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If higher education is not going to educate the public, someone else will.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">The single best policy to combat climate change is an internationally enforced carbon tax. There is pretty much a consensus on this among economists. But despite the fact that the experts agree, and that the issue of climate change is of great public interest, there seems to be almost no discussion of this policy in mainstream circles. William Nordhaus, winner of the 2018 economics Nobel prize, is finally writing about his “climate club” proposal, for this year’s May/June issue of Foreign Affairs. All I could find before that, outside of academic publications, was a post by Matthew Yglesias on Vox:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Online Standardized Tests Are a Bad Idea</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/17/online-standardized-tests.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online Standardized Tests Are a Bad Idea" /><published>2020-04-17T10:05:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-17T10:05:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/17/online-standardized-tests</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/17/online-standardized-tests.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The SAT and rival ACT, the nation’s most important college entrance exams, are taking steps to offer their tests online and at students’ homes later this year in an unprecedented move that will require massive amounts of digital proctoring to prevent cheating, officials announced Wednesday. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Emergency backup plans are being developed by both influential testing organizations if schools remain closed in the fall, preventing the usual in-school testing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If the coronavirus crisis persists, the College Board, the organization that sponsors the SAT, said it is preparing for an online, at-home offering of the exam that would implement technology that monitors movement and sound of possible cheating activities and also locks down access to other sites on the Internet during testing. Such online SAT exams previously have been used at some school districts and wider versions are already being tested.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“While the idea of at-home SAT testing is new, digital delivery of the test is not,” College Board CEO David Coleman said in a statement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;https://edsource.org/2020/sat-and-act-plan-at-home-college-admissions-exams-during-health-crisis/629182&quot;&gt;EdSource&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very skeptical of this move. Online education has enormous promise, and I think that it will ultimately replace the vast majority of in-person education. Notwithstanding the bad experience of many students who, because of COVID19, have to endure an improvised online version of their previously in-person classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, testing and credentialing will probably not make that transition anytime soon. The problem is that the more a test matters and is important for a student’s future, the greater the incentive is to cheat. And the stakes of the SAT are (or appear to be) quite high. With a great enough incentive, no software or digital monitoring will prove good enough to prevent cheating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A webcam and a microphone will never provide enough information of the surrounding environment. And if Apple hasn’t found a way to stop people from jailbreaking their devices, and video game creators haven’t figured out a reliable way to prevent people from pirating their games, the idea that anyone is going to come up with a software solution to ensure the integrity of online tests seems laughable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also why I think that anyone wanting to create a degree-equivalent standardized test (as I argue for &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/05/what-i-learned-dropping-out-of-high-school.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/10/pinker-on-education.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), will have to stick to in-person test proctoring. At least if they want their test to carry a high signaling value. That also explains to some extent why online degree programs haven’t been more popular, and are viewed with some skepticism by employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future of learning is on the internet, but credentialing will probably remain offline.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">The SAT and rival ACT, the nation’s most important college entrance exams, are taking steps to offer their tests online and at students’ homes later this year in an unprecedented move that will require massive amounts of digital proctoring to prevent cheating, officials announced Wednesday. Emergency backup plans are being developed by both influential testing organizations if schools remain closed in the fall, preventing the usual in-school testing. If the coronavirus crisis persists, the College Board, the organization that sponsors the SAT, said it is preparing for an online, at-home offering of the exam that would implement technology that monitors movement and sound of possible cheating activities and also locks down access to other sites on the Internet during testing. Such online SAT exams previously have been used at some school districts and wider versions are already being tested. “While the idea of at-home SAT testing is new, digital delivery of the test is not,” College Board CEO David Coleman said in a statement</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Questions to Guide Life and Learning</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/15/guiding-questions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Questions to Guide Life and Learning" /><published>2020-04-15T10:05:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-15T10:05:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/15/guiding-questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/15/guiding-questions.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-worth-knowing&quot;&gt;What’s Worth Knowing?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Teaching-Subversive-Activity-Neil-Postman/dp/0385290098&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teaching as a Subversive Activity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Neil Postman and Charles Weingartner suggest the following exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Suppose all the syllabi and curricula and textbooks in the schools disappeared. Suppose all of the standardized tests – city-wide, state-wide and national – were lost. In other words, suppose that the most common material impeding innovation in the schools simply did not exist. Then suppose that you decided to turn this ‘catastrophe’ into an opportunity to increase the relevance of the schools. What would you do? &lt;br /&gt;
We have a possibility for you to consider: suppose that you decide to have the entire ‘curriculum’ consist of questions. These questions would have to be worth seeking answers to not only from your point of view but, more importantly, from the point of view of the students. In order to get still closer to reality, add the requirement that the questions must help the students to develop and internalize concepts that will help them to survive in the rapidly changing world of the present and future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They then encourage the reader to write down a list of questions, and propose their own list. Here are some of the best ones:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;If you had an important idea that you wanted to let everyone (in the world) know about, how might you go about letting them know?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What bothers you most about adults? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How do you want to be similar to or different from adults you know when you become an adult?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What, if anything, seems to you to be worth dying for?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How did you come to believe this?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What seems worth living for?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How did you come to believe this?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;At the present moment, what would you most like to be – or be able to do? Why? What would you have to know in order to be able to to do it? What would you have to do in order to get to know it?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How can you tell ‘good guys’ from ‘bad guys’?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How can ‘good’ be distinguished from ‘evil’?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What kind of person would you most like to be? How might you get to be this kind of person?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Where does knowledge come from?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What do you think are some of man’s most important ideas? Where did they come from? Why? How? Now what?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What’s a ‘good idea’?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How do you know when a good or live idea becomes a bad or dead idea?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Which of man’s ideas would we be better off forgetting? How do you decide?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What is ‘progress’?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the relationships between new ideas and change?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Where do &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; ideas come from? How come? So what?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Of the important changes going on in our society, which should be encouraged and which resisted? Why? How?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What would you change if you could? How might you go about it? Of those changes which are going to occur, which would you stop if you could? Why? How? So what?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Who do you think has the most important things to say today? To whom? How? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the dumbest and most dangerous ideas that are ‘popular’ today? Why do you thing so? Where did these ideas come from?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the conditions necessary for life to survive? Plants? Animals? Humans?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the greatest threats to all forms of life? To plants? To animals? To humans?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What does man’s language permit him to develop as survival strategies that animals cannot develop?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What other ‘languages’ does man have besides those consisting of words?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are some good symbols? Some bad?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What’s worth knowing? How do you decide? What are some ways to go about getting to know what’s worth knowing?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason these questions should be thought about during one’s education, and beyond, is because they lead one to consider what issues are important from a societal and civilizational perspective, and can guide one on the path to a meaningful life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-will-you-measure-your-life&quot;&gt;How Will You Measure Your Life?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clayton Christensen, in his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/How-Will-Measure-Your-Life/dp/0062102419&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Will You Measure Your Life?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (another question worth thinking about), observes how many of his classmates at the Harvard Buisness School ended up unhappy despite great professional success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Behind the facade of professional success, there were many who did not enjoy what they were doing for a living. There were, also, numerous stories of divorces or unhappy marriages. I remember one classmate who hadn’t talked to his children in years, who was now living on the opposite coast from them. Another was on her third marriage since we’d graduated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the time, I assumed it was a blip; a kind of midlife crisis. But at our twenty-five- and thirty-year reunions, the problems were worse. One of our classmates—Jeffrey Skilling—had landed in jail for his role in the Enron scandal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christensen then attempts to answer the following 3 questions using lessons he learned studying buisnesses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How can I be sure that&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I will be successful and happy in my career?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;My relationships with my spouse, my children, and my extended family and close friends become an enduring source of happiness?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I live a life of integrity—and stay out of jail?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the epilogue, he stresses the importance of purpose:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Without a purpose, the value to executives of any business theory would be limited. Even though theory is able to predict the possible outcomes of an important decision, on what basis would the executives be deciding among them to determine which is the best outcome? […] &lt;br /&gt;
In a similar way, to maximize the value of the advice in this book, you must have a purpose in your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And proposes another question, crucial in finding a purpose worth commiting to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Who do I truly want to become?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might make a post at some point about some of the most interesting ideas in this book. But for now, I encourage you to consider some of these questions, and try to come up with your own answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-are-the-most-important-questions-in-your-life&quot;&gt;What Are The Most Important Questions In Your Life?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mathematician Richard Hamming had another set of great questions. Here’s from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/hamming.html&quot;&gt;transcript of a 1986 talk&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Over on the other side of the dining hall was a chemistry table. I had worked with one of the fellows, Dave McCall; furthermore he was courting our secretary at the time. I went over and said, “Do you mind if I join you?” They can’t say no, so I started eating with them for a while. And I started asking, &lt;strong&gt;“What are the important problems of your field?”&lt;/strong&gt; And after a week or so, “What important problems are you working on?” And after some more time I came in one day and said, &lt;strong&gt;“If what you are doing is not important, and if you don’t think it is going to lead to something important, why are you at Bell Labs working on it?”&lt;/strong&gt; I wasn’t welcomed after that; I had to find somebody else to eat with!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(emphasis is mine)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line of inquiry is targeted at researchers, but it can also be applied to one’s life. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rationality.org/&quot;&gt;Center For Applied Rationality&lt;/a&gt; (CFAR) has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/the-hamming-question-boston-edition-tickets-16449605212&quot;&gt;turned&lt;/a&gt; the question into:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What are the most important questions in our lives (or in our organizations/work), and why aren’t we working on them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, if none of the questions I listed above seemed compelling, this modified Hamming question should give you some food for thought. 
I think most people don’t spend enough time wondering if the path of least resistance is actually the best one. So going for a walk, and pondering on one or more of these questions does seem like a good investment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">What’s Worth Knowing?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Steven Pinker Could Become Really Rich</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/10/pinker-on-education.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Steven Pinker Could Become Really Rich" /><published>2020-04-10T11:53:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-10T11:53:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/10/pinker-on-education</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/10/pinker-on-education.html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://newrepublic.com/article/119321/harvard-ivy-league-should-judge-students-standardized-tests&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Trouble With Harvard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Steven Pinker has some thoughts on what an education should entail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think we can be more specific. It seems to me that educated people should know something about the 13-billion-year prehistory of our species and the basic laws governing the physical and living world, including our bodies and brains. They should grasp the timeline of human history from the dawn of agriculture to the present. They should be exposed to the diversity of human cultures, and the major systems of belief and value with which they have made sense of their lives. They should know about the formative events in human history, including the blunders we can hope not to repeat. They should understand the principles behind democratic governance and the rule of law. They should know how to appreciate works of fiction and art as sources of aesthetic pleasure and as impetuses to reflect on the human condition. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
On top of this knowledge, a liberal education should make certain habits of rationality second nature. Educated people should be able to express complex ideas in clear writing and speech. They should appreciate that objective knowledge is a precious commodity, and know how to distinguish vetted fact from superstition, rumor, and unexamined conventional wisdom. They should know how to reason logically and statistically, avoiding the fallacies and biases to which the untutored human mind is vulnerable. They should think causally rather than magically, and know what it takes to distinguish causation from correlation and coincidence. They should be acutely aware of human fallibility, most notably their own, and appreciate that people who disagree with them are not stupid or evil. Accordingly, they should appreciate the value of trying to change minds by persuasion rather than intimidation or demagoguery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like these two paragraphs as they contrast with what one usually gets from people defending the value of a college education: vague verbiage like “students learn to think,” “become better citizens,” “have their mind expanded” or “become cultured.” And people are then rarely challenged to actually explain what they mean by that. Pinker agrees:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Any rethinking of elite university admissions must begin with an inkling of the goals of a university education. As the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mFblhcQjKeY&quot;&gt;song&lt;/a&gt; says, if you don’t know where you’re going, any road will take you there. One contributor to the admissions mess is that so few of a university’s thought leaders can say anything coherent about what those goals are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People, especially academics at elite universities, should get concrete about what an education ought to entail more often, as that then allows to create an independent test to check if a person is “educated,” using the standards laid out. If Pinker says that to get a Harvard degree you need to know X, Y and Z, then a comprehensive standardized test that checks if someone knows X, Y and Z, should be of equivalent prestige as a Harvard degree, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last part of the piece, Pinker goes on to make the case for the use of standardized tests in college admissions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Let’s daydream for a moment. If only we had some way to divine the suitability of a student for an elite education, without ethnic bias, undeserved advantages to the wealthy, or pointless gaming of the system. […] A sample of behavior that could be gathered quickly and cheaply, assessed objectively, and double-checked for its ability to predict the qualities we value….&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We do have this magic measuring stick, of course: it’s called standardized testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a standardized test is the most meritocratic way to figure out who should get admitted to university, then why wouldn’t it also be the best way to figure out who is “educated?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Pinker should do is quit Harvard, and create a rigorous and comprehensive standardized test, the Pinker Degree of Psychology, that would test all that a psychology major learns at Harvard. With his name and reputation behind it, it should carry as much prestige as an actual Harvard psychology degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he could charge virtually as much as he wants. A Harvard degree costs more than $200k. I’m sure a lot of people would love to pay $10k to get a degree that, according to one of Harvard’s most well known and respected professors, is equivalent to a Harvard bachelor’s degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe higher education will get fixed when prestigious professors realize that they don’t need the university to award diplomas. They can democratize education by simply accrediting students directly, and make a lot of money along the way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">In The Trouble With Harvard, Steven Pinker has some thoughts on what an education should entail:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The End of Education</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/end-of-education.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The End of Education" /><published>2020-04-06T10:05:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-06T10:05:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/end-of-education</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/end-of-education.html">&lt;p&gt;Me reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/End-Education-Redefining-Value-School/dp/0679750312&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The End of Education&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Neil Postman, was a bit of an accident. It was published in 1996 and its main topic is public education, K-12 specifically. So even though the topic of education does interest me a great deal, I don’t think I would have picked it up weren’t it for the fact that I stumbled on it on my mother’s bookshelf, and that the title seemed intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sets up the question of what the &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt; of education is, and tries to provide an answer. I found part II of the book, which focuses on possible answers, a little weak. I think that the narratives presented are too vague, outdated or incomplete. The first part however, which describes the problem, is excellent. Here are a few passages from the book that carry some of the best ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preface&quot;&gt;Preface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is as if we are a nation of technicians, consumed by our expertise in how something should be done, afraid or incapable of thinking about why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By giving the book its ambiguous title, I mean to suggest that without a transcendent and honorable purpose schooling must reach its finish, and the sooner we are done with it, the better. With such a purpose, schooling becomes the central institution through which the young may find reasons for continuing to educate themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-the-necessity-of-gods&quot;&gt;1. The Necessity of Gods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For school to make sense, the young, their parent, and their teachers must have a god to serve, or, even better, several gods. If they have none, school is pointless. Nietzsche’s famous aphorism is relevant here: “He who has a &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; to live can bear with almost any &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt;.” This applies as much to learning as to living.
	&lt;br /&gt;To put it simply, there is no surer way to bring an end to schooling than for it to have no end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By a god to serve, I do not necessarily mean &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A god, in the sense I am using the word, is the name of a great narrative, one that has sufficient credibility, complexity, and symbolic power to enable one to organize one’s life around it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The point is that, call them what you will, we are unceasing in creating histories and futures for ourselves through the medium of narrative. Without a narrative, life has no meaning. Without meaning, learning has no purpose. Without a purpose, schools are houses of detention, not attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What happens to people when they have no gods to serve? Some commit suicide. […] Some envelop themselves in drugs, including alcohol. Some take whatever pleasure is to be found in random violence. Some encase themselves in an impenetrable egoism. Many, apparently, find a momentary and pitiful release from dread in commercial re-creations of once powerful narratives of the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-some-gods-that-fail&quot;&gt;2. Some Gods That Fail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So far, America’s answer has largely been, Believe in a market economy, which is not much of a story, not much of an answer. The problem is that America’s better gods have been badly wounded. As America has moved towards the status of an empire […], its great story of liberal democracy has lost much of its luster. Of Tocqueville’s “civic participation,” there is less in America than in any other industrialized nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the narrative of the great melting-pot has also sufferend as many insults as an imperfect god can bear. For some , for example, Koreans, Chinese, and Russians, it has worked tolerable well, but too many others have been blocked from sharing in the fullness of the American promise because of their race or native language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As for the rigorous tale of the blessedness of Hard Work, too many Americans no longer believe in it. The great school of the Higher Learning, television, teaches them that a dream deferred is a dream forever denied – which is to say, no dream at all; that they are, in fact, entitled to the fruits of technology’s largesse; and that the god of Consumership confers its graciousness more freely than can any god of Labor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There was a time when educators became famous for providing reasons for learning; now they become famous for inventing a method. &lt;br /&gt;
	There are, of course, many things wrong with all of this, not least that it diverts attention from the important matters – for example, the fundamental simplicity of teaching and learning when both teacher and student share a reason for the enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, when the student shares the reason for the enterprise, learning becomes so simple that the student may even not need the teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It may properly go by the name of the god of Economic Utility. As its name suggests, it is a passionless god, cold and severe. But it makes a promise, and not a trivial one. Addressing the young, it offers a covenant of sorts with them: If you will pay attention in school, and do your homework, and score well on tests, and behave yourself, you will be rewarded with a well-paying job when you are done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The story goes on to preach that America is not so much a culture as it is an economy, and that the vitality of a nation’s economy rests on high standards of achievement and rigorous discipline in schools. There is little evidence (that is to say, none) that the productivity of a nation’s economy is related to the quality of its schooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bryan Caplan makes a similar argument. Because of credentialling, people spending more time in school do end up earning more, however this does not necessarily translate in better economic outcomes for the country as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One need hardly add that the story of the god of Economic Utility is rarely believed by students and certainly has almost no power to inspire them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many parents, in fact, are apt to like the idea of school as a primary training ground for future employment, as do many corporate executives. This is why the story of Economic Utility is told and re-told in television commercials and political speeches as the reason why children should go to school, and stay in school, and why schools should receive public support. &lt;br /&gt;
	But for all its widespread popularity, the god of Economic Utility is impotent to create satisfactory reasons for schooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Any education that is mainly &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; economic utility is far too limited to be useful, and, in any case, so diminishes the world that it mocks one’s humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I refer to the god of Consumership, whose basic moral axiom is expressed in the slogan “Whoever dies with the most toys, wins” – that is to say, goodness inheres in those who buy things; evil in those who do not. The similarity between this god and the god of Economic Utility is obvious, but with this difference: The latter postulates that you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; what you do for a living; the former that you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; what you accumulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is probably unnecessary to say that all traditional religions reject the god of Consumership, claiming that devotion to it is a false spirituality, if not outright blasphemy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-some-new-gods-that-fail&quot;&gt;3. Some New Gods That Fail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Schools are not now and have never been chiefly about getting information to children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that was the case, the internet would have made schools obsolete a long time ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One might even say that schools have never been essentially about individualized learning. It is true, of course, that groups do not learn; individuals do. But the idea of a school is that individuals must learn in a setting in which individual needs are subordinated to group interests. Unlike other media of mass communication, which celebrate individual response and are experienced in private, the classroom is intended to tame the ego, to connect the individual with others, to demonstrate the value and necessity of group cohesion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I refer to the fact that those who advocate a “multicultural” curriculum, especially those who speak for an Afrocentric bias, understand better than most […] the need for a god to serve; they understand that the reason why students are demoralized, bored, and distracted is not that the teachers lack interesting methods and machinery but that both students and teachers lack a narrative to provide profoud meaning to their lessons. It does not go too far to say that the “multiculturalists” are the most active and dedicated education philosophers we have at the moment. They are not especially interested in methods or machinery and, generally, are not competent to speak on such matters. But they have a story to tell, and they believe their story can serve as a foundation to schooling. The trouble is that it is a terrible story, at least for public schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This provides an interesting pespective on how the universities have found themselves embroiled in the culture wars. One of the reasons the wing of the progressive left focused on identity politics may have gotten such a strong foothold in educational institutions is that it describes one of the most compelling narratives available for education at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t be the &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/07/08/gay-rites-are-civil-rites/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://areomagazine.com/2018/12/18/postmodern-religion-and-the-faith-of-social-justice/&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; to observe that progressive identity politics can have a quasy religious character to it. And I don’t necessarily mean that in a bad way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But the point is that it is possible, by ignoring its transcendent ideals, to tell America’s story as a history of racism, inequity, and violence. Is this the story we wish to be the foundation of American public schooling?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-gods-that-may-serve&quot;&gt;4. Gods That May Serve&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-spaceship-earth&quot;&gt;The Spaceship Earth&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have here, then, a narrative of extraordinary potential: the story of human beings as stewards of the Earth, caretakers of a vulnerable space capsule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-fallen-angel&quot;&gt;The Fallen Angel&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I beseach you, in the bowels of Christ,” Oliver Cromwell pleaded, “think it possible that you may be mistaken.” That we may be mistaken, and probably are, is the meaning of the “fall” in the fallen angel. The meaning of “angel” is that we are capable of correcting our mistakes, provided we proceed without hubris, pride, or dogmatism; provided that we accept our cosmic status as the error-prone species.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the last program of his television series, Bronowsky is seen standing in a pond on the grounds of the old Auschwitz concentration camp. Near-overwrought by what Auschwitz symbolizes, he resorts, as so many have done before him, to a religious metaphor. “Into this pond,” he says, “were flushed the ashes of some four million people. And that was not done by gas. It was done by arrogance. It was done by dogma…. When people believe that they have absolute knowledge…. this is how they behave. This is what men do when they aspire to the knowledge of gods.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the clip:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ltjI3BXKBgY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-american-experiment&quot;&gt;The American Experiment&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But the story properly begins, as Abraham Lincoln saw it, with a series of stunning and dangerous questions. Is it possible to have a government of the people, by the people, and for the people? And who are the people, anyway? And how shall we protect individuals from the power of the people? And why should we do all this in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;America was the first nation to be argued into existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This, it seems to me, is a fine and noble story to offer as a reason for schooling: to provide our youth with the knowledge and will to participate in the great experiment; to teach them how to argue, and to help them discover what questions are worth arguing about; and, of course, to make sure they know what happens when arguments cease. No one is excluded from the story. Every group has made good arguments, and bad ones. All points are admissible. The only thing we have to fear is that someone will insist on putting in an exclamation point when we are not yet finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As national stories go, America may have one of the most compelling ones. However, I’m looking for something a bit more transcendent and universal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-law-of-diversity&quot;&gt;The Law of Diversity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We simply cannot enter the twenty-first century at each other’s throats…. We are at a crucial crossroads in the history of this nation – and we either hang together by combating these forces that divide and degrade us or we hang seperately.” I take this to be a heartfelt plea for the necessity of providing ourselves and especially our young with a comprehensive narrative that makes a constructive and unifying use of diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We learn about these people for two reasons: because they demonstrate how the vitality and creativity of humanity depend on diversity, and because they have set the standards to which civilized people adhere. The law of diversity thus makes intelligent humans of us all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-world-weaversthe-world-makers&quot;&gt;The World Weavers/The World Makers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One answer that can provide schooling with a profound organizing principle is that we use language to create the world – which is to say, language is not only a vehicle of thought; it is, as Wittgenstein said, also the driver. We go where it leads. We see the world as it permits us to see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are the world makers, and the world weavers. That is what makes us smart, and dumb; moral and immoral; tolerant and bigoted. That is what makes us human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are quite good. But I find all of them lacking in some way or another. The main issue I have with almost all of them is the vagueness. They offer some abstract ideals to live by, but none of them offers a truly concrete and inspiring purpose to education. At least to my eyes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">Me reading The End of Education, by Neil Postman, was a bit of an accident. It was published in 1996 and its main topic is public education, K-12 specifically. So even though the topic of education does interest me a great deal, I don’t think I would have picked it up weren’t it for the fact that I stumbled on it on my mother’s bookshelf, and that the title seemed intriguing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Quarantine Reading List</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/update-and-reading-list.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Quarantine Reading List" /><published>2020-04-06T10:05:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-06T10:05:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/update-and-reading-list</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/update-and-reading-list.html">&lt;p&gt;I currently have a piece in the pipeline that follows up on my &lt;a href=&quot;/education/2020/02/05/what-i-learned-dropping-out-of-high-school.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;. In it I offer a vision of what higher education could be like, I describe what I have been doing since dropping out of college, and I announce a project that would put my ideas into practice. However, the coronavirus situation has put my plans on hold for now. So you will probably get to read that piece once the circumstances are more auspicious to a project that involves getting people physically together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I might still reconsider, and post it before any of my ideas can feasably, or advisably, be put into practice. If there is anyone out there who is particularly curious about what I’ve been up to, or what I’m planning, you can DM me on Twitter, and I’ll share my draft with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I hope to make the most of the quarantine. In the coming weeks and months, I want to work on a post that examines the role that educational institutions should play, from a societal and civilizational perspective. Some of the key ideas that motivate this line of inquiry are contained in a 1995 book by Neil Postman, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/End-Education-Redefining-Value-School/dp/0679750312&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The End of Education&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and in a piece in The Atlantic by Patrick Collison and Tyler Cowen from last year: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/07/we-need-new-science-progress/594946/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;We Need a New Science of Progress&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postman’s key insight is that the purpose of education is in fact just as important, if not more important, than the method (more on this &lt;a href=&quot;/education/2020/04/06/end-of-education.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). This rings very true to me, since in my own learning, progress seems to have been greatest when I intrisically valued my learning, and found it meaningful. In my experience, the financial cost of the education seems to have no effect on the speed or quality of learning. In a world in which student debt in the US stands at more than $1.6 Trillion, this is quite a striking observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while I have a good idea of how education should work, I now want to answer the question of why. To help me with this, I have created reading list of books, papers and blog posts that I plan to go through in the coming weeks and months. Here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;books&quot;&gt;Books&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tyler Cowen, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Great-Stagnation-Low-Hanging-Eventually-eSpecial-ebook/dp/B004H0M8QS/&quot;&gt;The Great Stagnation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tyler Cowen, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Average-Over-Powering-America-Stagnation-ebook/dp/B00C1N5WOI/&quot;&gt;Average Is Over&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tyler Cowen, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Complacent-Class-Self-Defeating-Quest-American/dp/B06XR2W1CM/&quot;&gt;The Complacent Class&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Deresiewicz, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Excellent-Sheep-Miseducation-American-Meaningful-ebook/dp/B00GEEB960/&quot;&gt;Excellent Sheep&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francis Fukuyama, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Origins-Political-Order-Prehuman-Revolution/dp/B006QGIQ94/&quot;&gt;The Origins of Political Order&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francis Fukuyama, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B00LU3YM8C&quot;&gt;Political Order and Political Decay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mancur Olson, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Rise-Decline-Nations-Stagflation-Rigidities-ebook/dp/B00267SS7W/&quot;&gt;The Rise and Decline of Nations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jared Diamond, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Collapse-Societies-Choose-Fail-Succeed/dp/B00P2QCN2U/&quot;&gt;Collapse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daron Acemoglu and James Robinson, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Why-Nations-Fail-Origins-Prosperity/dp/B007MIXOEC/&quot;&gt;Why Nations Fail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eliezer Yudkowsky, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/s/oLGCcbnvabyibnG9d&quot;&gt;Inadequate Equilibria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert J. Gordon, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Rise-Fall-American-Growth-Standard/dp/B01ITPUXEU/&quot;&gt;The Rise and Fall of American Growth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon Gertner, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Idea-Factory-Great-American-Innovation/dp/0143122797&quot;&gt;The Idea Factory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might also revisit these two:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Deutsch, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Beginning-Infinity-Explanations-Transform-World/dp/B005HTYBCM/&quot;&gt;The Beginning of Infinity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joseph Henrich, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Secret-Our-Success-Evolution-Domesticating/dp/B07B53C56B/&quot;&gt;The Secret of Our Success&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;papersblog-postsother&quot;&gt;Papers/Blog posts/Other&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nicholas Bloom et al, &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.stanford.edu/~chadj/IdeaPF.pdf&quot;&gt;Are Ideas Getting Harder to Find?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pierre Azoulay et al, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w15466.pdf&quot;&gt;Incentives and Creativity: Evidence from the Academic Life Sciences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay Bhattacharya et al, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w26752.pdf&quot;&gt;Stagnation and Scientific Incentives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dominic Cummings, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dominiccummings.files.wordpress.com/2013/11/20130825-some-thoughts-on-education-and-political-priorities-version-2-final.pdf&quot;&gt;Some thoughts on education and political priorities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dominic Cummings, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dominiccummings.files.wordpress.com/2017/02/201702-effective-action-2-systems-engineering-to-systems-politics.pdf&quot;&gt;The unrecognised simplicities of effective action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LessWrong, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/zhPGbnAhgqFsCDK4C/how-to-fix-academia&quot;&gt;How to fix academia?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LessWrong, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/x2fkoZMuMNhBashH4/academia-as-a-career-option-its-social-value-and&quot;&gt;Academia as a career option, its social value, and alternatives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LessWrong, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/gZgjqrotKyCJR9zGq/why-academic-papers-are-a-terrible-discussion-forum&quot;&gt;Why Academic Papers Are A Terrible Discussion Forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LessWrong, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/xQ9tMMk3RArodLtDq/intellectual-progress-inside-and-outside-academia&quot;&gt;Intellectual Progress Inside and Outside Academia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eli Dourado, &lt;a href=&quot;https://elidourado.com/blog/move-the-needle-on-progress/&quot;&gt;How do we move the needle on progress?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nintil, &lt;a href=&quot;https://nintil.com/progress-in-progress/&quot;&gt;About the ‘Progress’ in Progress Studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francis Jervis, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.progressstudies.org/2019/08/09/manifesto/&quot;&gt;A Progress Studies Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Archbridge Institute, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@ArchbridgeInst/reflections-on-studying-human-flourishing-and-progress-shared-challenges-and-shared-potential-45f277572f30&quot;&gt;Reflections on Studying Human Flourishing and Progress: Shared Challenges and Shared Potential&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Fallows, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/1993/12/how-the-world-works/305854/&quot;&gt;How the World Works&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Hamming, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/hamming.html&quot;&gt;You and Your Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Many of these are taken from Patrick Collison’s site, &lt;a href=&quot;https://patrickcollison.com/progress&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://patrickcollison.com/growth&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://patrickcollison.com/fast&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might also end up drawing on these two lists, also found through Collison’s site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt Clancy, &lt;a href=&quot;http://matt-clancy.com/economics-of-innovation-detailed-reading-list/&quot;&gt;Economics of Innovation: Detailed Reading List&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jasmine Wang, &lt;a href=&quot;https://jasminew.me/post/progress/&quot;&gt;[Normative] Progress Studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">I currently have a piece in the pipeline that follows up on my previous post. In it I offer a vision of what higher education could be like, I describe what I have been doing since dropping out of college, and I announce a project that would put my ideas into practice. However, the coronavirus situation has put my plans on hold for now. So you will probably get to read that piece once the circumstances are more auspicious to a project that involves getting people physically together. Though I might still reconsider, and post it before any of my ideas can feasably, or advisably, be put into practice. If there is anyone out there who is particularly curious about what I’ve been up to, or what I’m planning, you can DM me on Twitter, and I’ll share my draft with you.</summary></entry></feed>