<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thememeticist.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thememeticist.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-28T13:33:33+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Memeticist</title><subtitle>Memes worth spreading </subtitle><entry><title type="html">List of Peter Thiel’s Online Writings</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/other/2020/07/28/thiel-online-writing-list.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="List of Peter Thiel's Online Writings" /><published>2020-07-28T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-07-28T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/other/2020/07/28/thiel-online-writing-list</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/other/2020/07/28/thiel-online-writing-list.html">&lt;p&gt;This 100 page document has recently made the rounds: &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1zao_AyBhNb8TPWrQqgXn5NzNAgfEqzTIaFYos7wdqGI/edit#&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thiel on Progress and Stagnation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Despite looking quite comprehensive, I was surprised to see that quite a few of Thiel’s online writings were absent from the references section. Maybe the creators of the document left those out on purpose, but I suspect they might just not have been aware of them. A lot of Thiel’s online writings appear in relatively obscure places, and I haven’t been able to find a good list that includes all of them. So here is a list of everything Peter Thiel has &lt;em&gt;written online&lt;/em&gt;, as far as I’m aware of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.firstthings.com/article/2007/11/spending-the-future&quot;&gt;Spending the Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.firstthings.com/article/2015/06/against-edenism&quot;&gt;Against Edenism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.firstthings.com/article/2020/03/back-to-the-future&quot;&gt;Back to the Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/2014/09/run-startup-like-cult-heres/&quot;&gt;You Should Run Your Startup Like a Cult. Here’s How&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hoover.org/research/optimistic-thought-experiment&quot;&gt;The Optimistic Thought Experiment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2015/11/28/opinion/the-new-atomic-age-we-need.html&quot;&gt;The New Atomic Age We Need&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/08/16/opinion/peter-thiel-the-online-privacy-debate-wont-end-with-gawker.html&quot;&gt;Peter Thiel: The Online Privacy Debate Won’t End With Gawker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/08/01/opinion/peter-thiel-google.html&quot;&gt;Good for Google, Bad for America&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cato-unbound.org/2009/04/13/peter-thiel/education-libertarian&quot;&gt;The Education of a Libertarian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evernote.com/shard/s542/client/snv?noteGuid=46c636b6-b404-45df-ab0a-1f84c6fdc8c2&amp;amp;noteKey=7c94233539b8258d72b395a063f3c589&amp;amp;sn=https://www.evernote.com/shard/s542/sh/46c636b6-b404-45df-ab0a-1f84c6fdc8c2/7c94233539b8258d72b395a063f3c589&amp;amp;title=That+Essay&quot;&gt;The Straussian Moment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalreview.com/2011/10/end-future-peter-thiel/&quot;&gt;The End of the Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can comment or DM me if I’m missing anything.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">This 100 page document has recently made the rounds: Thiel on Progress and Stagnation. Despite looking quite comprehensive, I was surprised to see that quite a few of Thiel’s online writings were absent from the references section. Maybe the creators of the document left those out on purpose, but I suspect they might just not have been aware of them. A lot of Thiel’s online writings appear in relatively obscure places, and I haven’t been able to find a good list that includes all of them. So here is a list of everything Peter Thiel has written online, as far as I’m aware of:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Patrick Collison on Effective Altruism</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/ea/2020/06/23/patrick-collison-on-effective-altruism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patrick Collison on Effective Altruism" /><published>2020-06-23T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-23T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/ea/2020/06/23/patrick-collison-on-effective-altruism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/ea/2020/06/23/patrick-collison-on-effective-altruism.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.effectivealtruism.org/posts/xBBXf7KXZCKHYBxeZ/patrick-collison-on-effective-altruism&quot;&gt;Crossposted&lt;/a&gt; on the EA Forum.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effective Altruism came up in a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/8rxS6kj5Zt0?t=1785&quot;&gt;discussion between Patrick Collison and Jason Crawford&lt;/a&gt; on the topic of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/07/we-need-new-science-progress/594946/&quot;&gt;Progress Studies&lt;/a&gt;. This is a transcript of the relevant passage. Edited for clarity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jason Crawford:&lt;/strong&gt; So compare and contrast the effective altruism movement with progress studies, and I would love to hear you comment on the notion of existential risk or global catastrophic risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patrick Collison:&lt;/strong&gt; On EA… Well… with anything that’s a kind of a totalizing framework and I don’t mean that pejoratively, I just mean that in principle everyone could have an EA mindset and I’m sure at least some EA members think that everyone should have an EA oriented mindset. And so you can then sort of ask the question of well, would it be good for everyone to have an EA mindset? But of course the other way of asking it is, is EA on the current margin a good new way for people to be thinking and would it be good, if instead of zero people before the EA movement to be thinking in an EA oriented fashion, would it be good for 5% of people or for 10% of people to be thinking that way? And in the latter sense, was it a good shift on the margin? I think EA has been great and I’m sort-of delighted that they have had the progress they they’ve had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now if the question is, should everyone be an EA or even, I guess in the individual sense, am I or do I think I should be an EA? I think – and obviously there’s kind of heterogeneity within the field – but my general sense is that the EA movement is always very focused on kind of rigid, not rigid, that’s that’s unfair perhaps, but on sort of, estimation, analytical, quantification, and sort of utilitarian calculation, and I think that that as a practical matter that means that you end up too focused on that which you can measure, which again means – or as a practical matter means – you’re too focus on things that are sort of short-term like bed nets or deworming or whatever being obvious examples. And are those good causes? I would say almost definitely yes, obviously. Now we’ve seen some new data over the last couple of years that maybe they’re not as good as they initially seemed but they’re very likely to be really good things to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s hard for me to see how, you know, writing a treatise of human nature would score really highly in an EA oriented framework. As assessed ex-post that looked like a really valuable thing for Hume to do. And similarly, as we have a look at the things that in hindsight seem like very good things to have happen in the world, it’s often unclear to me how an EA oriented intuition might have caused somebody to do so. And so I guess I think of EA as sort of like a metal detector, and they’ve invented a new kind of metal detector that’s really good at detecting some metals that other detectors are not very good at detecting. But I actually think we need some diversity in the different metallic substances which our detectors are attuned to, and for me EA would not be the only one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jason Crawford:&lt;/strong&gt; Good metaphor. And what about the particular concerns about global catastrophic risk or existential risks especially from technology. This is where I get sort of the most, I won’t even say push back exactly, but concern from people about progress studies, is the question of, if we just run full throttle with progress what about the risk of, we’re just not careful enough and we get some catastrophe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patrick Collison:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I think it is probably true that the optimal rate of technological change is not monotonically better the more that there is. There probably are kind of shear forces with society at a certain point. I think the question is to, as a practical matter should our concern be having too much or having too little. And actually, I should say I don’t want to conflate ‘progress’ in progress studies with purely technological advancement, but it’s still a significant part of it. And generally I think, looking historically I think that too little has been a problem far more frequently than too much. I think that today in many super obvious ways we have… too many lives are not as good as they obviously could be, and so in a very tangible sense we have too little progress, and I think there are very valid ways in which one could imagine having too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I guess, I feel sort of, for every one unit of concern I give to ‘too much’ I give it four or five to ‘we have too little.’ Now there is an asymmetry there where the existential risks are, by definition, existential and I thought Toby Ord’s book was a great contribution. Broadly I think the existential risks folks, again, have introduced a good line of thinking that we really should be taking seriously. I suspect that it’s possible to mitigate most of those risks relatively effectively without redirecting vast swathes of society and I think the more difficult problem will actually be how do we generate enough.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">Crossposted on the EA Forum.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Students Are Employees</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/06/05/students-are-employees.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Students Are Employees" /><published>2020-06-05T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-06-05T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/06/05/students-are-employees</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/06/05/students-are-employees.html">&lt;p&gt;Education is a peculiar good. The usual model of private education is that the students are the consumers, the professors are the employees, and the lectures are the product. Students pay to receive the education they want. In reality, students pay more for the degree than the education. But let’s assume for now that education is all about increasing human capital, rather than being mostly about &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2018/11/23/the-case-for-dropping-out-of-college/&quot;&gt;signaling&lt;/a&gt;. For the sake of argument, let’s assume that I’m talking about an education start-up that doesn’t grant any kind of degree or certification, and is solely focused on the students’ learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, the model describing students as the consumer is still missing something important. The problem is that modeling students as simple homo economicus agents is not perfect. As the field of behavioral economics has extensively documented, humans aren’t perfectly rational, self-interested, utility-maximizing agents. And education seems to be one of the fields where the homo economicus model is most misleading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With education, a better model is the one of the elephant and the rider described by Jonathan Haidt in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Happiness-Hypothesis-Putting-Ancient-Science-ebook/dp/B00YY05O7G/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Happiness Hypothesis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. He explains it thus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The rider can see farther into the future, and the rider can learn valuable information by talking to other riders or by reading maps, but the rider cannot order the elephant around against its will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The rider […] is conscious, controlled thought. The elephant, in contrast, is everything else. The elephant includes the gut feelings, visceral reactions, emotions, and intuitions that comprise much of the automatic system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When everything works well, it does look like the rider is in control. But sometimes things go wrong, and then it becomes apparent that really, the elephant is the one in control. Depression and addiction are the two main examples of when the rider is obviously not in charge anymore. Haidt describes the rider as more of an “advisor,” capable of nudging the elephant in the right direction, but incapable of just ordering the elephant around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rider also has the role of lawyer. If you eat a piece of cake even though the diet you’re trying to stick to forbids it, the rider might start trying to justify it. “I totally meant to do that.” - “It’s fine, I’ll eat less tomorrow.” - “This diet is dumb anyways.” Self-justification is the rider pretending that he’s still in control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that humans have a unified self is one thing that both the homo economicus model and most people’s model of themselves have in common. Self-justification is one way that people resolve the cognitive dissonance that arises when the model of the unified, in control, self is challenged by evidence that the self is more like a rider on an elephant with a mind of its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is not to say that the model of the rider and the elephant is the “correct” way of understanding the mind. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/All_models_are_wrong&quot;&gt;All models are wrong, but some are useful.&lt;/a&gt; So take it with a grain of salt. You probably should use the unified model of the self in most settings, especially in the ones involving other people. No court of law is going to accept the excuse “the elephant did it.” Nor should it. The same goes for broken personal commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assumption that people are unified, responsible, agents is what makes society work. However, coming to terms with the fact that this model of individuals is flawed is just as important. Appeals to individual agency might work in most cases, but when trying to deal with depression or addiction, the assumption that people are always in control can be counterproductive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how does this relate to education? Well, for one thing, this model explains why online education hasn’t made in-person education obsolete yet. The fact that it’s much harder to get recognition for things self-learned online is part of the reason. But just as important is the fact that self-learning online is really hard. MOOCs’ completion rates are around 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, some people starting MOOCs don’t intend to finish them in the first place. But I’m certain that a significant share of those who don’t complete, did mean to finish when they first started. At the beginning, the rider managed to nudge the elephant onto the steep path that is learning anything challenging. The rider thought that the view on top would be incredible and managed to infect the elephant with the excitement that comes with the vision of achieving something ambitious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point along the track, however, the elephant gives up. All the elephant sees, is an arduous, unrewarding path ahead. The rider tries to convince the elephant to continue. He argues that the effort is worth it. He explains that he will be very disappointed if they don’t go ahead. To no avail. The elephant has started watching Netflix, and the rider gives up and joins the elephant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been there, and I suspect that anyone who has attempted anything difficult on their own will recognize themselves in this story. So, what is the solution? The self-help literature is full of advice on how to overcome this. Habits, to-do lists, separate work and leisure spaces… Self-help literature is all about advice to empower the rider to get the elephant to do what the rider wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One self-help service that takes this elephant and rider theory of the mind very seriously, is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.beeminder.com/&quot;&gt;Beeminder&lt;/a&gt;. It relies on the fact that the elephant really hates losing money. Beeminder allows you to make goals, track them, and if you fail to meet the set target, Beeminder takes a preset amount of money out of your bank account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sounds insane to anyone having a model of the self as unified and in control. With the elephant and rider model however, it makes sense. The rider is extorting the elephant. He threatens the elephant with sending money to Beeminder unless the rider’s demands are met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it works, to some extent. I have been using it for almost 2 years now to keep me writing a certain minimum amount of words in a personal diary. The document is now close to 400k words long. And I have paid $15 to Beeminder (3x$5). However, I also have entered fake data a few times. Beeminder works best when there’s independent verification. For example, a running app connected to beeminder to provide reliable data on the distance run. Absent that, the best one can do is to attempt to be strict and to never allow the elephant to enter any fake data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there a better way? Certainly. Something that much of the self-help literature misses is that taming the elephant is really a social activity. Humans have a deep-seated compulsion to conform to societal expectations, a strong desire for validation by peers and an instinctual impulse to obey authority figures. Thus, just as the rider can take advantage of the elephant’s aversion of short-term financial losses, he can also lead the elephant into situations in which the elephant will feel strongly motivated by social factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One technique that uses that insight is the accountability buddy system. It uses the fact that it is significantly harder to renege on a public commitment than one that remains hidden within one’s mind. The elephant hates the embarrassment that comes with publicly declaring one’s intention to do something, but then failing to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the extent that schools enable learning, it is also because of this. People learn from an early age that good grades are synonymous with approval and praise by both teachers and parents, while bad grades are usually met with opprobrium and disappointment. Thus, students will be able to expend a great deal of effort to prepare for an exam in some random subject they find uninteresting and won’t ever use. However, the same amount of effort can be extremely difficult to come up with when outside an educational institution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Average-Over-Powering-America-Stagnation-ebook/dp/B00C1N5WOI&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Average Is Over&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Tyler Cowen echoes a similar idea:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It will become increasingly apparent how much of current education is driven by human weakness, namely the inability of most students to simply sit down and try to learn something on their own. It’s a common claim that you can’t replace professors with Nobel-quality YouTube lectures because the professor, and perhaps also the classroom setting, is required to motivate most of the students. Fair enough, but let’s take this seriously. The professor is then a motivator first and foremost. Let’s hire good motivators. Let’s teach our professors how to motivate. Let’s judge them on that basis. Let’s treat professors more like athletic coaches, personal therapists, and preachers, because that is what they will evolve to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, the primary role of the hypothetical education start-up I mentioned at the beginning would be to motivate the elephant. Just like Beeminder, it would be used by the rider to get the elephant to do what the rider wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Universities do partly fulfill this function. However, as I mentioned at the beginning, the fact that the average student is more motivated by the degree than the education, makes it a poor example of what an organization solely focused on education would look like. The average professor is a mediocre motivator, whose main tool is the threat of a lower GPA and the impediment to degree completion, and students have only limited freedom to choose what and how to learn. I will explore these points further in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does this translate to the economic model? In light of this understanding of how and why educational institutions work, a more accurate model of education would put the rider as the consumer, the elephant as the employee, and the professor as the manager. Even in the best educational institutions, if the student doesn’t study, if the elephant isn’t motivated, the student isn’t going to learn anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An education isn’t something the professor makes and the student receives. It is something the student creates, and the professor’s role is to make sure that the student stays on track. In the end, the students are the ones creating the value. By studying, reading, doing their homework, students are the main contributors to the value created in educational institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;employees-are-students&quot;&gt;Employees Are Students&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Viewing students as both the consumers and the employees also raises an interesting question: where lies the dividing line between being a student and being an employee? To illustrate this point more clearly, take the case of unpaid internships that some students take as part of their degree program. It is not uncommon for students to not only work for free but then also having to pay their university to get college credits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is often alleged that unpaid internships are exploitative, but then what is paying a university to get college credits for your work? It is a farce. It reveals the inherent contradiction in the standards we apply to higher education institutions and private companies. Why is it socially acceptable to get deep into debt to study at a university, while learning at an internship &lt;em&gt;for free&lt;/em&gt; is looked down upon? The reality is that the term ‘study’ masks the fact that there is no clear dividing line between studying and working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a journalism school that also runs a newspaper. It hires professional journalists and editors to both create content for the newspaper and to teach a batch of aspiring writers. The school thus earns money through both its newspaper and the students who pay for the education. Early on, students are encouraged to write pieces that might be published in the newspaper. What better practice can there be for an aspiring journalist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, almost none of the students manage to write anything worth publishing, or, when they do, the writing needs so much editing and feedback that the school ends up publishing their piece at a significant loss. But gradually, the writing becomes better and the cost of having to train the young aspiring reporters, and the additional editing required on their writing, starts being offset by their contribution to the newspaper. And so the school starts reducing the tuition of the students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, the students’ writing becomes so good that it completely offsets the cost. They can stay for free. And then they start getting paid. Gradually, their contributions become more and more valuable, and it starts exceeding the costs of mentoring, teaching, editing, advising… In the end, they become so skilled that they become indistinguishable from any of the other employees at the school/newspaper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At what point did they stop ‘studying’ and started ‘working’? The truth is that there is no point at which one stopped and the other started. Studying has always involved working, and working has always involved learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why is there such a vast gap between educational institutions and the rest of the productive economy? Why aren’t newspapers simultaneously also journalism schools? Wouldn’t that be the ideal way to find and train talent and to create an additional revenue stream? Why aren’t companies more involved in the education of the workforce?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to these questions is called regulatory capture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two reasons why someone might want to pay for work. First, because of the work’s educational value, and second for the signaling it provides. But because of a plethora of policies, such as minimum wage laws, subsidies for educational institutions, availability of student loans, regulations governing educational bodies, etc., companies cannot compete with universities for this kind of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contributing to this state of affairs is also a misplaced societal bias against any work that is paid less than the minimum wage. Concerns about equity are valid, but then why the double standard with educational institutions? Why is work at an educational institution not significantly more exploitative than work in an unpaid internship?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I propose is that instead of giving money to universities and restricting businesses’ ability to provide educational opportunities, give the money directly to young people&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; and let them decide what constitutes the best opportunity for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; If you really don’t trust young people to spend the money responsibly, vouchers could work as well.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">Education is a peculiar good. The usual model of private education is that the students are the consumers, the professors are the employees, and the lectures are the product. Students pay to receive the education they want. In reality, students pay more for the degree than the education. But let’s assume for now that education is all about increasing human capital, rather than being mostly about signaling. For the sake of argument, let’s assume that I’m talking about an education start-up that doesn’t grant any kind of degree or certification, and is solely focused on the students’ learning. Then, the model describing students as the consumer is still missing something important. The problem is that modeling students as simple homo economicus agents is not perfect. As the field of behavioral economics has extensively documented, humans aren’t perfectly rational, self-interested, utility-maximizing agents. And education seems to be one of the fields where the homo economicus model is most misleading.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Harari on Religions and Ideologies</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/religion/2020/05/18/harari-on-religions-and-ideologies.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Harari on Religions and Ideologies" /><published>2020-05-18T11:53:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-18T11:53:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/religion/2020/05/18/harari-on-religions-and-ideologies</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/religion/2020/05/18/harari-on-religions-and-ideologies.html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Sapiens-Yuval-Noah-Harari-audiobook/dp/B0741F3M7C/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sapiens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Yuval Noah Harari writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The last 300 years are often depicted as an age of growing secularism, in which religions have increasingly lost their importance. If we are talking about theist religions, this is largely correct. But if we take into consideration natural-law religions, then modernity turns out to be an age of intense religious fervour, unparalleled missionary efforts, and the bloodiest wars of religion in history. The modern age has witnessed the rise of a number of new natural-law religions, such as liberalism, Communism, capitalism, nationalism and Nazism. These creeds do not like to be called religions, and refer to themselves as ideologies. But this is just a semantic exercise. If a religion is a system of human norms and values that is founded on belief in a superhuman order, then Soviet Communism was no less a religion than Islam. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Islam is of course different from Communism, because Islam sees the superhuman order governing the world as the edict of an omnipotent creator god, whereas Soviet Communism did not believe in gods. But Buddhism too gives short shrift to gods, and yet we commonly classify it as a religion. Like Buddhists, Communists believed in a superhuman order of natural and immutable laws that should guide human actions. Whereas Buddhists believe that the law of nature was discovered by Siddhartha Gautama, Communists believed that the law of nature was discovered by Karl Marx, Friedrich Engels and Vladimir Ilyich Lenin. The similarity does not end there. Like other religions, Communism too has its holy scripts and prophetic books, such as Marx’s Das Kapital, which foretold that history would soon end with the inevitable victory of the proletariat. Communism had its holidays and festivals, such as the First of May and the anniversary of the October Revolution. It had theologians adept at Marxist dialectics, and every unit in the Soviet army had a chaplain, called a commissar, who monitored the piety of soldiers and officers. Communism had martyrs, holy wars and heresies, such as Trotskyism. Soviet Communism was a fanatical and missionary religion. A devout Communist could not be a Christian or a Buddhist, and was expected to spread the gospel of Marx and Lenin even at the price of his or her life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It would be impossible to survey here the history of all the new modern creeds, especially because there are no clear boundaries between them. They are no less syncretic than monotheism and popular Buddhism. Just as a Buddhist could worship Hindu deities, and just as a monotheist could believe in the existence of Satan, so the typical American nowadays is simultaneously a nationalist (she believes in the existence of an American nation with a special role to play in history), a free-market capitalist (she believes that open competition and the pursuit of self-interest are the best ways to create a prosperous society), and a liberal humanist (she believes that humans have been endowed by their creator with certain inalienable rights).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Homo-Deus-Yuval-Noah-Harari-audiobook/dp/B01MYZ4OUW&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Homo Deus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, he makes a similar argument:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Equating religion with faith in supernatural powers implies that you can understand all known natural phenomena without religion, which is just an optional supplement. Having understood perfectly well the whole of nature, you can now choose whether to add some ‘super-natural’ religious dogma or not. However, most religions argue that you simply cannot understand the world without them. You will never comprehend the true reason for disease, drought or earthquakes if you do not take their dogma into account. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Defining religion as ‘belief in gods’ is also problematic. We tend to say that a devout Christian is religious because she believes in God, whereas a fervent communist isn’t religious, because communism has no gods. However, religion is created by humans rather than by gods, and it is defined by its social function rather than by the existence of deities. Religion is anything that confers superhuman legitimacy on human social structures. It legitimises human norms and values by arguing that they reflect superhuman laws. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Religion asserts that we humans are subject to a system of moral laws that we did not invent and that we cannot change. A devout Jew would say that this is the system of moral laws created by God and revealed in the Bible. A Hindu would say that Brahma, Vishnu and Shiva created the laws, which were revealed to us humans in the Vedas. Other religions, from Buddhism and Daoism to Nazism, communism and liberalism, argue that the superhuman laws are natural laws, and not the creation of this or that god. Of course, each believes in a different set of natural laws discovered and revealed by different seers and prophets, from Buddha and Laozi to Hitler and Lenin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Liberals, communists and followers of other modern creeds dislike describing their own system as a ‘religion’, because they identify religion with superstitions and supernatural powers. If you tell communists or liberals that they are religious, they think you accuse them of blindly believing in groundless pipe dreams. In fact, it means only that they believe in some system of moral laws that wasn’t invented by humans, but which humans must nevertheless obey. As far as we know, all human societies believe in this. Every society tells its members that they must obey some superhuman moral law, and that breaking this law will result in catastrophe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m planning to write a post digging deeper into this at some point. For now, if you’re interested in this topic, I recommend the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/03/25/is-everything-a-religion/&quot;&gt;Is Everything a Religion?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://meltingasphalt.com/playing-god-for-fun-and-profit/&quot;&gt;Playing God for Fun and Profit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/07/08/gay-rites-are-civil-rites/&quot;&gt;Gay Rites Are Civil Rites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2017/04/breaking-faith/517785/&quot;&gt;Breaking Faith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2018/12/andrew-sullivan-americas-new-religions.html&quot;&gt;America’s New Religions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nationalinterest.org/feature/war-over-liberal-democracy-44242&quot;&gt;The War over Liberal Democracy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.evernote.com/shard/s542/client/snv?noteGuid=46c636b6-b404-45df-ab0a-1f84c6fdc8c2&amp;amp;noteKey=7c94233539b8258d72b395a063f3c589&amp;amp;sn=https://www.evernote.com/shard/s542/sh/46c636b6-b404-45df-ab0a-1f84c6fdc8c2/7c94233539b8258d72b395a063f3c589&amp;amp;title=That+Essay&quot;&gt;The Straussian Moment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">In Sapiens, Yuval Noah Harari writes:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Schools and Churches</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/13/schools-and-churches.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Schools and Churches" /><published>2020-05-13T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-13T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/13/schools-and-churches</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/13/schools-and-churches.html">&lt;p&gt;From Ivan Illich’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Deschooling-Society-Open-Forum-S-ebook/dp/B007EDLBBI/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deschooling Society&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;teacher-as-custodian&lt;/em&gt; acts as a master of ceremonies, who guides his pupils through a drawn-out labyrinthine ritual. He arbitrates the observance of rules and administers the intricate rubrics of initiation to life. At his best, he sets the stage for the acquisition of some skill as schoolmasters always have. Without illusions of producing any profound learning, he drills his pupils in some basic routines. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The &lt;em&gt;teacher-as-moralist&lt;/em&gt; substitutes for parents, God, or the state. He indoctrinates the pupil about what is right or wrong, not only in school buy also in society at large. He stands &lt;em&gt;in loco parentis&lt;/em&gt; for each one and thus ensures that all feel themselves children of the same state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Children are protected by neither the First nor the Fifth Amendment when they stand before that secular priest, the teacher. The child must confront a man who wears an invisible triple crown, like the papal tiara, the symbol of triple authority combined in one person. For the child, the teacher pontificates as pastor, prophet and priest–he is at once guide, teacher, and administrator of a sacred ritual. He combines the claims of medieval popes in a society constituted under the guarantee these claims shall never be exercised together by one established and obligatory institution–church or state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Classroom attendance removes children from the everyday world of Western culture and plunges them into an environment for more primitive, magical and deadly serious. School could not create such an enclave within which the rules of ordinary reality are suspended, unless it physically incarcerated the young on sacred territory. The attendance rule makes it possible for the schoolroom to serve as a magic womb, from which the child is delivered periodically at the schoolday’s and school year’s completion until he is finally expelled into adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The school system today performs the threefold function common to powerful churches throughout history. It is simultaneously the repository of society’s myth, the institutionalization of the myth’s contradictions, and the locus of the ritual which reproduces and veils the disparities between myth and reality. Today the school system, and especially the university, provides ample opportunity for criticism of the myth and for rebellion against institutional perversions. But the ritual which demands tolerance of the fundamental contradictions between myth and institution still goes unchallenged, for neither ideological criticism nor social action can bring about a new society. Only disenchantment with and detachment from the central societal ritual and reform of that ritual can bring about social change. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The American university has become the final stage of the most all-encompassing initiation rite the world has ever known. No society in history has been able to survive without ritual or myth, but ours is the first which has needed such a dull, protracted, destructive, and expensive initiation ritual in the name of education. We cannot begin a reform of education unless we first understand that neither individual learning nor social equality can be enhanced by the ritual of schooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;School seems eminently suited to be the World Church of our decaying culture. No institution could better veil from its participants the deep discrepancy between social principles and social reality in today’s world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure I fully endorse these paragraphs, but the school-church comparison is interesting. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Average-Over-Powering-America-Stagnation-ebook/dp/B00C1N5WOI&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Average Is Over&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Tyler Cowen also points out the parallels between educational and religious institutions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Of course, educational institutions aren’t ready to admit how much they share with churches. These temples of secularism don’t want to admit they are about simple tasks such as motivating the slugs or acculturating people into the work habits and sociological expectations of the so-called educated class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We like to pretend our instructors teach as well as chess computers, but too often they don’t come close to that ideal. They are something far less noble, something that we are afraid to call by its real name, something quite ordinary: They are a mix of exemplars and nags and missionaries, packaged with a marketing model that stressed their nobility and a financial model that pays them pretty well and surrounds them with administrators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil Postman also &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/end-of-education.html&quot;&gt;identified a connection&lt;/a&gt; beween religion and education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, Peter Thiel is also fond of the analogy. He often compares the state of the education system today to the state of the Catholic Church 500 years ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SO_00POR-Po?start=2037&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">From Ivan Illich’s Deschooling Society:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Trillion Dollar Bills on the Sidewalk</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/12/trillion-dollar-bills.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trillion Dollar Bills on the Sidewalk" /><published>2020-05-12T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-12T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/12/trillion-dollar-bills</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/12/trillion-dollar-bills.html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading some more Mancur Olson. This is from a 1996 paper titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jstor.org/stable/2138479?seq=1&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Big Bills Left on the Sidewalk: Why Some Nations are Rich, and Others Poor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If what has been said so far is correct, then the large differences in per capita income across countries cannot be explained by differences in access to the world’s stock of productive knowledge or to its capital markets, by differences in the ratio of population to land or natural resources, or by differences in the quality of marketable human capital or personal culture. Albeit at a high level of aggregation, this eliminates each of the factors of production as possible explanations of most of the international differences in per capita income. The only remaining plausible explanation is that the great differences in the wealth of nations are mainly due to differences in the quality of their institutions and economic policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The best thing a society can do to increase its prosperity is to wise up. This means, in turn, that it is very important indeed that economists, inside government and out, get things right. When we are wrong, we do a lot of harm. When we are right-and have the clarity needed to prevail against the special interests and the quacks-we make an extraordinary contribution to the amelioration of poverty and the progress of humanity. The sums lost because the poor countries obtain only a fraction of-and because even the richest countries do not reach-their economic potentials are measured in the trillions of dollars. &lt;br /&gt;
None of the familiar ideologies is sufficient to provide the needed wisdom. The familiar assumption that the quality of a nation’s economic institutions and policies is given by the smallness, or the largeness, of its public sector-or by the size of its transfers to low-income people-does not fit the facts very well (Levine and Renelt, 1992; Rubinson, 1977; Olson, 1986).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does remind me of something David Manheim recently said on Twitter about the government’s inept response to the COVID-19 crisis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Markets may be efficient, but government is not. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are nearly-literal trillion dollar bills people are trying to hand to governments, begging them to take them, and it has taken months for them to notice and respond. Most still haven&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; David Manheim (@davidmanheim) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidmanheim/status/1255020027343966208?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 28, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Off the top of my head, testing capacity, tracing programs, monitoring / fixing international food supply bottlenecks, stopping trade wars, better directed small business relief programs, ramped-up unemployment benefits that don&amp;#39;t discourage work.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; David Manheim (@davidmanheim) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidmanheim/status/1255044177995485184?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 28, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;They realize. The problem is that legislation is getting written quickly, by committee, without flexibility, and can&amp;#39;t be renegotiated easily.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;That doesn&amp;#39;t mean these aren&amp;#39;t free trillion dollar bills, it means the country is so arthritic it can&amp;#39;t bend down to pick them up.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; David Manheim (@davidmanheim) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/davidmanheim/status/1255045943445147649?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;April 28, 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">I’ve been reading some more Mancur Olson. This is from a 1996 paper titled Big Bills Left on the Sidewalk: Why Some Nations are Rich, and Others Poor.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Public Good of Education</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/11/education-public-good.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Public Good of Education" /><published>2020-05-11T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-05-11T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/11/education-public-good</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/05/11/education-public-good.html">&lt;p&gt;From Mancur Olson’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Rise-Decline-Nations-Stagflation-Rigidities-ebook/dp/B00267SS7W/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Rise and Decline of Nations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Individuals in a few special vocations can receive considerable rewards in private goods if they acquire exceptional knowledge of public goods. Politicians, lobbyists, journalists, and social scientists, for example, may earn more money, power, or prestige from knowledge of this or that public business. Occasionally, exceptional knowledge of public policy can generate exceptional profits in stock exchanges or other markets. Withal, the typical citizen will find that his or her income and life chances will not be improved by zealous study of public affairs, or even of any single collective good. &lt;br /&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
The limited knowledge of public affairs is in turn necessary to explain the effectiveness of lobbying. If all citizens had obtained and digested all pertinent information, they could not then be swayed by advertising or other persuasion. With perfectly informed citizens, elected officials would not be subject to the blandishments of lobbyists, since the constituents would then know if their interests were betrayed and defeat the unfaithful representative at the next election. Just as lobbies provide collective goods to special-interest groups, so their effectiveness is explained by the imperfect knowledge of citizens, and this in turn is due mainly to the fact that information and calculation about collective goods is also a collective good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A citizenry with limited knowledge of public affairs can thus fail to recognize how various interest groups (dubbed &lt;em&gt;distributional coalitions&lt;/em&gt; by Olson) are advancing their own agenda at the expense of society at large. This is a great argument in favor of an education that is not purely designed to get people higher wages. A singular focus on economic return is a flaw in many critiques of education today. However, education can just as well exacerbate the problem of the accumulation of distributional coalitions. Still from Olson:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If a society mainly rewards production or the capacity to satisfy those with whom one engages in free exchange, it stimulates the development of productive traits. It does this particularly through cultural or Lamarckian evolution, whereby learned or acquired behavior can be passed on to descendants. If the accumulation of distributional coalitions increases the incentive for distributional struggle, augments regulatory complexity, encourages the dominance of politics, stimulates bargaining, and increases the complexity of understandings, this encourages the development of different attitudes and attributes. What we loosely call intelligence, or aptitude for education, will probably be favored as much as or more than before because the articulate and educated have a comparative advantage in regulation, politics, and complex understandings. This, in turn, probably limits the extent to which intellectuals oppose their elaboration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, a greater demand for education can also be a sign of an increasingly dysfunctional and sclerotic economy. Not only that, educational credentialing is in fact often a tool used by distributional coalitions. Olson gives the example of medicine and law:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If the number of physicians increases, for example, the earnings of physicians must decline if other things are equal, and in country after country one finds that the professional organizations representing physicians work to limit entry into the profession. As the high income-levels of physicians in many countries testify, these efforts often succeed. The educational credentials and qualifying examinations usually required of those who would enter the practice of medicine are, of course, explained as necessary to protect the patient against incompetence. But note that the examinations are almost always imposed only on entrants. If the limits were mainly motivated by the interest of patients, older physicians would also be required to pass periodic qualifying examinations to demonstrate that they have kept their medical knowledge up-to-date. Among lawyers and other professionals in many countries there are similar limitations on entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2018/11/23/the-case-for-dropping-out-of-college/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Case For Dropping Out of College&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I also made the argument that the whole higher education system has become in large part a zero-sum credentialing competition that entrenches racial and class inequalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ideal education system should serve as a counterweight to a society’s tendency to develop rent-seeking organizations. In the current system however, it seems that universities have more of an enabling function, and have devolved into rent-seeking institutions themselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">From Mancur Olson’s The Rise and Decline of Nations:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Single Best Policy to Combat Climate Change</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/24/climate-change.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Single Best Policy to Combat Climate Change" /><published>2020-04-24T10:37:43+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-24T10:37:43+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/24/climate-change</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/24/climate-change.html">&lt;p&gt;The single best policy to combat climate change is an internationally enforced carbon tax. There is pretty much a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-01-17/from-greenspan-to-yellen-economic-brain-trust-backs-carbon-tax&quot;&gt;consensus&lt;/a&gt; on this among economists. But despite the fact that the experts agree, and that the issue of climate change is of great public interest, there seems to be almost no discussion of this policy in mainstream circles. William Nordhaus, winner of the 2018 economics Nobel prize, is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foreignaffairs.com/articles/united-states/2020-04-10/climate-club&quot;&gt;finally writing about his “climate club”&lt;/a&gt; proposal for this year’s May/June issue of Foreign Affairs. All I could find before that, outside of academic publications, was a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/2018/10/10/17959686/carbon-tax&quot;&gt;post by Matthew Yglesias&lt;/a&gt; on Vox:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What &lt;em&gt;ought&lt;/em&gt; to happen is that the US sits down with the European Union and Japan and decides on a carbon tax. The initial tax should be low, but it should be set to escalate. And the three big players in the global economy should also agree to impose a fairly stiff tariff on any country that doesn’t agree to join the carbon tax club.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Right away, a bunch of countries will want to join the club, and with each new country that joins, staying out of the club becomes costlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That pretty much sums it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked on YouTube, and there seems to be no good video explaining a carbon tax. These two are the best I could find:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zD64kaTY5Vg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/CilVymuAM8A&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
They are alright, but it could be explained much better. This from MRU is on cap and trade, not carbon tax, but it has a clearer explanation of the economics involved:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9tUb3MDrgEc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in none of these is there mention of how a carbon tax might be enforced at an international level. Why isn’t there anything better on this? This is an issue that has led millions, across the globe, to protest. It’s supposed to be one of the biggest issues of our time. Yet, the best policy solution seems to be barely discussed outside of academic economics papers. What are the billions going to higher education doing? What happened to educating the public?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in his post, Yglesias writes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But activists, unlike me, need to find a politics that actually works politically. I think it’s pretty clear that this wonky pitch has failed, over and over again, in a range of times and places.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he then goes on to praise the Green New Deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.econlib.org/if-the-only-way-you-can-get-your-great-idea-implemented/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; by Bryan Caplan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When you look at the real world, though, you see something strange: Almost &lt;em&gt;no one&lt;/em&gt; actually pushes for the textbooks’ clever-and-appealing policy proposals.  Instead, the people inspired by the textbooks routinely attach themselves to trendy-but-awful policy proposals.  If you point out the discrepancy, they’re often too annoyed to respond.  When they do, reformers shrug and say: “The clever-and-appealing policy never has – and probably never will – have much political support.  So we have to do this instead.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The moral: If the only way you can get your great idea implemented is to mutilate it and/or package it with a pile of expensive junk, you really should wonder, “Is it still worth it?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beyond that, what pitch is Yglesias talking about? The public was never pitched. No one has ever heard of the “climate club” proposal. There never has been a serious attempt to educate the public on this. I mean, how hard can it be to create a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/Kurzgesagt&quot;&gt;Kurzgesagt&lt;/a&gt; type video explaining the “climate club” proposal? That would really be the minimum. Academic institutions aren’t even trying. And people who know better have already given up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WWM9gIVvm78&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt; about a carbon tax with the most views at the moment is barely longer than a minute and has under half a million views. Meanwhile the latest Michael Moore &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Zk11vI-7czE&quot;&gt;documentary&lt;/a&gt;, promoting population control as a solution to climate change, has already 1.5M views. It lasts 1h40 and was released 3 days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If higher education is not going to educate the public, someone else will.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">The single best policy to combat climate change is an internationally enforced carbon tax. There is pretty much a consensus on this among economists. But despite the fact that the experts agree, and that the issue of climate change is of great public interest, there seems to be almost no discussion of this policy in mainstream circles. William Nordhaus, winner of the 2018 economics Nobel prize, is finally writing about his “climate club” proposal for this year’s May/June issue of Foreign Affairs. All I could find before that, outside of academic publications, was a post by Matthew Yglesias on Vox:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Online Standardized Tests Are a Bad Idea</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/17/online-standardized-tests.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online Standardized Tests Are a Bad Idea" /><published>2020-04-17T10:05:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-17T10:05:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/17/online-standardized-tests</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/17/online-standardized-tests.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The SAT and rival ACT, the nation’s most important college entrance exams, are taking steps to offer their tests online and at students’ homes later this year in an unprecedented move that will require massive amounts of digital proctoring to prevent cheating, officials announced Wednesday. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Emergency backup plans are being developed by both influential testing organizations if schools remain closed in the fall, preventing the usual in-school testing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If the coronavirus crisis persists, the College Board, the organization that sponsors the SAT, said it is preparing for an online, at-home offering of the exam that would implement technology that monitors movement and sound of possible cheating activities and also locks down access to other sites on the Internet during testing. Such online SAT exams previously have been used at some school districts and wider versions are already being tested.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“While the idea of at-home SAT testing is new, digital delivery of the test is not,” College Board CEO David Coleman said in a statement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;https://edsource.org/2020/sat-and-act-plan-at-home-college-admissions-exams-during-health-crisis/629182&quot;&gt;EdSource&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very skeptical of this move. Online education has enormous promise, and I think that it will ultimately replace the vast majority of in-person education. Notwithstanding the bad experience of many students who, because of COVID-19, have to endure an improvised online version of their previously in-person classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, testing and credentialing will probably not make that transition anytime soon. The problem is that the more a test matters and is important for a student’s future, the greater the incentive to cheat. And the stakes of the SAT are (or appear to be) quite high. With a great enough incentive, no software or digital monitoring will prove good enough to prevent cheating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A webcam and a microphone will never provide enough information of the surrounding environment. And if Apple hasn’t found a way to stop people from jailbreaking their devices, and video game creators haven’t figured out a reliable way to prevent people from pirating their games, the idea that anyone is going to come up with a software solution to ensure the integrity of online tests seems laughable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also why I think that anyone wanting to create a degree-equivalent standardized test (as I argue for &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/05/what-i-learned-dropping-out-of-high-school.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/10/pinker-on-education.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), will have to stick to in-person test proctoring. At least if they want their test to carry a high signaling value. That also explains to some extent why online degree programs haven’t been more popular, and are viewed with some skepticism by employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future of learning is on the internet, but credentialing will probably remain offline.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">The SAT and rival ACT, the nation’s most important college entrance exams, are taking steps to offer their tests online and at students’ homes later this year in an unprecedented move that will require massive amounts of digital proctoring to prevent cheating, officials announced Wednesday. Emergency backup plans are being developed by both influential testing organizations if schools remain closed in the fall, preventing the usual in-school testing. If the coronavirus crisis persists, the College Board, the organization that sponsors the SAT, said it is preparing for an online, at-home offering of the exam that would implement technology that monitors movement and sound of possible cheating activities and also locks down access to other sites on the Internet during testing. Such online SAT exams previously have been used at some school districts and wider versions are already being tested. “While the idea of at-home SAT testing is new, digital delivery of the test is not,” College Board CEO David Coleman said in a statement</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Questions to Guide Life and Learning</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/15/guiding-questions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Questions to Guide Life and Learning" /><published>2020-04-15T10:05:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-15T10:05:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/15/guiding-questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/15/guiding-questions.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-worth-knowing&quot;&gt;What’s Worth Knowing?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Teaching-Subversive-Activity-Neil-Postman/dp/0385290098&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teaching as a Subversive Activity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Neil Postman and Charles Weingartner suggest the following exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Suppose all the syllabi and curricula and textbooks in the schools disappeared. Suppose all of the standardized tests – city-wide, state-wide and national – were lost. In other words, suppose that the most common material impeding innovation in the schools simply did not exist. Then suppose that you decided to turn this ‘catastrophe’ into an opportunity to increase the relevance of the schools. What would you do? &lt;br /&gt;
We have a possibility for you to consider: suppose that you decide to have the entire ‘curriculum’ consist of questions. These questions would have to be worth seeking answers to not only from your point of view but, more importantly, from the point of view of the students. In order to get still closer to reality, add the requirement that the questions must help the students to develop and internalize concepts that will help them to survive in the rapidly changing world of the present and future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They then encourage the reader to write down a list of questions, and propose their own list. Here are some of the best ones:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;If you had an important idea that you wanted to let everyone (in the world) know about, how might you go about letting them know?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What bothers you most about adults? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How do you want to be similar to or different from adults you know when you become an adult?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What, if anything, seems to you to be worth dying for?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How did you come to believe this?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What seems worth living for?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How did you come to believe this?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;At the present moment, what would you most like to be – or be able to do? Why? What would you have to know in order to be able to to do it? What would you have to do in order to get to know it?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How can you tell ‘good guys’ from ‘bad guys’?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How can ‘good’ be distinguished from ‘evil’?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What kind of person would you most like to be? How might you get to be this kind of person?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Where does knowledge come from?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What do you think are some of man’s most important ideas? Where did they come from? Why? How? Now what?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What’s a ‘good idea’?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How do you know when a good or live idea becomes a bad or dead idea?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Which of man’s ideas would we be better off forgetting? How do you decide?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What is ‘progress’?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the relationships between new ideas and change?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Where do &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; ideas come from? How come? So what?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Of the important changes going on in our society, which should be encouraged and which resisted? Why? How?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What would you change if you could? How might you go about it? Of those changes which are going to occur, which would you stop if you could? Why? How? So what?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Who do you think has the most important things to say today? To whom? How? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the dumbest and most dangerous ideas that are ‘popular’ today? Why do you thing so? Where did these ideas come from?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the conditions necessary for life to survive? Plants? Animals? Humans?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the greatest threats to all forms of life? To plants? To animals? To humans?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What does man’s language permit him to develop as survival strategies that animals cannot develop?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What other ‘languages’ does man have besides those consisting of words?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are some good symbols? Some bad?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What’s worth knowing? How do you decide? What are some ways to go about getting to know what’s worth knowing?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason these questions should be thought about during one’s education, and beyond, is because they lead one to consider what issues are important from a societal and civilizational perspective, and can guide one on the path to a meaningful life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-will-you-measure-your-life&quot;&gt;How Will You Measure Your Life?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clayton Christensen, in his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/How-Will-Measure-Your-Life/dp/0062102419&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Will You Measure Your Life?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (another question worth thinking about), observes how many of his classmates at the Harvard Buisness School ended up unhappy despite great professional success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Behind the facade of professional success, there were many who did not enjoy what they were doing for a living. There were, also, numerous stories of divorces or unhappy marriages. I remember one classmate who hadn’t talked to his children in years, who was now living on the opposite coast from them. Another was on her third marriage since we’d graduated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the time, I assumed it was a blip; a kind of midlife crisis. But at our twenty-five- and thirty-year reunions, the problems were worse. One of our classmates—Jeffrey Skilling—had landed in jail for his role in the Enron scandal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christensen then attempts to answer the following 3 questions using lessons he learned studying buisnesses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How can I be sure that&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I will be successful and happy in my career?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;My relationships with my spouse, my children, and my extended family and close friends become an enduring source of happiness?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I live a life of integrity—and stay out of jail?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the epilogue, he stresses the importance of purpose:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Without a purpose, the value to executives of any business theory would be limited. Even though theory is able to predict the possible outcomes of an important decision, on what basis would the executives be deciding among them to determine which is the best outcome? […] &lt;br /&gt;
In a similar way, to maximize the value of the advice in this book, you must have a purpose in your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and proposes another question, crucial in finding a purpose worth committing to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Who do I truly want to become?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might make a post at some point about some of the most interesting ideas in this book. But for now, I encourage you to consider some of these questions, and try to come up with your own answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-are-the-most-important-questions-in-your-life&quot;&gt;What Are The Most Important Questions In Your Life?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mathematician Richard Hamming had another set of great questions. Here’s from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/hamming.html&quot;&gt;transcript of a 1986 talk&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Over on the other side of the dining hall was a chemistry table. I had worked with one of the fellows, Dave McCall; furthermore he was courting our secretary at the time. I went over and said, “Do you mind if I join you?” They can’t say no, so I started eating with them for a while. And I started asking, &lt;strong&gt;“What are the important problems of your field?”&lt;/strong&gt; And after a week or so, “What important problems are you working on?” And after some more time I came in one day and said, &lt;strong&gt;“If what you are doing is not important, and if you don’t think it is going to lead to something important, why are you at Bell Labs working on it?”&lt;/strong&gt; I wasn’t welcomed after that; I had to find somebody else to eat with!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(emphasis is mine)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line of inquiry is targeted at researchers, but it can also be applied to one’s life. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rationality.org/&quot;&gt;Center For Applied Rationality&lt;/a&gt; (CFAR) has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/the-hamming-question-boston-edition-tickets-16449605212&quot;&gt;turned&lt;/a&gt; the question into:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What are the most important questions in our lives (or in our organizations/work), and why aren’t we working on them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, if none of the questions I listed above seemed compelling, this modified Hamming question should give you some food for thought. 
I think most people don’t spend enough time wondering if the path of least resistance is actually the best one. So going for a walk, and pondering on one or more of these questions does seem like a good investment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">What’s Worth Knowing?</summary></entry></feed>