<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thememeticist.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://thememeticist.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-17T13:57:59+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Memeticist</title><subtitle>Memes worth spreading </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Online Standardized Tests Are a Bad Idea</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/17/online-standardized-tests.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Online Standardized Tests Are a Bad Idea" /><published>2020-04-17T10:05:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-17T10:05:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/17/online-standardized-tests</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/17/online-standardized-tests.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The SAT and rival ACT, the nation’s most important college entrance exams, are taking steps to offer their tests online and at students’ homes later this year in an unprecedented move that will require massive amounts of digital proctoring to prevent cheating, officials announced Wednesday. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Emergency backup plans are being developed by both influential testing organizations if schools remain closed in the fall, preventing the usual in-school testing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If the coronavirus crisis persists, the College Board, the organization that sponsors the SAT, said it is preparing for an online, at-home offering of the exam that would implement technology that monitors movement and sound of possible cheating activities and also locks down access to other sites on the Internet during testing. Such online SAT exams previously have been used at some school districts and wider versions are already being tested.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“While the idea of at-home SAT testing is new, digital delivery of the test is not,” College Board CEO David Coleman said in a statement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;https://edsource.org/2020/sat-and-act-plan-at-home-college-admissions-exams-during-health-crisis/629182&quot;&gt;EdSource&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very skeptical of this move. Online education has enormous promise, and I think that it will ultimately replace the vast majority of in-person education. Notwithstanding the bad experience of many students who, because of COVID19, have to endure an improvised online version of their previously in-person classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, testing and credentialing will probably not make that transition anytime soon. The problem is that the more a test matters and is important for a student’s future, the greater the incentive is to cheat. And the stakes of the SAT are (or appear to be) quite high. With a great enough incentive, no software or digital monitoring will prove good enough to prevent cheating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A webcam and a microphone will never provide enough information of the surrounding environment. And if Apple hasn’t found a way to stop people from jailbreaking their devices, and video game creators haven’t figured out a reliable way to prevent people from pirating their games, the idea that anyone is going to come up with a software solution to ensure the integrity of online tests seems laughable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also why I think that anyone wanting to create a degree-equivalent standardized test (as I argue for &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/05/what-i-learned-dropping-out-of-high-school.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/10/pinker-on-education.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), will have to stick to in-person test proctoring. At least if they want their test to carry a high signaling value. That also explains to some extent why online degree programs haven’t been more popular, and are viewed with some skepticism by employers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future of learning is on the internet, but credentialing will probably remain offline.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">The SAT and rival ACT, the nation’s most important college entrance exams, are taking steps to offer their tests online and at students’ homes later this year in an unprecedented move that will require massive amounts of digital proctoring to prevent cheating, officials announced Wednesday. Emergency backup plans are being developed by both influential testing organizations if schools remain closed in the fall, preventing the usual in-school testing. If the coronavirus crisis persists, the College Board, the organization that sponsors the SAT, said it is preparing for an online, at-home offering of the exam that would implement technology that monitors movement and sound of possible cheating activities and also locks down access to other sites on the Internet during testing. Such online SAT exams previously have been used at some school districts and wider versions are already being tested. “While the idea of at-home SAT testing is new, digital delivery of the test is not,” College Board CEO David Coleman said in a statement</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Questions to Guide Life and Learning</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/15/guiding-questions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Questions to Guide Life and Learning" /><published>2020-04-15T10:05:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-15T10:05:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/15/guiding-questions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/15/guiding-questions.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-worth-knowing&quot;&gt;What’s Worth Knowing?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Teaching-Subversive-Activity-Neil-Postman/dp/0385290098&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teaching as a Subversive Activity&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Neil Postman and Charles Weingartner suggest the following exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Suppose all the syllabi and curricula and textbooks in the schools disappeared. Suppose all of the standardized tests – city-wide, state-wide and national – were lost. In other words, suppose that the most common material impeding innovation in the schools simply did not exist. Then suppose that you decided to turn this ‘catastrophe’ into an opportunity to increase the relevance of the schools. What would you do? &lt;br /&gt;
We have a possibility for you to consider: suppose that you decide to have the entire ‘curriculum’ consist of questions. These questions would have to be worth seeking answers to not only from your point of view but, more importantly, from the point of view of the students. In order to get still closer to reality, add the requirement that the questions must help the students to develop and internalize concepts that will help them to survive in the rapidly changing world of the present and future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They then encourage the reader to write down a list of questions, and propose their own list. Here are some of the best ones:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;If you had an important idea that you wanted to let everyone (in the world) know about, how might you go about letting them know?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What bothers you most about adults? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How do you want to be similar to or different from adults you know when you become an adult?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What, if anything, seems to you to be worth dying for?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How did you come to believe this?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What seems worth living for?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How did you come to believe this?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;At the present moment, what would you most like to be – or be able to do? Why? What would you have to know in order to be able to to do it? What would you have to do in order to get to know it?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How can you tell ‘good guys’ from ‘bad guys’?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How can ‘good’ be distinguished from ‘evil’?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What kind of person would you most like to be? How might you get to be this kind of person?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Where does knowledge come from?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What do you think are some of man’s most important ideas? Where did they come from? Why? How? Now what?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What’s a ‘good idea’?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How do you know when a good or live idea becomes a bad or dead idea?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Which of man’s ideas would we be better off forgetting? How do you decide?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What is ‘progress’?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the relationships between new ideas and change?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Where do &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; ideas come from? How come? So what?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Of the important changes going on in our society, which should be encouraged and which resisted? Why? How?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What would you change if you could? How might you go about it? Of those changes which are going to occur, which would you stop if you could? Why? How? So what?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Who do you think has the most important things to say today? To whom? How? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the dumbest and most dangerous ideas that are ‘popular’ today? Why do you thing so? Where did these ideas come from?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the conditions necessary for life to survive? Plants? Animals? Humans?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are the greatest threats to all forms of life? To plants? To animals? To humans?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What does man’s language permit him to develop as survival strategies that animals cannot develop?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What other ‘languages’ does man have besides those consisting of words?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What are some good symbols? Some bad?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What’s worth knowing? How do you decide? What are some ways to go about getting to know what’s worth knowing?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason these questions should be thought about during one’s education, and beyond, is because they lead one to consider what issues are important from a societal and civilizational perspective, and can guide one on the path to a meaningful life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-will-you-measure-your-life&quot;&gt;How Will You Measure Your Life?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clayton Christensen, in his book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/How-Will-Measure-Your-Life/dp/0062102419&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How Will You Measure Your Life?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (another question worth thinking about), observes how many of his classmates at the Harvard Buisness School ended up unhappy despite great professional success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Behind the facade of professional success, there were many who did not enjoy what they were doing for a living. There were, also, numerous stories of divorces or unhappy marriages. I remember one classmate who hadn’t talked to his children in years, who was now living on the opposite coast from them. Another was on her third marriage since we’d graduated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At the time, I assumed it was a blip; a kind of midlife crisis. But at our twenty-five- and thirty-year reunions, the problems were worse. One of our classmates—Jeffrey Skilling—had landed in jail for his role in the Enron scandal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christensen then attempts to answer the following 3 questions using lessons he learned studying buisnesses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;How can I be sure that&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I will be successful and happy in my career?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;My relationships with my spouse, my children, and my extended family and close friends become an enduring source of happiness?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I live a life of integrity—and stay out of jail?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the epilogue, he stresses the importance of purpose:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Without a purpose, the value to executives of any business theory would be limited. Even though theory is able to predict the possible outcomes of an important decision, on what basis would the executives be deciding among them to determine which is the best outcome? […] &lt;br /&gt;
In a similar way, to maximize the value of the advice in this book, you must have a purpose in your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And proposes another question, crucial in finding a purpose worth commiting to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Who do I truly want to become?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might make a post at some point about some of the most interesting ideas in this book. But for now, I encourage you to consider some of these questions, and try to come up with your own answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-are-the-most-important-questions-in-your-life&quot;&gt;What Are The Most Important Questions In Your Life?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mathematician Richard Hamming had another set of great questions. Here’s from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/hamming.html&quot;&gt;transcript of a 1986 talk&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Over on the other side of the dining hall was a chemistry table. I had worked with one of the fellows, Dave McCall; furthermore he was courting our secretary at the time. I went over and said, “Do you mind if I join you?” They can’t say no, so I started eating with them for a while. And I started asking, &lt;strong&gt;“What are the important problems of your field?”&lt;/strong&gt; And after a week or so, “What important problems are you working on?” And after some more time I came in one day and said, &lt;strong&gt;“If what you are doing is not important, and if you don’t think it is going to lead to something important, why are you at Bell Labs working on it?”&lt;/strong&gt; I wasn’t welcomed after that; I had to find somebody else to eat with!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(emphasis is mine)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line of inquiry is targeted at researchers, but it can also be applied to one’s life. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rationality.org/&quot;&gt;Center For Applied Rationality&lt;/a&gt; (CFAR) has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.com/e/the-hamming-question-boston-edition-tickets-16449605212&quot;&gt;turned&lt;/a&gt; the question into:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What are the most important questions in our lives (or in our organizations/work), and why aren’t we working on them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, if none of the questions I listed above seemed compelling, this modified Hamming question should give you some food for thought. 
I think most people don’t spend enough time wondering if the path of least resistance is actually the best one. So going for a walk, and pondering on one or more of these questions does seem like a good investment.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">What’s Worth Knowing?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Steven Pinker Could Become Really Rich</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/10/pinker-on-education.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Steven Pinker Could Become Really Rich" /><published>2020-04-10T11:53:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-10T11:53:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/10/pinker-on-education</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/10/pinker-on-education.html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://newrepublic.com/article/119321/harvard-ivy-league-should-judge-students-standardized-tests&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Trouble With Harvard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Steven Pinker has some thoughts on what an education should entail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I think we can be more specific. It seems to me that educated people should know something about the 13-billion-year prehistory of our species and the basic laws governing the physical and living world, including our bodies and brains. They should grasp the timeline of human history from the dawn of agriculture to the present. They should be exposed to the diversity of human cultures, and the major systems of belief and value with which they have made sense of their lives. They should know about the formative events in human history, including the blunders we can hope not to repeat. They should understand the principles behind democratic governance and the rule of law. They should know how to appreciate works of fiction and art as sources of aesthetic pleasure and as impetuses to reflect on the human condition. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
On top of this knowledge, a liberal education should make certain habits of rationality second nature. Educated people should be able to express complex ideas in clear writing and speech. They should appreciate that objective knowledge is a precious commodity, and know how to distinguish vetted fact from superstition, rumor, and unexamined conventional wisdom. They should know how to reason logically and statistically, avoiding the fallacies and biases to which the untutored human mind is vulnerable. They should think causally rather than magically, and know what it takes to distinguish causation from correlation and coincidence. They should be acutely aware of human fallibility, most notably their own, and appreciate that people who disagree with them are not stupid or evil. Accordingly, they should appreciate the value of trying to change minds by persuasion rather than intimidation or demagoguery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like these two paragraphs as they contrast with what one usually gets from people defending the value of a college education: vague verbiage like “students learn to think,” “become better citizens,” “have their mind expanded” or “become cultured.” And people are then rarely challenged to actually explain what they mean by that. Pinker agrees:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Any rethinking of elite university admissions must begin with an inkling of the goals of a university education. As the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mFblhcQjKeY&quot;&gt;song&lt;/a&gt; says, if you don’t know where you’re going, any road will take you there. One contributor to the admissions mess is that so few of a university’s thought leaders can say anything coherent about what those goals are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People, especially academics at elite universities, should get concrete about what an education ought to entail more often, as that then allows to create an independent test to check if a person is “educated,” using the standards laid out. If Pinker says that to get a Harvard degree you need to know X, Y and Z, then a comprehensive standardized test that checks if someone knows X, Y and Z, should be of equivalent prestige as a Harvard degree, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last part of the piece, Pinker goes on to make the case for the use of standardized tests in college admissions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Let’s daydream for a moment. If only we had some way to divine the suitability of a student for an elite education, without ethnic bias, undeserved advantages to the wealthy, or pointless gaming of the system. […] A sample of behavior that could be gathered quickly and cheaply, assessed objectively, and double-checked for its ability to predict the qualities we value….&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We do have this magic measuring stick, of course: it’s called standardized testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a standardized test is the most meritocratic way to figure out who should get admitted to university, then why wouldn’t it also be the best way to figure out who is “educated?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Pinker should do is quit Harvard, and create a rigorous and comprehensive standardized test, the Pinker Degree of Psychology, that would test all that a psychology major learns at Harvard. With his name and reputation behind it, it should carry as much prestige as an actual Harvard psychology degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And he could charge virtually as much as he wants. A Harvard degree costs more than $200k. I’m sure a lot of people would love to pay $10k to get a degree that, according to one of Harvard’s most well known and respected professors, is equivalent to a Harvard bachelor’s degree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe higher education will get fixed when prestigious professors realize that they don’t need the university to award diplomas. They can democratize education by simply accrediting students directly, and make a lot of money along the way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">In The Trouble With Harvard, Steven Pinker has some thoughts on what an education should entail:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The End of Education</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/end-of-education.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The End of Education" /><published>2020-04-06T10:05:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-06T10:05:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/end-of-education</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/end-of-education.html">&lt;p&gt;Me reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/End-Education-Redefining-Value-School/dp/0679750312&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The End of Education&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, by Neil Postman, was a bit of an accident. It was published in 1996 and its main topic is public education, K-12 specifically. So even though the topic of education does interest me a great deal, I don’t think I would have picked it up weren’t it for the fact that I stumbled on it on my mother’s bookshelf, and that the title seemed intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sets up the question of what the &lt;em&gt;purpose&lt;/em&gt; of education is, and tries to provide an answer. I found part II of the book, which focuses on possible answers, a little weak. I think that the narratives presented are too vague, outdated or incomplete. The first part however, which describes the problem, is excellent. Here are a few passages from the book that carry some of the best ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;preface&quot;&gt;Preface&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is as if we are a nation of technicians, consumed by our expertise in how something should be done, afraid or incapable of thinking about why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By giving the book its ambiguous title, I mean to suggest that without a transcendent and honorable purpose schooling must reach its finish, and the sooner we are done with it, the better. With such a purpose, schooling becomes the central institution through which the young may find reasons for continuing to educate themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-the-necessity-of-gods&quot;&gt;1. The Necessity of Gods&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;For school to make sense, the young, their parent, and their teachers must have a god to serve, or, even better, several gods. If they have none, school is pointless. Nietzsche’s famous aphorism is relevant here: “He who has a &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; to live can bear with almost any &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt;.” This applies as much to learning as to living.
	&lt;br /&gt;To put it simply, there is no surer way to bring an end to schooling than for it to have no end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;By a god to serve, I do not necessarily mean &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A god, in the sense I am using the word, is the name of a great narrative, one that has sufficient credibility, complexity, and symbolic power to enable one to organize one’s life around it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The point is that, call them what you will, we are unceasing in creating histories and futures for ourselves through the medium of narrative. Without a narrative, life has no meaning. Without meaning, learning has no purpose. Without a purpose, schools are houses of detention, not attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What happens to people when they have no gods to serve? Some commit suicide. […] Some envelop themselves in drugs, including alcohol. Some take whatever pleasure is to be found in random violence. Some encase themselves in an impenetrable egoism. Many, apparently, find a momentary and pitiful release from dread in commercial re-creations of once powerful narratives of the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-some-gods-that-fail&quot;&gt;2. Some Gods That Fail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So far, America’s answer has largely been, Believe in a market economy, which is not much of a story, not much of an answer. The problem is that America’s better gods have been badly wounded. As America has moved towards the status of an empire […], its great story of liberal democracy has lost much of its luster. Of Tocqueville’s “civic participation,” there is less in America than in any other industrialized nation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the narrative of the great melting-pot has also sufferend as many insults as an imperfect god can bear. For some , for example, Koreans, Chinese, and Russians, it has worked tolerable well, but too many others have been blocked from sharing in the fullness of the American promise because of their race or native language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As for the rigorous tale of the blessedness of Hard Work, too many Americans no longer believe in it. The great school of the Higher Learning, television, teaches them that a dream deferred is a dream forever denied – which is to say, no dream at all; that they are, in fact, entitled to the fruits of technology’s largesse; and that the god of Consumership confers its graciousness more freely than can any god of Labor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There was a time when educators became famous for providing reasons for learning; now they become famous for inventing a method. &lt;br /&gt;
	There are, of course, many things wrong with all of this, not least that it diverts attention from the important matters – for example, the fundamental simplicity of teaching and learning when both teacher and student share a reason for the enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, when the student shares the reason for the enterprise, learning becomes so simple that the student may even not need the teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It may properly go by the name of the god of Economic Utility. As its name suggests, it is a passionless god, cold and severe. But it makes a promise, and not a trivial one. Addressing the young, it offers a covenant of sorts with them: If you will pay attention in school, and do your homework, and score well on tests, and behave yourself, you will be rewarded with a well-paying job when you are done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The story goes on to preach that America is not so much a culture as it is an economy, and that the vitality of a nation’s economy rests on high standards of achievement and rigorous discipline in schools. There is little evidence (that is to say, none) that the productivity of a nation’s economy is related to the quality of its schooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bryan Caplan makes a similar argument. Because of credentialling, people spending more time in school do end up earning more, however this does not necessarily translate in better economic outcomes for the country as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One need hardly add that the story of the god of Economic Utility is rarely believed by students and certainly has almost no power to inspire them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Many parents, in fact, are apt to like the idea of school as a primary training ground for future employment, as do many corporate executives. This is why the story of Economic Utility is told and re-told in television commercials and political speeches as the reason why children should go to school, and stay in school, and why schools should receive public support. &lt;br /&gt;
	But for all its widespread popularity, the god of Economic Utility is impotent to create satisfactory reasons for schooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Any education that is mainly &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; economic utility is far too limited to be useful, and, in any case, so diminishes the world that it mocks one’s humanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I refer to the god of Consumership, whose basic moral axiom is expressed in the slogan “Whoever dies with the most toys, wins” – that is to say, goodness inheres in those who buy things; evil in those who do not. The similarity between this god and the god of Economic Utility is obvious, but with this difference: The latter postulates that you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; what you do for a living; the former that you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; what you accumulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is probably unnecessary to say that all traditional religions reject the god of Consumership, claiming that devotion to it is a false spirituality, if not outright blasphemy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-some-new-gods-that-fail&quot;&gt;3. Some New Gods That Fail&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Schools are not now and have never been chiefly about getting information to children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that was the case, the internet would have made schools obsolete a long time ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One might even say that schools have never been essentially about individualized learning. It is true, of course, that groups do not learn; individuals do. But the idea of a school is that individuals must learn in a setting in which individual needs are subordinated to group interests. Unlike other media of mass communication, which celebrate individual response and are experienced in private, the classroom is intended to tame the ego, to connect the individual with others, to demonstrate the value and necessity of group cohesion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I refer to the fact that those who advocate a “multicultural” curriculum, especially those who speak for an Afrocentric bias, understand better than most […] the need for a god to serve; they understand that the reason why students are demoralized, bored, and distracted is not that the teachers lack interesting methods and machinery but that both students and teachers lack a narrative to provide profoud meaning to their lessons. It does not go too far to say that the “multiculturalists” are the most active and dedicated education philosophers we have at the moment. They are not especially interested in methods or machinery and, generally, are not competent to speak on such matters. But they have a story to tell, and they believe their story can serve as a foundation to schooling. The trouble is that it is a terrible story, at least for public schools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This provides an interesting pespective on how the universities have found themselves embroiled in the culture wars. One of the reasons the wing of the progressive left focused on identity politics may have gotten such a strong foothold in educational institutions is that it describes one of the most compelling narratives available for education at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn’t be the &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/07/08/gay-rites-are-civil-rites/&quot;&gt;first&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://areomagazine.com/2018/12/18/postmodern-religion-and-the-faith-of-social-justice/&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt; to observe that progressive identity politics can have a quasy religious character to it. And I don’t necessarily mean that in a bad way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But the point is that it is possible, by ignoring its transcendent ideals, to tell America’s story as a history of racism, inequity, and violence. Is this the story we wish to be the foundation of American public schooling?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-gods-that-may-serve&quot;&gt;4. Gods That May Serve&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-spaceship-earth&quot;&gt;The Spaceship Earth&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We have here, then, a narrative of extraordinary potential: the story of human beings as stewards of the Earth, caretakers of a vulnerable space capsule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-fallen-angel&quot;&gt;The Fallen Angel&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I beseach you, in the bowels of Christ,” Oliver Cromwell pleaded, “think it possible that you may be mistaken.” That we may be mistaken, and probably are, is the meaning of the “fall” in the fallen angel. The meaning of “angel” is that we are capable of correcting our mistakes, provided we proceed without hubris, pride, or dogmatism; provided that we accept our cosmic status as the error-prone species.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In the last program of his television series, Bronowsky is seen standing in a pond on the grounds of the old Auschwitz concentration camp. Near-overwrought by what Auschwitz symbolizes, he resorts, as so many have done before him, to a religious metaphor. “Into this pond,” he says, “were flushed the ashes of some four million people. And that was not done by gas. It was done by arrogance. It was done by dogma…. When people believe that they have absolute knowledge…. this is how they behave. This is what men do when they aspire to the knowledge of gods.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the clip:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ltjI3BXKBgY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-american-experiment&quot;&gt;The American Experiment&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;But the story properly begins, as Abraham Lincoln saw it, with a series of stunning and dangerous questions. Is it possible to have a government of the people, by the people, and for the people? And who are the people, anyway? And how shall we protect individuals from the power of the people? And why should we do all this in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;America was the first nation to be argued into existence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This, it seems to me, is a fine and noble story to offer as a reason for schooling: to provide our youth with the knowledge and will to participate in the great experiment; to teach them how to argue, and to help them discover what questions are worth arguing about; and, of course, to make sure they know what happens when arguments cease. No one is excluded from the story. Every group has made good arguments, and bad ones. All points are admissible. The only thing we have to fear is that someone will insist on putting in an exclamation point when we are not yet finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As national stories go, America may have one of the most compelling ones. However, I’m looking for something a bit more transcendent and universal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-law-of-diversity&quot;&gt;The Law of Diversity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We simply cannot enter the twenty-first century at each other’s throats…. We are at a crucial crossroads in the history of this nation – and we either hang together by combating these forces that divide and degrade us or we hang seperately.” I take this to be a heartfelt plea for the necessity of providing ourselves and especially our young with a comprehensive narrative that makes a constructive and unifying use of diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We learn about these people for two reasons: because they demonstrate how the vitality and creativity of humanity depend on diversity, and because they have set the standards to which civilized people adhere. The law of diversity thus makes intelligent humans of us all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-world-weaversthe-world-makers&quot;&gt;The World Weavers/The World Makers&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One answer that can provide schooling with a profound organizing principle is that we use language to create the world – which is to say, language is not only a vehicle of thought; it is, as Wittgenstein said, also the driver. We go where it leads. We see the world as it permits us to see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We are the world makers, and the world weavers. That is what makes us smart, and dumb; moral and immoral; tolerant and bigoted. That is what makes us human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are quite good. But I find all of them lacking in some way or another. The main issue I have with almost all of them is the vagueness. They offer some abstract ideals to live by, but none of them offers a truly concrete and inspiring purpose to education. At least to my eyes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">Me reading The End of Education, by Neil Postman, was a bit of an accident. It was published in 1996 and its main topic is public education, K-12 specifically. So even though the topic of education does interest me a great deal, I don’t think I would have picked it up weren’t it for the fact that I stumbled on it on my mother’s bookshelf, and that the title seemed intriguing.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Quarantine Reading List</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/update-and-reading-list.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Quarantine Reading List" /><published>2020-04-06T10:05:21+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-06T10:05:21+01:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/update-and-reading-list</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/04/06/update-and-reading-list.html">&lt;p&gt;I currently have a piece in the pipeline that follows up on my &lt;a href=&quot;/education/2020/02/05/what-i-learned-dropping-out-of-high-school.html&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;. In it I offer a vision of what higher education could be like, I describe what I have been doing since dropping out of college, and I announce a project that would put my ideas into practice. However, the coronavirus situation has put my plans on hold for now. So you will probably get to read that piece once the circumstances are more auspicious to a project that involves getting people physically together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I might still reconsider, and post it before any of my ideas can feasably, or advisably, be put into practice. If there is anyone out there who is particularly curious about what I’ve been up to, or what I’m planning, you can DM me on Twitter, and I’ll share my draft with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I hope to make the most of the quarantine. In the coming weeks and months, I want to work on a post that examines the role that educational institutions should play, from a societal and civilizational perspective. Some of the key ideas that motivate this line of inquiry are contained in a 1995 book by Neil Postman, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/End-Education-Redefining-Value-School/dp/0679750312&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The End of Education&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and in a piece in The Atlantic by Patrick Collison and Tyler Cowen from last year: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/07/we-need-new-science-progress/594946/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;We Need a New Science of Progress&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postman’s key insight is that the purpose of education is in fact just as important, if not more important, than the method (more on this &lt;a href=&quot;/education/2020/04/06/end-of-education.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). This rings very true to me, since in my own learning, progress seems to have been greatest when I intrisically valued my learning, and found it meaningful. In my experience, the financial cost of the education seems to have no effect on the speed or quality of learning. In a world in which student debt in the US stands at more than $1.6 Trillion, this is quite a striking observation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So while I have a good idea of how education should work, I now want to answer the question of why. To help me with this, I have created reading list of books, papers and blog posts that I plan to go through in the coming weeks and months. Here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;books&quot;&gt;Books&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tyler Cowen, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Great-Stagnation-Low-Hanging-Eventually-eSpecial-ebook/dp/B004H0M8QS/&quot;&gt;The Great Stagnation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tyler Cowen, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Average-Over-Powering-America-Stagnation-ebook/dp/B00C1N5WOI/&quot;&gt;Average Is Over&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tyler Cowen, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Complacent-Class-Self-Defeating-Quest-American/dp/B06XR2W1CM/&quot;&gt;The Complacent Class&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;William Deresiewicz, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Excellent-Sheep-Miseducation-American-Meaningful-ebook/dp/B00GEEB960/&quot;&gt;Excellent Sheep&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francis Fukuyama, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Origins-Political-Order-Prehuman-Revolution/dp/B006QGIQ94/&quot;&gt;The Origins of Political Order&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francis Fukuyama, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/dp/B00LU3YM8C&quot;&gt;Political Order and Political Decay&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mancur Olson, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Rise-Decline-Nations-Stagflation-Rigidities-ebook/dp/B00267SS7W/&quot;&gt;The Rise and Decline of Nations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jared Diamond, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Collapse-Societies-Choose-Fail-Succeed/dp/B00P2QCN2U/&quot;&gt;Collapse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daron Acemoglu and James Robinson, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Why-Nations-Fail-Origins-Prosperity/dp/B007MIXOEC/&quot;&gt;Why Nations Fail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eliezer Yudkowsky, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/s/oLGCcbnvabyibnG9d&quot;&gt;Inadequate Equilibria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert J. Gordon, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Rise-Fall-American-Growth-Standard/dp/B01ITPUXEU/&quot;&gt;The Rise and Fall of American Growth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon Gertner, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Idea-Factory-Great-American-Innovation/dp/0143122797&quot;&gt;The Idea Factory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might also revisit these two:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Deutsch, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Beginning-Infinity-Explanations-Transform-World/dp/B005HTYBCM/&quot;&gt;The Beginning of Infinity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joseph Henrich, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Secret-Our-Success-Evolution-Domesticating/dp/B07B53C56B/&quot;&gt;The Secret of Our Success&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;papersblog-postsother&quot;&gt;Papers/Blog posts/Other&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nicholas Bloom et al, &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.stanford.edu/~chadj/IdeaPF.pdf&quot;&gt;Are Ideas Getting Harder to Find?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pierre Azoulay et al, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w15466.pdf&quot;&gt;Incentives and Creativity: Evidence from the Academic Life Sciences&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay Bhattacharya et al, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w26752.pdf&quot;&gt;Stagnation and Scientific Incentives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dominic Cummings, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dominiccummings.files.wordpress.com/2013/11/20130825-some-thoughts-on-education-and-political-priorities-version-2-final.pdf&quot;&gt;Some thoughts on education and political priorities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dominic Cummings, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dominiccummings.files.wordpress.com/2017/02/201702-effective-action-2-systems-engineering-to-systems-politics.pdf&quot;&gt;The unrecognised simplicities of effective action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LessWrong, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/zhPGbnAhgqFsCDK4C/how-to-fix-academia&quot;&gt;How to fix academia?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LessWrong, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/x2fkoZMuMNhBashH4/academia-as-a-career-option-its-social-value-and&quot;&gt;Academia as a career option, its social value, and alternatives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LessWrong, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/gZgjqrotKyCJR9zGq/why-academic-papers-are-a-terrible-discussion-forum&quot;&gt;Why Academic Papers Are A Terrible Discussion Forum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LessWrong, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/xQ9tMMk3RArodLtDq/intellectual-progress-inside-and-outside-academia&quot;&gt;Intellectual Progress Inside and Outside Academia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eli Dourado, &lt;a href=&quot;https://elidourado.com/blog/move-the-needle-on-progress/&quot;&gt;How do we move the needle on progress?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nintil, &lt;a href=&quot;https://nintil.com/progress-in-progress/&quot;&gt;About the ‘Progress’ in Progress Studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francis Jervis, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.progressstudies.org/2019/08/09/manifesto/&quot;&gt;A Progress Studies Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Archbridge Institute, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@ArchbridgeInst/reflections-on-studying-human-flourishing-and-progress-shared-challenges-and-shared-potential-45f277572f30&quot;&gt;Reflections on Studying Human Flourishing and Progress: Shared Challenges and Shared Potential&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James Fallows, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/1993/12/how-the-world-works/305854/&quot;&gt;How the World Works&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Hamming, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/hamming.html&quot;&gt;You and Your Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Many of these are taken from Patrick Collison’s site, &lt;a href=&quot;https://patrickcollison.com/progress&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://patrickcollison.com/growth&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://patrickcollison.com/fast&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I might also end up drawing on these two lists, also found through Collison’s site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt Clancy, &lt;a href=&quot;http://matt-clancy.com/economics-of-innovation-detailed-reading-list/&quot;&gt;Economics of Innovation: Detailed Reading List&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jasmine Wang, &lt;a href=&quot;https://jasminew.me/post/progress/&quot;&gt;[Normative] Progress Studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">I currently have a piece in the pipeline that follows up on my previous post. In it I offer a vision of what higher education could be like, I describe what I have been doing since dropping out of college, and I announce a project that would put my ideas into practice. However, the coronavirus situation has put my plans on hold for now. So you will probably get to read that piece once the circumstances are more auspicious to a project that involves getting people physically together. Though I might still reconsider, and post it before any of my ideas can feasably, or advisably, be put into practice. If there is anyone out there who is particularly curious about what I’ve been up to, or what I’m planning, you can DM me on Twitter, and I’ll share my draft with you.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What I Learned Dropping Out of High School</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/05/what-i-learned-dropping-out-of-high-school.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What I Learned Dropping Out of High School" /><published>2020-02-05T09:05:21+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-05T09:05:21+00:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/05/what-i-learned-dropping-out-of-high-school</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/05/what-i-learned-dropping-out-of-high-school.html">&lt;h4 id=&quot;i--dropping-out-of-high-school&quot;&gt;I – Dropping out of high school&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point in middle school I started to want to graduate from high school early. I didn’t enjoy school. Most subjects were boring. Lectures were uninspiring and exams stressful. But it was the subjects I enjoyed the most that were the worst. I wanted to become a physicist. And so I liked to read ahead in the math and physics textbooks. But then the lectures became even more boring since they didn’t teach me anything new. And if I made it known that I already knew the material taught, I was usually just told to stay quiet and probably seen as smug by the rest of the class. And so I spent the vast majority of class time sleeping or doodling in the back of the class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s a teacher to do? Send you home until the exam? But then a lot of people would probably learn things on their own, and the teacher would be shown to be useless! Can’t risk that. Learning at a rate any different than the one dictated by the teacher is almost always actively disincentivized. And so I, wanting to know all there is to know about physics as fast as possible, found the situation quite depressing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, I did imagine that college would be different; that the primary motivation in college wouldn’t be grades and exams, but genuine curiosity about the material; that in college you’d be treated as an adult. And so I asked a few times to skip a grade so that I’d get to college faster, but the request was always rejected by the school administrators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time I had reached the end of the equivalent of sophomore year of high-school, I had hatched a new plan. I had seen that the EPFL, a Swiss university, had an entrance exam that allowed people to get admitted even without a high school diploma. I set myself the goal of studying for that exam over the summer, and then try to take it in the fall. It was a very ambitious goal, and I failed miserably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had this bad habit of not telling anyone about my plans. In part because failing at something no one knew I was working on felt much less scary than failing in public, and in part because succeeding at something no one was expecting seemed quite appealing. I lacked the discipline that was required to prepare for the exam, and the fact that I set myself the constraint of having to work in secret didn’t help. I wonder whether, had I told my parents about my plans and sought outside help, I might have been able to do it. I had yet to develop self-discipline, and to realize and value the importance of outside support and accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of a relatively unproductive summer it became clear to me that there was no way I was going to be able to pass that exam. I did, however, start to hatch another plan. I grew up in France, where the high-school diploma, the Baccalauréat, consists of a comprehensive exam over 2 weeks. It’s like the GED in the US, if everyone had to take the GED. And it’s possible to take the Baccalauréat even if one is not enrolled in high school. So the idea was to drop out, try to take the Baccalauréat one year early, and if that failed I could always try again the following year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that dropping out of high-school seems unthinkable at first glance, I couldn’t find any concrete flaws with my plan that would provide a real counterweight to the potential upside I saw – one additional year of my life. So a month and a half into my junior year, (or “Premiere” in France) I dropped out of high school. It was a scary decision to take, and my plan ended up not going the way I had hoped it would, but I still feel proud of the path I chose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks after my last day in a high-school classroom, when registering to take the Baccalauréat exam, I was met with an unpleasant surprise. In France, the French section of the Baccalaureat is taken one year early. In the last year of school, French is then replaced by Philosophy. My plan to finish one year early therefore hinged on the fact that I’d be able to take both the French section and all the other subjects in the same year. And according to my research, that was possible. However, when registering, I discovered that one had to be at least 20 to be allowed to take both in the same year. And so, finally, I had to abandon my ambition of entering university early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I stayed out of school. Which was the right decision. In the first year I ended up doing little to prepare for my Baccalauréat. I did prepare for the French exam, and learned some math and physics. But because the deadline was more than a year away, and because of my poor work ethic, I spent only a minority of my time studying. I progressively realized that the temporary rushes of excitement that usually fueled my learning outside of school weren’t going to cut it this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading a blog post on “fixed mindset” vs “growth mindset,” I also started to realize that at the core of my poor work ethic lied a perverse attitude towards work. In school, I had grown proud of how little I was working while still getting decent grades. I wanted to look smart, both to others and to myself, and so studying became something to avoid as it would be a sign that I wasn’t smart enough to get a good grade with little effort. It also gave me an excuse when I got a bad grade: I didn’t get it because I was dumb, but just because I didn’t study. This also relates to the fear of failing in public I mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting from a fixed to a growth mindset was a slow journey, one I’m still on. But this alone made my dropping out worth it. I progressively learned to value work, discipline and organization. I learned to learn. And I would have never gotten this out of a normal high-school education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the only thing that I got out of these two years. I probably spent the majority of my time on the internet. When I dropped out of high-school, I was far from being fluent in English. But I thought it was important, and so I started watching English speaking TV including American satirical comedy about US politics, and so I got obsessed with US politics, started watching debates, interviews and talks on a variety of political, societal and cultural issues on YouTube. I became an avid reader of The Atlantic, regularly checking if there was any article in their top 5 that I hadn’t read yet. I started listening to English speaking podcasts, read English books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, I still struggled a lot to understand, and constantly had to look up words. But it took me less than a year to get to a point at which I could read long texts without the need to look up any word. In the fall a little over a year after dropping out, I took the SAT and got a 720 on the critical reading section. So by dropping out, and following my interests, I ended up learning a foreign language, which is more than anyone expects from high-school. And while all this may not have prepared me for the Baccalauréat (except for the English section), I cannot say it was wasted time either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my second year, I started to spend an increasing amount of time on preparing for the Baccalauréat. I started doing to-do lists, developed a morning habit, started waking up early, spent days with my laptop and phone hidden under the bed to avoid distraction. And I started making some real progress. On the whole, I probably spent significantly less time preparing for the exams than I would have had I attended high-school. But in the end I got my Baccalauréat with honors (“Mention tres bien”). It turns out, you learn faster reading and actively working on exercises and problems than sitting in a classroom all day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two years of near complete freedom were an almost unique education experience. I wouldn’t necessarily recommend it to everyone, but it did teach me valuable lessons, and allowed me to grow in ways that wouldn’t have been possible had I stayed in school.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;ii--why-we-need-standardized-tests-as-an-alternative-to-college&quot;&gt;II – Why we need standardized tests as an alternative to college&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With my high school diploma successfully obtained, I enrolled at Fordham University. In college however, my dream of an educational institution that would treat students like adults were quickly dashed. I’m not sure why I had this idealized vision of academia. The fact that Fordham University had a policy of mandatory attendance for most classes, and a substantial common core, didn’t help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But those classes with interesting material, non-mandatory attendance, and a good professor lowered my esteem for academia even more. In those cases, I typically didn’t attend lectures, just going when there was an exam, and learned on my own, often with the help of free online educational material that was far superior to anything I was getting at Fordham. So I was left wondering, why a class that would only require me to take a few exams cost more than $5k?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another episode, among countless others, that left me wondering if college was in fact about learning occurred when I tested out of two introductory programming classes, by doing the final assignment of the second class. One thing I learned on that occasion was that to learn what I had taught myself using free online tutorials over a few months when I was 15, at Fordham one had to pay more than $10k.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second thing I discovered was that when learning something outside of University, it doesn’t deserve credit, as despite being allowed to take upper level computer science classes, I didn’t receive the credits for the introductory classes. Had I paid to learn C++ at another university, I certainly would have received transfer credits, but I learned it for free, so it didn’t really count.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end I did come to the conclusion that Universities were in fact not mainly about learning. Rather, they are the arena of a zero-sum competition for signaling that favors the wealthy and hurts society as a whole. And I did end up dropping out after my sophomore year. But that is &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2018/11/23/the-case-for-dropping-out-of-college/&quot;&gt;another story&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rapidly started to wish that an exam like the Baccalauréat existed for college. Why not? It should be possible to test everything learned in college in two weeks or less. Math would be easy. Simply give a student the final exams of all 10-15 math classes a math major typically has to take. It may seem like testing a subject like philosophy might be harder, but it is far from impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have exam takers write, on their own time, ~5-10 high quality essays. An examinator is then tasked with asking questions, discussing and challenging the arguments of the essays. This, combined with a regular standardized test on general philosophical knowledge and the writing of a few essays under examination conditions should be enough to demonstrate someone’s knowledge and understanding of philosophy, as well as reasoning and writing abilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why doesn’t this exist? By making these exams so difficult that at least a substantial minority of Ivy League graduates fail at them, they could become an equal or even superior sign of subject knowledge, intelligence and conscientiousness as a degree from a top University. I can see how the organization creating such exams could offer money to recent Ivy League graduates who pass the exam, and then anonymously publicize the results as a marketing ploy. Is it because passing such an exam rather than going the University route would &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.econlib.org/archives/2006/02/what_does_educa_1.html&quot;&gt;signal non-conformity&lt;/a&gt;? Surely that wouldn’t be worth an almost 2 orders of magnitude difference in price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe it boils down to a chicken and egg problem. Anyone trying to create such an exam would be hard pressed to find people who need such an exam. Non-college graduates who learned a subject up to a University graduate level, and now would be willing to pay to get their effort rewarded with a degree-substitute they can show employers, are pretty rare. But at the same time, the reason why no one learns a subject up to a college graduate level outside of college, is because there is no obvious path to a degree or degree-substitute and self-learning therefore becomes a seemingly pointless effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguments against college abound. 40% of University students never end up graduating, University has gotten more and more expensive, student debt has ballooned, and that while many students get degrees in subjects of little practical value. “We need more apprenticeships!” they say. I agree with these points, and have made them myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is one aspect of the disaster that is today’s higher education system that is missed by many: The fact that college is not only failing those who struggle to keep up, or have no inherent desire to learn the things taught in college, it is also failing many bright, curious and hard-working students for whom a different, more self-directed learning environment would be much more effective and enjoyable. They deserve better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike many, Peter Thiel does pay attention to those talented college students who might be better off outside of college. And thus he offers Thiel Fellowships for students to drop-out of college and start a company. But is this really the best way to demonstrate that bright young adults shouldn’t go to college? Wouldn’t getting students to drop out and then have them learn Physics or Mathematics to a graduate level, or write Philosophy papers, doing research, become a writer, prove the point much better?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An exam like I discussed above could provide the empirical evidence. The reckoning for Universities will come when it becomes evident that they are bad even at what they are supposed to do best, getting talented students to learn academic subjects. But it is hard to create an innovative alternative to college if there is no objective measure to compare it to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might even be possible that companies would end up preferring applicants having passed such an exam to those with a college degree. It is unclear what the difference in rigor between different degree programs and universities is. Even the difficulty experienced by two students in the same University pursuing the same degree can vary significantly. Did one manage to get all easy professors? Impossible to know. A challenging and comprehensive test, identical for all, would solve this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is one crucial question that I haven’t addressed yet. And that is the question of how and where people would study for such exams. It can be extremely hard to learn on your own, especially when all one is used to is the traditional model of education. And despite the fact that I have more experience than most with self-teaching, I still often find it quite difficult. And living with one’s parents for a few years just learning probably doesn’t sound like an attractive proposition to the vast majority of young adults.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will address this in my next post (or the one after that), along with what I’ve been doing since dropping out of college, and what my plans are now.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">I – Dropping out of high school At some point in middle school I started to want to graduate from high school early. I didn’t enjoy school. Most subjects were boring. Lectures were uninspiring and exams stressful. But it was the subjects I enjoyed the most that were the worst. I wanted to become a physicist. And so I liked to read ahead in the math and physics textbooks. But then the lectures became even more boring since they didn’t teach me anything new. And if I made it known that I already knew the material taught, I was usually just told to stay quiet and probably seen as smug by the rest of the class. And so I spent the vast majority of class time sleeping or doodling in the back of the class.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Simple $15k Experiment to Prove That College Is a Sham</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/04/a-simple-experiment.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Simple $15k Experiment to Prove That College Is a Sham" /><published>2020-02-04T09:37:43+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-04T09:37:43+00:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/04/a-simple-experiment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/04/a-simple-experiment.html">&lt;p&gt;Take a group of 20 college students taking a four credit introductory physics class. Let’s assume they pay the average tuition at a non-profit college of $34,740 in 2017, and each student takes 16 credits per semester. This would mean that each student is paying $4,342.5 for this class, and the total cost of the class is $86,850¹.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-experiment&quot;&gt;The Experiment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Divide the class randomly into 5 groups of 4 students. No lectures. Only 4 two-hour exams. Every group has the possibility to take one exam every week, when they feel they are ready. The catch, if anyone in a group fails the exam, the whole group has to retake it. Every member of the first group to complete all exams, receives $500, the members of the second group, $250, the third, $150, and the members of the last two groups, each receive $50 once all exams are completed. Furthermore, each member of the group with the best group grade point average receives $300, the second best $200 and the third best $100.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the semester, all students are pointed toward all the introductory physics material that MIT has put online together with video of all their lectures, Khan Academy’s physics videos as well as one of the many free online physics textbooks. If that is not enough, each group also has access to 20 hours with a professional tutor. That shouldn’t be necessary, as the strongest students in any group have a great incentive to help the others out. But just in case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cost&quot;&gt;Cost&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cost of all this? All the prize money amounts to $6,400. The cost of proctoring a two-hour exam every week for 13 weeks? Given a proctor paid $50 an hour as well as an examination space fitting up to 20 people rented at $50 an hour, this would amount to a total of $2,600 for the entire semester. For a grader paid $25 an hour (average TA salary: $11/hour), taking 30 minutes to grade one exam, this would amount to a total of $1,000 to grade all exams. Finally, a total of 100 hours of tutoring (20h/group) from a professional tutor, at a rate of $50 an hour, would cost a total of $5,000. I proceed on the assumption that creating the exams would entail no extra costs. All one needs is a large enough database of problems, and creating an exam becomes as simple as picking a few problems out at random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;in-summary&quot;&gt;In summary:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prize money: $6,400&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exam proctoring: $2,600&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grading: $1,000&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Extra tutoring: $5,000&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;TOTAL: $15,000&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing this would, therefore, cost less than 20% of the average cost of an introductory physics class. It should be noted that, if the students are the ones paying for this, the prize money is actually only redistributed on a meritocratic basis. The cost of the class without the prize money is $8,600 or less than 10% of the average cost of this college class. This amounts to $430 per student. It should also be noted that many of the estimates I make here do seem high, and if done efficiently, such a system could be even cheaper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;hypothesis&quot;&gt;Hypothesis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My hypothesis is that with this setup, students would learn just as well, and probably better, than in the traditional setting. There are a couple of reasons for this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I believe that free online educational material is almost always superior in teaching a subject matter compared to traditional, live, in-person lecture. Even just a video of a lecture is more useful than the lecture itself, since a video can be replayed at will at any time, played faster, paused… Furthermore, it is online that “The state of the art in explanation of a concept” is advanced, not in university, as online, there is competition between content creators for the best explanation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There is a financial incentive for working hard and helping one’s group mates.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inter-group competition. This can be a great motivator. As Jonathan Haidt argues in “The Righteous Mind”, human psychology has evolved for inter-group competition.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Both the tutoring between students and the tutoring from an outside professional tutor can greatly help learning. A 1984 study found that students taught one-on-one performed better than 98% of their peers taught in a regular classroom.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peer pressure. Those who are most motivated to win will pressure those who are less motivated to work harder.
One important assumption here is that the main value college provides with respect to learning is just the incentive it creates for learning. And the only incentive college provides is grades and the diploma. If something is “on the test”, students figure out a way to learn it, even if the professor was completely unintelligible during lecture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implications&quot;&gt;Implications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If my hypothesis is correct, it may have wide-ranging implications. The most important of which is that the college affordability crisis could be solved by simply embracing modern technology and by changing the incentive structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would also be further evidence that the main value college provides is not learning, and would lend credence to Bryan Caplan’s argument in “The Case Against Education” that it is mostly about signaling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of variables in this experiment that can be played around with. The size and the distribution of the prizes, the size of each group, the number of exams… My proposed distribution of prizes puts a greater emphasis on speed than performance. That is because I believe that most students, if properly incentivized, could learn much faster than they are doing today. And theoretically, if students finish one class before the end of one semester, they could start a new one right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students do not only spend a lot of money on college. They also spend a lot of time. Making college cheaper should be just as much about lowering the price tag as about reducing the opportunity cost of spending months and years not working. This being said, my proposed prize distribution is probably not the most optimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another variable that would be interesting to look at is the composition of the groups. It is important for there to be not too much disparity between groups, so that they remain competitive, and all groups have a shot at winning. However, it is important for there to be some disparity, but not too much, within a group, so that the stronger students have the opportunity to help those struggling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There also needs to be a process by which a group can expel a student if they are really not pulling their weight. This, however, would need to carry a penalty, like making it impossible for the group to win anything just for finishing all exams, or taking a percentage of any other of their winning. This should only be a last resort though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, this model can be adapted to any class. There are free online resources available for almost any subject matter. Grading for some classes might be a little more expensive than for introductory physics, particularly for classes involving lots of writing. But, if this experiment is successful, then there is little doubt that universities are astonishingly inefficient at teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I challenge any university to try this out. I doubt students would be opposed, so why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;¹ 20 students, $34,740 for one year, 32 credits per year and a four credit class: 20*34,740*4/32=$86,850&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally published on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@sknoche/a-simple-15k-experiment-to-prove-that-college-is-a-scam-5a60adf3ed24&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt; in 2018.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">Take a group of 20 college students taking a four credit introductory physics class. Let’s assume they pay the average tuition at a non-profit college of $34,740 in 2017, and each student takes 16 credits per semester. This would mean that each student is paying $4,342.5 for this class, and the total cost of the class is $86,850¹.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Case for Dropping Out of College</title><link href="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/04/the-case-for-dropping-out-of-college.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Case for Dropping Out of College" /><published>2020-02-04T09:30:22+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-04T09:30:22+00:00</updated><id>https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/04/the-case-for-dropping-out-of-college</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thememeticist.com/education/2020/02/04/the-case-for-dropping-out-of-college.html">&lt;p&gt;During the summer, my father asked me whether the money he’d spent to finance my first few years at Fordham University in New York City, one of the more expensive private colleges in the United States, had been well spent. I said yes, which was a lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I majored in computer science, a field with good career prospects, and involved myself in several extracurricular clubs. Since I managed to test out of some introductory classes, I might even have been able to graduate a year early—thereby producing a substantial cost savings for my family. But the more I learned about the relationship between formal education and actual learning, the more I wondered why I’d come to Fordham in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can read the whole piece on &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2018/11/23/the-case-for-dropping-out-of-college/&quot;&gt;Quillette&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Samuel Knoche</name></author><summary type="html">During the summer, my father asked me whether the money he’d spent to finance my first few years at Fordham University in New York City, one of the more expensive private colleges in the United States, had been well spent. I said yes, which was a lie.</summary></entry></feed>